<!--

File produced by pipelineRunner package (for JATS 2 SCJATS with pipeline SCJATS)
At: 2025-05-21T06:10:50.161Z

Version        : 1.16.1
Last update    : 2024-08-27
Modified by    : dunnm

-->
<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Europace</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Europace</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">europace</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Europace</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1099-5129</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2092</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40314213</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12092914</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/europace/euaf091</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">euaf091</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Meta-Analysis</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00200</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>Eurheartj/1</subject><subject>Eurheartj/7</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Multiparametric models for predicting major arrhythmic events in Brugada syndrome: a systematic review and critical appraisal</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6894-648X</contrib-id><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>Daniel A</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Cardiology, Hospital de Santa Cruz</institution>, <addr-line>Lisbon</addr-line>, <country country="PT">Portugal</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9055-9267</contrib-id><name><surname>Lambiase</surname><given-names>Pier D</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Institute of Cardiovascular Science, University College London</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Barts Heart Centre, St Bartholomew&#x02019;s Hospital, Barts Health NHS Trust</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0621-8241</contrib-id><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>Richard J</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Barts Heart Centre, St Bartholomew&#x02019;s Hospital, Barts Health NHS Trust</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff>
<institution>William Harvey Research Institute, Faculty of Medicine and Dentistry, Queen Mary University of London</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0615-9525</contrib-id><name><surname>Cappato</surname><given-names>Riccardo</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Arrhythmia and Clinical Electrophysiology Center, IRCCS, MultiMedica</institution>, <addr-line>Milan</addr-line>, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3729-3137</contrib-id><name><surname>Adrag&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>Pedro</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Department of Cardiology, Hospital de Santa Cruz</institution>, <addr-line>Lisbon</addr-line>, <country country="PT">Portugal</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Department of Cardiology, Hospital da Luz</institution>, <addr-line>Lisbon</addr-line>, <country country="PT">Portugal</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9141-9883</contrib-id><name><surname>Provid&#x000ea;ncia</surname><given-names>Rui</given-names></name><aff>
<institution>Barts Heart Centre, St Bartholomew&#x02019;s Hospital, Barts Health NHS Trust</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff>
<institution>Institute of Health Informatics Research, University College London</institution>, <addr-line>222 Euston Road, London NW1 2DA</addr-line>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><xref rid="euaf091-cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><xref rid="FN01" ref-type="author-notes"/><!--r.providencia@ucl.ac.uk--></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="euaf091-cor1">Corresponding author. Tel: +44 (0) 20 7679 2000. <italic toggle="yes">E-mail address</italic>: <email>r.providencia@ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="FN01" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> none declared.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2025-05-02"><day>02</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>02</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>euaf091</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="corrected-typeset"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the European Society of Cardiology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="euaf091.pdf"/><related-article related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" id="RA1" xlink:href="10.1093/europace/euaf092"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s1"><title>Aims</title><p>Despite several risk models to predict major arrhythmic events (MAE) in Brugada syndrome (BrS) having been developed, reproducibility and methodology remain a concern. Our aim was to assess the quality of model development and validation, and determine the discriminative performance of available models.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods and results</title><p>Electronic databases (Medline, Embase, and Central) were searched through September/2024 for studies developing or validating multivariable prediction models for MAE in BrS. Methodological quality and risk of bias (RoB) were assessed using the Critical Appraisal and Data Extraction for Systematic Reviews of Prediction Modelling Studies (CHARMS) checklist and the Prediction Model Risk of Bias Assessment (PROBAST) Tool. Pooled random-effects c-statistics were obtained for each model. A total of 16 studies, including 11 unique multivariable scores, were included. All models had domains classified as high RoB. Common sources of bias were inappropriate inclusion/exclusion criteria, predictor selection, low number of events and underreporting of performance measures. Pooled c-statistics among patients without previous MAE showed good performance for Brugada-Risk [AUC 0.81, 95% confidence interval (CI) 0.71&#x02013;0.91; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 64%; three studies], fair for PAT (AUC 0.79, 95% CI 0.45&#x02013;1.12; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 95%; two studies), Delise (AUC 0.77, 95% CI 0.72&#x02013;0.81, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 39%, three studies), and Sieira (AUC 0.73, 95% CI 0.64&#x02013;0.82; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 64%; five studies), and moderate for Shanghai (AUC 0.69, 95% CI 0.61&#x02013;0,76; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 13%; three studies).</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Currently available multiparametric models for prediction of MAE in BrS have important shortcomings in model development and inadequate evaluation. Further validation of current models in external cohorts is required before safe transition to clinical practice.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><p>
<fig position="anchor" id="euaf091-euaf091_ga"><label>Graphical Abstract</label><graphic xlink:href="euaf091_ga" position="float"/></fig>
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Brugada syndrome</kwd><kwd>Sudden cardiac death</kwd><kwd>Ventricular arrhythmia</kwd><kwd>Risk scores</kwd><kwd>PROBAST</kwd><kwd>Methods</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>UCL BHF Research Accelerator</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>AA/18/6/34223</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>NIHR</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="DOI">10.13039/501100000272</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>NIHR129463</award-id><award-id>UKRI/ERC/HORIZON 10103153</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="euaf091-s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Brugada syndrome (BrS), first described as a clinical entity in 1992, is an inherited cardiac channelopathy characterized by atypical right bundle branch block with coved ST-segment elevation (&#x0003e;2&#x02005;mm) in the right precordial leads (Type 1 pattern) and increased risk of ventricular tachycardia (VT), ventricular fibrillation (VF), and sudden cardiac death (SCD).<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> This pattern arises in the context of a structurally normal heart and can occur either spontaneously or be induced by fever or exposure to sodium channel-blocking drugs.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> According to current guidelines, BrS is diagnosed in patients presenting either with a spontaneous type 1 pattern or with a drug-induced type 1 along with additional clinical features, (including history of arrhythmic syncope, VT/VF, aborted SCD, family history of BrS, or arrhythmic SCD), provided phenocopies have been excluded.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p><p>Despite most patients being asymptomatic at diagnosis, in some series up to 10% may develop life-threatening ventricular arrhythmias or sudden death during follow-up periods of up to 10 years.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B4" ref-type="bibr">4&#x02013;6</xref></sup></p><p>Major arrhythmic events (MAE) in patients with BrS include SCD, sustained VT/VF, and appropriate implantable cardioverter-defibrillators (ICD) shocks. Identifying patients at risk for MAE is of utmost importance for preventing these ominous outcomes. Although ICD indication is well defined as a Class I recommendation in secondary prevention of SCD, risk stratification is particularly challenging in asymptomatic patients due to low event rates and conflicting evidence, with no single variable able to accurately predict arrhythmic events.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B5" ref-type="bibr">5&#x02013;7</xref></sup></p><p>A multivariable prediction model for MAE in BrS, providing accurate risk estimates for individual patients, would allow for the better selection of appropriate candidates for ICD in primary prevention. Over the past years, numerous models have been proposed to address this question.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B8" ref-type="bibr">8&#x02013;11</xref></sup> However, concerns remain regarding their development, which is based on relatively small retrospective studies with low number of events and limited validation in external cohorts.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> This is, in fact, similar to other inherited cardiac conditions such as idiopathic VF, early repolarization syndrome and long QT, where temporal and geographical variations in syndrome definitions, low incidence in the general population, and low event rates, even among high-risk patients, have made many risk models prone to significant bias and unsuitable for routine use.</p><p>Previous systematic reviews on BrS addressed this issue but were limited by either a lack or minimal critical appraisal of development methodology, or by a non-comprehensive bibliographic database search strategy.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> The aim of this systematic review of studies describing the development or external validation of multiparametric models for predicting MAE in BrS patients was to (i) critically appraise the methodology utilized in model development, and assessing the risk of bias and (ii) provide a comprehensive assessment of the discriminative power of each individual model in predicting MAE.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="euaf091-s2"><title>Methods</title><p>This systematic review was conducted in accordance with the Preferred Reported Items for Systematic Reviews and Meta-analyses (PRISMA) guidelines.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> The protocol was registered in the international prospective register of systematic reviews (PROSPERO, CRD42024586543).</p><sec id="euaf091-s2.1"><title>Search strategy and selection criteria</title><p>We performed a systematic search of three electronic databases (MEDLINE, EMBASE, and CENTRAL) 16/09/2024, using (but not limited) the following key search words: &#x02018;Brugada syndrome&#x02019;, &#x02018;prediction&#x02019;, &#x02018;risk model&#x02019;, &#x02018;score&#x02019;, &#x02018;sudden cardiac death&#x02019;, &#x02018;ventricular fibrillation&#x02019;, and &#x02018;ventricular tachycardia&#x02019;. The full search strategy is presented in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>, <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref></italic>. Reference lists of potentially eligible studies were searched for additional sources of information. No start date or language restrictions were applied. Studies were considered suitable if they (i) developed or externally validated a clinical multiparametric score to predict MAE in BrS patients, as defined by the occurrence of SCD, sustained VT/VF, or appropriate ICD shocks and (ii) included adult (&#x02265;18 years old) patients. Only full-text articles were included, and studies developing models based on artificial intelligence (AI) alone were not considered due to lack of traceability of the predictors used (i.e. models with no clear information on included variables and their weighting). Two investigators (D.G. and R.P.) independently screened and selected potentially eligible studies based on title and abstract. Final eligibility was decided after evaluation of full-text publications. All disagreements were resolved via discussion or through the involvement of a third referee (P.A.).</p></sec><sec id="euaf091-s2.2"><title>Data extraction and quality assessment</title><p>Data extraction was undertaken independently by two investigators (D.G. and R.P.) based on the Critical Appraisal and Data Extraction for Systematic Reviews of Prediction Modelling Studies checklist (CHARMS), and all disagreements were resolved via discussion, or through the involvement of a third referee (P.A.).<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> A standardized form was used to extract the following information from each study: (i) study design, number of events, outcome definition, and follow-up; (ii) baseline characteristics of the participants (age, sex, spontaneous Brugada pattern type 1, prior syncope, family history of SCD, previous aborted SCD or ventricular arrhythmia, genetic testing, electrophysiological study); (iii) information on predictors and model development; and (iv) information on model discrimination, calibration and validation (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>, <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref></italic>).<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup></p><p>Following data extraction, a pair of reviewers (D.G. and R.P.) independently assessed study methodological quality according to the Prediction Model Risk of Bias Assessment Tool (PROBAST).<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> PROBAST is a tool designed to assess the risk of bias and concerns about applicability of studies in which a multiparametric diagnostic or prognostic model is developed or validated. The assessor evaluates the risk of bias based on four domains of signalling questions: (i) the number and characteristics of participants, (ii) the definition of predictors, (iii) the definition and assessment of outcomes, and (iv) model analysis and performance measures (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>, <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref></italic>).<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Models scoring &#x02018;high risk of bias&#x02019; in at least one domain were considered as overall high risk. All disagreements were resolved via discussion, or through the involvement a third referee (P.A.).</p></sec><sec id="euaf091-s2.3"><title>Data synthesis and analysis</title><p>Data were synthesized if reported in at least two included studies. Continuous variables were presented as mean and standard deviation (SD) or medians and interquartile range (IQR), when appropriate. The outcome of interest was MAE, as previously defined. Pooled discriminative power of each model, as assessed by the reported c-statistics (AUC) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CI), were used as summary statistics and were calculated using both the DerSimonian and Laird random-effects and fixed-effects model. When the 95% CI were not reported, we estimated them based on the size of the population and number of events.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Heterogeneity across studies was assessed by <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> using Cochran&#x02019;s Q test, where values of less than 25, 50, and 75% were regarded as evidence of low, moderate, and high levels of heterogeneity, respectively.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Pooled c-statistics values between 1 and 0.9 were considered &#x02018;excellent&#x02019;, 0.9 and 0.8 &#x02018;good&#x02019;, 0.8 and 0.7 &#x02018;fair&#x02019;, 0.7 and 0.6 &#x02018;poor&#x02019;, and 0.6&#x02013;0.5 &#x02018;failed&#x02019;.</p><p>The primary analysis was individual model performance for predicting MAE in patients in primary prevention (i.e. without prior VT/VF or aborted SCD), as there is consensus on the indication for secondary prevention ICD in BrS (Class of recommendation I, level of evidence C).<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Studies included in this analysis were those that either excluded patients with prior VF/aborted SCD from the entire derivation or validation cohort, or provided subgroup analyses that omitted these patients. A subsequent analysis including results for both primary and secondary prevention BrS was performed. Analyses were undertaken using the R version 4.3.2 (packages: &#x02018;meta&#x02019;, &#x02018;ggplot2&#x02019;, and &#x02018;shiny&#x02019;).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="euaf091-s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="euaf091-s3.1"><title>Study selection and characteristics</title><p>A total of 3651 records were identified through database searching. Following exclusion of duplicates and screening, 31 studies were identified for full-text review, and further 15 were subsequently excluded (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>, <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S3</xref></italic>).</p><p>Overall, 16 different records published between 2010 and 2024 were included in the final analysis (<italic toggle="yes">Figure <xref rid="euaf091-F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></italic>).<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B8" ref-type="bibr">8&#x02013;11</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B20" ref-type="bibr">20&#x02013;31</xref></sup> There was full agreement between investigators (D.G. and R.P.) on the eligibility of the selected studies. A summary of the main characteristics is presented in <italic toggle="yes">Table <xref rid="euaf091-T1" ref-type="table">1</xref></italic>. Briefly, study types included model development, alone (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4, 25.0%) or with external validation of the new and/or existing models (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6, 37.5%), and external validation only (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6, 37.5%).</p><fig position="float" id="euaf091-F1" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA flowchart.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="euaf091f1" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="euaf091-T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Study, model, and analysis details for included studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis type (distinguishing feature of model from others developed in same study)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Derivation model name</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">For external validations, reference for model development study if different from listed study (model name, if applicable)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of patients</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outcome</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of events (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1) Honarbakhh (2021)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BRUGADA-RISK</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 &#x000b1; 4.0 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 (10.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2) Kawada (2018)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996&#x02013;2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.7 (39.7&#x02013;142.1) months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (10.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3) Delise (2010)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delise model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (20&#x02013;67) months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (5.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4) Sieira (2017)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1992&#x02013;2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.7 &#x000b1; 57.2 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (8.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">(5) Subramanian (2019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subramanian model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007&#x02013;2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.3 (55.7&#x02013;97.1) months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (12.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kawazoe model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">India</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007&#x02013;2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.3 (55.7&#x02013;97.1) months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (12.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">(6) Lee (2022)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hong Kong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 &#x000b1; 55 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (12.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delise model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hong Kong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 &#x000b1; 55 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (12.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hong Kong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 &#x000b1; 55 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (12.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Okamura model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hong Kong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 &#x000b1; 55 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (12.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BRUGAGA-RISK score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hong Kong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 &#x000b1; 55 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (12.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Letsas model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hong Kong</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1997&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 &#x000b1; 55 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (12.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">(7) Letsas (2019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Letsas model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 &#x000b1; 3.5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 &#x000b1; 3.5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delise model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 &#x000b1; 3.5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Okamura model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Greece</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6 &#x000b1; 3.5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.3)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8) Shinohara (2020)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shinohara model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002&#x02013;2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 &#x000b1; 48 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (3.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9) Okamura (2015)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Okamura model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996&#x02013;2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 &#x000b1; 49 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (11.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10) Kawazoe (2016)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kawazoe model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2001&#x02013;2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.8 &#x000b1; 49.0 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (17.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">(11) Rattanawong (2023)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAT score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 &#x000b1; 4.1 y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (51.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAT score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 &#x000b1; 6.9 y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (9.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 &#x000b1; 6.9 y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (9.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BRUGAGA-RISK score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 &#x000b1; 6.9 y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (9.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 &#x000b1; 6.9 y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (9.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">(12) Probst (2021)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1613</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 &#x000b1; 4.7 y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (4.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1993&#x02013;2016</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">461</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4 &#x000b1; 4.1 y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (5.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">(13) Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Ma&#x000f1;ero (2022)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">831</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 &#x000b1; 4.7 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (5.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">831</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 &#x000b1; 4.7 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (5.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delise model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1998&#x02013;2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">831</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2 &#x000b1; 4.7 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (5.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(14) Chow (2021)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004&#x02013;2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1 &#x000b1; 2.8 y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (11.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15) Delini&#x000e8;re (2019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">International</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclear</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (39.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">(16) Kamakura (2024)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAT score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002&#x02013;2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.8 &#x000b1; 66.1 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (13.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BRUGAGA-RISK score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002&#x02013;2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.8 &#x000b1; 66.1 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (13.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002&#x02013;2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.8 &#x000b1; 66.1 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (13.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2002&#x02013;2015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VA/SCD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.8 &#x000b1; 66.1 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (13.1)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p>Values reported as numbers and percentages, mean &#x000b1; standard deviation or median (interquartile range), as appropriate.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn2"><p>D, derivation; EV, external validation; IV, internal validation; NR, not reported; SCD, sudden cardiac death; VA, ventricular arrhythmia.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Among the included studies, a total of 11 unique multivariable prediction models for MAE in BrS were either developed and/or externally validated. In all cases, data derived from existing registries or retrospective cohorts including patients from 1992 up to 2020. The number of participants in each study varied from 103 to 1613 (median 269) and the rate of events ranged from 3.6% to 51.1% during a mean follow-up of 3.3 to 10.2 years. The mean patient age was 41&#x02013;52 years, and 58&#x02013;99% were males. The incidence of spontaneous type 1 pattern was 13&#x02013;81%, and 12&#x02013;58% had history of syncope except in one study in which all symptomatic patients were excluded.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Electrophysiological study and genetic testing were not performed routinely in most reports. Patients with a history of VT/VF or aborted SCD were excluded from 6 out of the 16 (37.5%) of the derivation and/or external validation cohorts.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B22" ref-type="bibr">22&#x02013;25</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> The baseline patients&#x02019; characteristics are depicted in <italic toggle="yes">Table <xref rid="euaf091-T2" ref-type="table">2</xref></italic>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="euaf091-T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of the patients included</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analysis type (distinguishing feature of model from others developed in same study)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">For external validations, reference for model development study if different from listed study</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male sex</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior syncope</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family history of SCD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spontaneous Brugada type 1</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive EPS study</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive genetic testing</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous aborted SCD/VF</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1) Honarbakhh (2021)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8 &#x000b1; 13.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">790 (71.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">204 (58.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">235 (21.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">388 (35.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128/402 (31.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175/731 (23.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2) Kawada (2018)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (36&#x02013;56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">374 (95.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (25.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (13.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">311 (79.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/167 (13.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (5.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3) Delise (2010)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (33&#x02013;54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">258 (81)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">174 (54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96/245 (39.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4) Sieira (2017)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1 &#x000b1; 17.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">233 (58.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (27.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">184 (46.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (19.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72/365 (19.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53/215 (25.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (5.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">(5) Subramanian (2019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (35&#x02013;60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (86.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (11.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (32.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (65.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/53 (41.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kawazoe model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (35&#x02013;60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (86.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (11.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (32.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (65.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/53 (41.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">(6) Lee (2022)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9 &#x000b1; 16.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508 (92.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">340 (62.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76/112 (67.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/52 (32.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (7.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delise model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9 &#x000b1; 16.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508 (92.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">340 (62.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76/112 (67.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/52 (32.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (7.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9 &#x000b1; 16.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508 (92.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">340 (62.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76/112 (67.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/52 (32.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (7.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Okamura model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9 &#x000b1; 16.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508 (92.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">340 (62.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76/112 (67.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/52 (32.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (7.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BRUGAGA-RISK score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9 &#x000b1; 16.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508 (92.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">340 (62.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76/112 (67.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/52 (32.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (7.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Letsas model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.9 &#x000b1; 16.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508 (92.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">231 (43.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (8.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">340 (62.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76/112 (67.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/52 (32.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (7.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">(7) Letsas (2019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.3 &#x000b1; 13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (77.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (44.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/59 (54.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.3 &#x000b1; 13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (77.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (44.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/59 (54.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delise model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.3 &#x000b1; 13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (77.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (44.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/59 (54.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Okamura model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.3 &#x000b1; 13.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (77.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (33.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (6.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (44.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/59 (54.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8) Shinohara (2020)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 &#x000b1; 13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180 (93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (35)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">155 (80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (26.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9) Okamura (2015)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 &#x000b1; 13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">211 (96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64 (29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">159 (73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (28.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10) Kawazoe (2016)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 &#x000b1; 12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140 (97.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (16.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (25.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 (58.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (24.5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">(11) Rattanawong (2023)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D + IV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.2 &#x000b1; 12.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 (99.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (27.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (16.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (81.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (67.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAT score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5 &#x000b1; 14.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (80.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (18.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (64.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/29 (62.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/44 (38.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5 &#x000b1; 14.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (80.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (18.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (64.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/29 (62.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/44 (38.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BRUGAGA-RISK score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5 &#x000b1; 14.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (80.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (18.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (64.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/29 (62.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/44 (38.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5 &#x000b1; 14.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (80.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (18.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (13.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (64.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/29 (62.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/44 (38.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">(12) Probst (2021)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 &#x000b1; 15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1119 (69.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">421 (26.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">492 (30.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">484 (30.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/569 (37.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">355 (22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66 (4.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 &#x000b1; 13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">356 (77.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (23.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183 (39.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169/461 (36.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">(13) Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Ma&#x000f1;ero (2022)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8 &#x000b1; 13.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">623 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282 (33.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 (46.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383 (46.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126/390 (32.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (3.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8 &#x000b1; 13.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">623 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282 (33.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 (46.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383 (46.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126/390 (32.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (3.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delise model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8 &#x000b1; 13.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">623 (75.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">127 (15.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">282 (33.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">386 (46.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">383 (46.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126/390 (32.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (3.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(14) Chow (2021)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.1 (NR)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (58.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (44.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (32.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (12.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/88 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (11.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15) Delini&#x000e8;re (2019)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.1 &#x000b1; 12.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (91.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/100 (42.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21/80 (26.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 (100.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31/57 (54.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/57 (17.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NR</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">(16) Kamakura (2024)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PAT score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9 &#x000b1; 13.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (95.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (22.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284 (68.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240/324 (74.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (24.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BRUGAGA-RISK score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9 &#x000b1; 13.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (95.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (22.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284 (68.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240/324 (74.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (24.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shanghai score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9 &#x000b1; 13.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (95.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (22.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284 (68.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240/324 (74.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (24.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sieira model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9 &#x000b1; 13.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">395 (95.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (23.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (22.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284 (68.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">240/324 (74.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99 (24.0)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn3"><p>Values reported as numbers and percentages, mean &#x000b1; SD or median (IQR), as appropriate.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn4"><p>D, derivation; EV, external validation; IV, internal validation; NR, not reported; SCD, sudden cardiac death; VA, ventricular arrhythmia, VF, ventricular fibrillation;</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="euaf091-s3.2"><title>Model appraisal&#x02014;PROBAST</title><p>For the &#x02018;participants&#x02019; domain, 3 of 10 model development analyses (30.0%) and 5 (83.3%) of external validation studies were evaluated as high risk of bias (<italic toggle="yes">Figure <xref rid="euaf091-F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></italic>). The main reasons for the high-risk rating were the inclusion of patients with the outcome of interest at baseline (past history of VT/VF or aborted SCD),<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> and use of a non-nested case&#x02013;control study design (in one development and two external validation analyses).<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup></p><fig position="float" id="euaf091-F2" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>PROBAST risk of bias and applicability assessment. (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) Individual risk of bias and applicability assessment; (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Overall PROBAST assessment in model development analyses; (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) Overall PROBAST assessment in external validation studies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="euaf091f2" position="float"/></fig><p>The candidate predictors and those included in the final risk scores are detailed in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>, <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Tables S4</xref></italic> and <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S5</xref></italic>. The most frequent final predictors were history of syncope, spontaneous type 1 Brugada pattern, family history of SCD, early repolarization pattern in inferolateral/peripheral leads, T-peak to T-end duration &#x02265; 100&#x02005;ms, and inducible VT/VF on electrophysiology study (EPS). Most of studies (90.0% of the development and all of the external validation analyses) were rated as unclear or high risk of bias (<italic toggle="yes">Figure <xref rid="euaf091-F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></italic>). The main reasons for this classification were the absence of information regarding blinding for variables assessment,<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B23" ref-type="bibr">23&#x02013;25</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> and the lack of a consistent predictor definition.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup></p><p>There was no information regarding blinding for outcome assessment in any of the studies (<italic toggle="yes">Figure <xref rid="euaf091-F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></italic>). In the Sieira model, a history SCD was included as one of the predictors despite SCD being part of the outcome.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> In the Kawazoe model, the outcome of interest during follow-up was appropriate shocks/VF recordings on ICD, although 44.1% of patients (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 63) did not undergo ICD implantation.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup></p><p>The median number of MAE events utilized for model development analyses was 26 (range 7&#x02013;114), corresponding to an events per candidate variable (EPV) ratio of 3.0 (range: 0.5 to 7.1). According to the PROBAST classification for model development studies, the number of participants with the outcome relative to the number of candidate predictor parameters is considered appropriate if EPV is &#x02265;10.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> A median of 47 events (range: 7&#x02013;75) were included in external validation analyses.</p><p>The most common model development approaches were Cox regression (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8, 80.0%) and logistic regression (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2, 20.0%) (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>, <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S6</xref></italic>). Eight (80.0%) derivation studies employed univariable candidate predictor screening prior to multivariable modelling, whereas predictors for the PAT score were selected based on a systematic review of the literature.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Regression coefficients or predictor weights were included in the final model in six cases. c-Statistic was reported in six (60.0%) model development analyses, of which five were adjusted via bootstrapping or cross-validation, and in all external validation studies as an estimate of model discrimination (see <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>, <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S6</xref></italic>). Calibration measures were reported in four (26.7%) studies.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> In no case was information on the amount and handling of missing data provided.</p><p>Overall, all model development and external validation analyses were rated at high risk of bias in the PROBAST analysis domain. This was mainly due to a high risk of overfitting caused by low sample size relative to number of candidate predictors coupled with data-driven predictor selection methods, lack of correction for optimism in performance measures, or no assessment of model calibration (<italic toggle="yes">Figure <xref rid="euaf091-F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></italic> and <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>, <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref></italic>).</p></sec><sec id="euaf091-s3.3"><title>Model performance</title><p>Of the 11 unique models, c-statistics were reported in at least one independent external validation cohort in 72.7%.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B9" ref-type="bibr">9&#x02013;11</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup> Pooled c-statistics for each multivariable score MAE prediction among primary prevention BrS patients across the derivation and/or external validation cohorts is presented in <italic toggle="yes">Figure <xref rid="euaf091-F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></italic>. Pooled c-statistics in this group of patients showed good performance for Brugada-Risk (AUC 0.81, 95% CI 0.71&#x02013;0.91; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 64%; three studies), fair for PAT (AUC 0.79, 95% CI 0.45&#x02013;1.12; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 95%; two studies), Delise (AUC 0.77, 95% CI 0.72&#x02013;0.81, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 39%, three studies), and Sieira (AUC 0.73, 95% CI 0.64&#x02013;0.82; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 64%; five studies), and moderate for Shanghai (AUC 0.69, 95% CI 0.61&#x02013;0,76; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 13%; three studies). It was not possible to pool data for the Subramanian, Letsas, Okamura, and Kawazoe models as c-statistics were only reported by one study.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> Additionally, for Shinohara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><sup><xref rid="euaf091-B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> and Delini&#x000e8;re <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>,<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> data on model discrimination was not reported. Individual c-statistics among all derivation/validation cohorts are detailed in <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>, <italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S6</xref></italic>.</p><fig position="float" id="euaf091-F3" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Forest plots with pooled c-statistics from individual multivariable models in patients without previous VT/VF or aborted SCD: (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) Sieira model, (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Shanghai score, (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) BRUGADA-RISK, (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) Delise model, and (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) PAT score. SCD, sudden cardiac death; VF, ventricular fibrillation; VT, ventricular tachycardia.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="euaf091f3" position="float"/></fig><p>Letsas <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><sup><xref rid="euaf091-B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> externally validated and reported the negative predictive value (NPV) of three different models in patients without a history of cardiac arrest. They found an overall excellent NPV of 96% for the Delise model, 100% for the Sieira score, and 100% for the Okamura model. A PAT score of &#x02265;10 had a very high NPV, 99.5%, among primary prevention BrS patients.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> For those with a Brugada-risk score of 0, freedom from events at 5 years was 98.5%, whilst for patients with 1 risk variable, this ranged between 94.1% and 96.4%.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p><p>When including all available data (i.e. primary and secondary prevention BrS patients), the overall discriminative power improved for PAT (AUC 0.84, 95% CI 0.59&#x02013;1.10, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 98%; two studies), Sieira (AUC 0.79, 95% CI 0.74&#x02013;0.84, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 62%; eight studies), and Shanghai (AUC 0.76, 95% CI 0.72&#x02013;0.81, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> 67%; six studies) (<italic toggle="yes">Figure <xref rid="euaf091-F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></italic>). In this setting, Sieira <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><sup><xref rid="euaf091-B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> reported event-free survival rates at 10 years of 97.2% and 96.4% for patients with scores of 0 and 1, respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="euaf091-F4" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Forest plots with pooled c-statistics from individual multivariable models: (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) Sieira model, (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Shanghai score, (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) BRUGADA-RISK, (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) Delise model, (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) Okamura model, (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>) Kawazoe model, and (<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>) PAT score.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="euaf091f4" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="euaf091-s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this systematic review, we have performed a critical appraisal and pooled analysis of multiparametric clinical scores to predict MAE in BrS. The main findings were as follows:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>(i) A total of 11 unique multivariable risk scores were identified, of which 8 (72.7%) were externally validated by independent groups.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(ii) All the development and/or external validation model analyses were assessed as having an overall high risk of bias, mainly due to inappropriate inclusion/exclusion criteria, predictor selection, low number of events per variable (median 3 EPV), and underreporting of model performance measures.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(iii) Pooled c-statistics for each unique model show an overall high heterogeneity and lower discriminative power than originally reported.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(iv) When applied to patients without previous MAE, Brugada-Risk had the best discriminative power (pooled AUC 0.81).</p></list-item><list-item><p>(v) The performance of Sieira, PAT, and Shanghai models improves in cohorts including primary and secondary prevention BrS patients.</p></list-item></list><p>At present, almost two thirds of patients with BrS are asymptomatic at the time of the diagnosis, and up to 0.2&#x02013;0.6%/year will eventually develop ventricular arrhythmia or SCD as the initial form of presentation.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> General preventive measures, including aggressive treatment of fever, avoiding dehydration and drugs that may induce ST-segment elevation in right precordial leads (Class I anti-arrhythmics, some anaesthetics, and psychotropic drugs), and avoiding recreational substances such as cocaine, cannabis and of excessive alcohol intake are recommended for all patients, as these can exacerbate type 1 pattern and trigger VF.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> A review of cases of 74 cases of &#x02018;drug-induced Brugada syndrome&#x02019; from non-cardiac medications, in which 23 individuals experienced spontaneous VF, was predominantly composed of young adult males, with drug toxicity appearing to play an important role.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup></p><p>However, identifying asymptomatic BrS patients who will develop MAE remains a challenge of current day cardiac electrophysiology and requires individualized patient assessment.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Prior studies have examined the value of routine clinical, electrocardiogram (ECG), EPS, and genetic variables in stratifying arrhythmic risk finding that a combined multiparametric approach may be more effective in predicting outcomes.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> This is of utmost importance, as the decision for ICD implantation must balance the benefits of preventing sudden death in at-risk patients against the rate of inappropriate shocks and long-term device-related complications (including lead-related issues and mortality), which can reach as high as 4&#x02013;6% per year in young populations with inherited arrhythmia syndromes.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B36" ref-type="bibr">36&#x02013;38</xref></sup> Implantable cardiac monitors have been suggested for BrS with unexplained syncope (Class of recommendation IIa, level of evidence C), and utilized for patients where uncertainty exists in the indication for an ICD.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup></p><sec id="euaf091-s4.1"><title>Quality of the assessed models</title><p>As a results of increasing publications on prediction models, health care providers frequently struggle to determine which to use, for whom or in which contexts.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Against this background, the PROBAST tool was developed to specifically examine the risk of bias and applicability of a given diagnostic or prognostic score to the intended population and setting.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> Because PROBAST is not validated for the assessment of AI-derived models, in the work Lee <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>,<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> only the external validation of existing risk scores was considered.</p><p>The major methodological limitations across studies were the use of inappropriate inclusion or exclusion patient criteria, selection of predictors, low number of events, and lack of appropriate internal and external validation of both discrimination and calibration. Specifically, all studies were judged to have an overall high risk of bias, with the majority (56%) also having major concerns regarding applicability. Almost one third of model development analyses and all external validation cohorts included patients with past history of ventricular arrhythmia or cardiac arrest, which may significantly affect the results. This may be particularly misleading, as good performance in external validation does not guarantee generalizability, especially when the population does not align with the intended use or clinical context.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup></p><p>Bias on the outcome and analysis domains was deemed unclear or high for all studies due to small population size and low MAE per candidate predictor ratio, far less than the recommended minimum of 10&#x02013;20 to reduce the probability of model overfitting.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup> Among model development analyses, 40% did not report c-statistic values and 70% lacked any appropriate calibration assessment.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup> Additionally, no information was provided regarding blinding for predictor and outcome assessment, nor was there a description of the amount and/or management of missing data.</p></sec><sec id="euaf091-s4.2"><title>Model performance</title><p>Readily available variables during routine management of BrS patients, such as clinical history (history of syncope and family history of SCD) and ECG findings (spontaneous type 1 Brugada pattern, early repolarization pattern in inferolateral/peripheral leads and T-peak to T-end duration &#x02265; 100&#x02005;ms), were among the most frequently included predictors in the final risk models.</p><p>Taken together, pooled c-statistics for each unique model was rather reasonable to moderate (AUC ranging from 0.74 to 0.84), and high heterogeneity was present in most cases. Interestingly, summary estimates were overall more modest when compared to the ones reported in the original publications. Significant variations in c-statistics and heterogeneity reflect differences in both the baseline characteristics of the population and absolute number of events, hindering the widespread applicability of the models. In this regard, ethnicity, family history, and genetics may play a pivotal role. Compared to white patients, Asians exhibit a higher prevalence of BrS and seemingly a greater incidence of SCD.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref></sup> Further research is required on the performance of these risk stratification models across different ethnicities, and how it compares to the prediction based on SCN5A status<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref></sup> or obtained via polygenic risk scores.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref></sup> While genetic risk stratification is still evolving and requires further evaluation, SCN5A loss-of-function mutations, along with single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) at other loci identified in genome-wide association studies (GWAS), have been variably associated with worse outcomes.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B45" ref-type="bibr">45&#x02013;47</xref></sup> Interestingly, a recent study has proposed a clinical arrhythmic prediction score for patients with an SCN5A loss-of-function variant.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref></sup></p><p>When utilized in primary prevention BrS patients, most models performed worse than initially reported in the primary publications. Nonetheless, they have been found to maintain an excellent NPV when all risk variables are absent (ranging from 96% to 100%). While prediction models may be less helpful than previously though in selecting patients for prophylactic ICD, withholding implantation in those without any of the identified high-risk criteria may still be appropriate.</p></sec><sec id="euaf091-s4.3"><title>Clinical implications</title><p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to systematically assess the quality of the multivariable risk scores predicting MAE in BrS patients. Using a dedicated tool for risk of bias assessment, we have demonstrated that there is significant room for improvement in the methodology of model development, validation, and reporting. Against this background, summary estimates for each predictive model were also provided, for all comers BrS patients, as well as for those in primary prevention.</p><p>Given the caveats in the available evidence, we propose the following key requirements to standardize the reporting and enhance the methodological robustness of future scores: (i) selection of derivation and validation cohorts from multicentre prospective registries using predefined inclusion and exclusion criteria that align with the population for which the model is intended; (ii) consistent syndrome definition (both temporal and geographical); (iii) sample size calculations ensuring an adequate ratio of EPV (&#x0003e;20); (iv) consistent predictors and outcome definitions for all patients and appropriate reporting and handling of any missing data; (v) blinded predictor and outcome assessment; (vi) appropriate internal validation and reporting of the discriminative power (AUC and respective 95% CI) and calibration (e.g. calibration plot); and (vii) external validation in an independent cohort. The added value of a prediction model for selecting BrS patients for prophylactic ICD should ideally be tested against current standard of care in a dedicated clinical outcomes randomized trial. We believe that these recommendations can be extended to different settings and not limited to BrS. In fact, risk models for other inherited cardiac arrhythmic syndromes and genetic cardiomyopathies may also exhibit comparable deficiencies due to the significant challenges associated with their development in the context of evolving definitions, low incidence, and low event rates. A similar methodological appraisal of these risk scores, along with adherence to standardized development criteria, would be valuable for better informing future decision-making and recommendations.</p><p>Recent advances in the understanding of risk stratification and genetic testing in inherited arrhythmic syndromes are expected to enhance the selection of tailored therapies in the near future. The presence of rare SCN5A variants may associate with worse arrhythmic outcomes. It is increasingly recognized that loss-of-function variants in SCN5A are linked to lethal events, highlighting their potential role in improving risk stratification.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref></sup> In the absence of these variants, BrS is considered to be largely polygenic, and with the advent of GWAS, there has been increased focus on SNPs as potential disease modifiers.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> While individual SNPs typically exhibit very small effect sizes in the occurrence of a given phenotype, when combined into polygenic scores, they may provide valuable insights into disease pathophysiology and severity.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref></sup> Additional advances in our understanding of the genotype&#x02013;phenotype correlation will be essential for further refining risk stratification, identifying new therapeutic targets, and introducing gene-specific therapies, which are becoming increasingly available for familial arrhythmogenic conditions.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="euaf091-B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref></sup> The integration of clinical and genetic information will likely soon become the new standard for risk stratification.</p></sec><sec id="euaf091-s4.4"><title>Limitations</title><p>Although this systematic review provides a comprehensive analysis of existing BrS MAE prediction scores, the results should be interpreted considering some limitations. Firstly, we excluded studies in which models were developed using AI. This was due to lack of traceability of the included parameters, and because the PROBAST tool was not validated in this context. A novel risk of bias instrument, the PROBAST-AI, to specifically address these studies, is in its early development.<sup><xref rid="euaf091-B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref></sup> This review did not include risk scores based on genomics, which are currently limited to the research setting as our aim was to assess models containing clinical predictors routinely collected as part of standard care. Thirdly, most of the study cohorts included patients spanning more than two decades, in which the definition of BrS, scientific knowledge on risk predictors, and emerging risk factors such as positive genetic testing have changed dramatically. Incorporation of type-1 Brugada pattern electrocardiograms from second and third intercostal spaces or following exposure to sodium channel-blocker drugs are diagnostic features that were not present in earlier cohorts and account for some of the observed heterogeneity. Finally, while we report pooled AUC for individual models in the primary prevention setting, the limited number of external validation studies and participants warrants cautious interpretation before drawing definitive conclusions. For example, the Brugada-Risk score had excellent discrimination in its original derivation cohort, with an AUC of 0.88, but a more modest performance in subsequent validation cohorts, with AUC of 0.79 and 0.73.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="euaf091-s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This systematic review highlights significant shortcomings in the development and validation of previous MAE prediction models in BrS patients. All models were found to carry a high risk of bias, primarily due to issues in model development and inadequate evaluation, which translates in high heterogeneity. Model performance in the primary prevention setting, and following external validation, was modest to fair for most models. Only one of the assessed scores, Brugada-Risk, had good discrimination when validated externally in primary prevention BrS patients.</p><p>Our findings provide valuable insights for improving the methodology of future research, with the goal of developing a reliable clinical tool to identify patients who may benefit from prophylactic ICD implantation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="sup1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>euaf091_Supplementary_Data</label><media xlink:href="euaf091_supplementary_data.zip"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="euaf091-s6"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>
<xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref> is available at <italic toggle="yes">Europace</italic> online.</p></sec><sec id="euaf091-s7"><title>Funding</title><p>R.P. is supported by the UCL BHF Research Accelerator AA/18/6/34223, National Institute for Health and Care Research grant NIHR129463, and UKRI/ERC/HORIZON 10103153 Aristoteles.</p></sec><sec id="euaf091-s8"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>D.G. and R.P. wrote the review protocol. P.L., R.S., R.C., P.A., and R.P. provided methods and clinical input. D.G. and R.P. accessed and verified the data. D.G. and R.P. prepared the first draft of the manuscript, which was revised by all authors, who subsequently provided input and comments to improve it and prepare the final version. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript, had final responsibility for the decision to submit for publication, and had access to all the data in the study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="euaf091-s9"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data supporting the findings of this study are available within the article and its <xref rid="sup1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material online</xref>.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="euaf091-B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Brugada</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campuzano</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arbelo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarquella-Brugada</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brugada</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Present status of Brugada syndrome: JACC state-of-the-art review</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2018</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>1046</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30139433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Vutthikraivit</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rattanawong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Putthapiban</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sukhumthammarat</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vathesatogkit</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ngarmukos</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Worldwide prevalence of Brugada syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Acta Cardiol Sin</source> &#x000a0;<year>20181</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29844648</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Zeppenfeld</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tfelt-Hansen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Riva</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winkel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Behr</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blom</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>2022 ESC guidelines for the management of patients with ventricular arrhythmias and the prevention of sudden cardiac death</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>3997</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4126</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36017572</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Probst</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veltmann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eckardt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meregalli</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaita</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Long-term prognosis of patients diagnosed with Brugada syndrome: results from the FINGER Brugada syndrome registry</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> &#x000a0;<year>2010</year>;<volume>121</volume>:<fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20100972</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sieira</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brugada</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Brugada syndrome: defining the risk in asymptomatic patients</article-title>. <source>Arrhythm Electrophysiol Rev</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28116080</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Adler</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosso</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chorin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Havakuk</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antzelevitch</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Viskin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk stratification in Brugada syndrome: clinical characteristics, electrocardiographic parameters, and auxiliary testing</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>310</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26341603</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Al-Khatib</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stevenson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>WG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ackerman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bryant</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Callans</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Curtis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>2017 AHA/ACC/HRS guideline for management of patients with ventricular arrhythmias and the prevention of sudden cardiac death</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> &#x000a0;<year>2018</year>;<volume>138</volume>:<fpage>e272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>391</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29084731</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Honarbakhsh</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Providencia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Hernandez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Martin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hunter</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lim</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>WY</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>A primary prevention clinical risk score model for patients with Brugada syndrome (BRUGADA-RISK)</article-title>. <source>JACC Clin Electrophysiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33602402</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sieira</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conte</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ciconte</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chierchia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>GB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casado-Arroyo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baltogiannis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>A score model to predict risk of events in patients with Brugada syndrome</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2017</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1756</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28379344</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kawada</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morita</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antzelevitch</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morimoto</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakagawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watanabe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Shanghai score system for diagnosis of Brugada syndrome: validation of the score system and system and reclassification of the patients</article-title>. <source>JACC Clin Electrophysiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2018</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>724</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29929664</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rattanawong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mattanapojanat</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mead-Harvey</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Der Walt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kewcharoen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kanitsoraphan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Predicting arrhythmic event score in Brugada syndrome: worldwide pooled analysis with internal and external validation</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1358</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37355026</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wei</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>YR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Performance of multiparametric models in patients with Brugada syndrome: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>859771</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35497979</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>McEnteggart</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Estes</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>NAM</given-names> &#x000a0;<suffix>3rd</suffix></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction and prevention of sudden death in the Brugada syndrome</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>1797</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>802</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31586529</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Page</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moher</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bossuyt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boutron</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoffmann</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mulrow</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>PRISMA 2020 explanation and elaboration: updated guidance and exemplars for reporting systematic reviews</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>372</volume>:<fpage>n160</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33781993</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Moons</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KGM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Groot</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JAH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vergouwe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mallett</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Critical appraisal and data extraction for systematic reviews of prediction modelling studies: the CHARMS checklist</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source> &#x000a0;<year>2014</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e1001744</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25314315</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Fernandez-Felix</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Alcalde</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roqu&#x000e9;</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muriel</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zamora</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>CHARMS and PROBAST at your fingertips: a template for data extraction and risk of bias assessment in systematic reviews of predictive models</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Res Methodol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36800933</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Moons</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KGM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolff</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Riley</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whiting</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Westwood</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Collins</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>GS</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>PROBAST: a tool to assess risk of bias and applicability of prediction model studies: explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>170</volume>:<fpage>W1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30596876</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Hanley</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McNeil</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The meaning and use of the area under a receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source> &#x000a0;<year>1982</year>;<volume>143</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7063747</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Higgins</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>G&#x000f8;tzsche</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>J&#x000fc;ni</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moher</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oxman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>The Cochrane collaboration's tool for assessing risk of bias in randomised trials</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source> &#x000a0;<year>2011</year>;<volume>343</volume>:<fpage>d5928</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22008217</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Ma&#x000f1;ero</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baluja</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calvo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Armenta</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Validation of multiparametric approaches for the prediction of sudden cardiac death in patients with Brugada syndrome and electrophysiological study</article-title>. <source>Rev Esp Cardiol (Engl Ed)</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>559</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34479845</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Probst</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goronflot</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anys</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tixier</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Briand</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berthome</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Robustness and relevance of predictive score in sudden cardiac death for patients with Brugada syndrome</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>1687</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33289793</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Subramanian</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Prabhu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rai</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harikrishnan</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sekhar</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pai</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>A novel prediction model for risk stratification in patients with a type 1 Brugada ECG pattern</article-title>. <source>J Electrocardiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31082614</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Shinohara</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takagi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kamakura</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sekiguchi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yokoyama</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aihara</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Risk stratification in asymptomatic patients with Brugada syndrome: utility of multiple risk factor combination rather than programmed electrical stimulation</article-title>. <source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33368830</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Okamura</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kamakura</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morita</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tokioka</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakajima</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wada</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Risk stratification in patients with Brugada syndrome without previous cardiac arrest&#x02014;prognostic value of combined risk factors</article-title>. <source>Circ J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2015</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25428522</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Letsas</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bazoukis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Efremidis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Georgopoulos</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korantzopoulos</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fragakis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Clinical characteristics and long-term clinical course of patients with Brugada syndrome without previous cardiac arrest: a multiparametric risk stratification approach</article-title>. <source>Europace</source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1911</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31638693</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Lee</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ROY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bazoukis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Letsas</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KP</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Comparing the performance of published risk scores in Brugada syndrome: a multi-center cohort study</article-title>. <source>Curr Probl Cardiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>101381</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36058344</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kawazoe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakano</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ochi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takagi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hayashi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uchimura</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Risk stratification of ventricular fibrillation in Brugada syndrome using noninvasive scoring methods</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1947</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27424075</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Delise</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allocca</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marras</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giustetto</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaita</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sciarra</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Risk stratification in individuals with the Brugada type 1 ECG pattern without previous cardiac arrest: usefulness of a combined clinical and electrophysiologic approach</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2011</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20978016</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chow</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leong</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KMW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yazdani</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huzaien</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jones</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shun-Shin</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>A multicenter external validation of a score model to predict risk of events in patients with Brugada syndrome</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34610873</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Delini&#x000e8;re</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Baranchuk</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Giai</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bessiere</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maucort-Boulch</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Defaye</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Prediction of ventricular arrhythmias in patients with a spontaneous Brugada type 1 pattern: the key is in the electrocardiogram</article-title>. <source>Europace</source> &#x000a0;<year>2019</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1400</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31177270</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kamakura</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takagi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Komatsu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shinohara</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aizawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sekiguchi</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Validation of novel risk prediction models in patients with Brugada syndrome: a multicenter study in Japan</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>:<fpage>S1547-5271(24)03321-6</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kamakura</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakazawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aizawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimizu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Long-term prognosis of probands with Brugada-pattern ST-elevation in leads V 1-V 3</article-title>. <source>Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2009</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>503</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19843917</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Eckardt</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Probst</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smits</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JPP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bahr</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ES</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolpert</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schimpf</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Long-term prognosis of individuals with right precordial ST-segment-elevation Brugada syndrome</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> &#x000a0;<year>2005</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642768</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Konigstein</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosso</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Topaz</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Postema</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Friedensohn</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heller</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Drug-induced Brugada syndrome: clinical characteristics and risk factors</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1083</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27131070</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Wijeyeratne</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>YD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tanck</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mizusawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Batchvarov</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barc</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crotti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>SCN5A mutation type and a genetic risk score associate variably with Brugada syndrome phenotype in SCN5A families</article-title>. <source>Circ Genom Precis Med</source> &#x000a0;<year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>E002911</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33164571</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Olde Nordkamp</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Postema</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knops</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Dijk</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Limpens</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilde</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Implantable cardioverter-defibrillator harm in young patients with inherited arrhythmia syndromes: a systematic review and meta-analysis of inappropriate shocks and complications</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source> &#x000a0;<year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26385533</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Tung</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zimetbaum</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Josephson</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A critical appraisal of implantable cardioverter-defibrillator therapy for the prevention of sudden cardiac death</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2008</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18804736</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Sacher</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Probst</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maury</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Babuty</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mansourati</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Komatsu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Outcome after implantation of a cardioverter-defibrillator in patients with Brugada syndrome: a multicenter study-Part 2</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> &#x000a0;<year>2013</year>;<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>1739</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23995538</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bergonti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sacher</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arbelo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crotti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sabbag</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casella</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Implantable loop recorders in patients with Brugada syndrome: the BruLoop study</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38445836</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bergonti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ciconte</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cruzalegui Gomez</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crotti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arbelo</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casella</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Continuous rhythm monitoring with implanted loop recorders in children and adolescents with Brugada syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>921</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39197982</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>la Roi-Teeuw</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Royen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>FS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Hond</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zahra</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Vries</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bartels</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Don't be misled: 3 misconceptions about external validation of clinical prediction models</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024 Aug</year>;<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>111387</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38729274</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Steyerberg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harrell</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>FE</given-names> &#x000a0;<suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borsboom</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eijkemans</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vergouwe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Habbema</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Internal validation of predictive models: efficiency of some procedures for logistic regression analysis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source> &#x000a0;<year>2001</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>774</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470385</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Moons</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Altman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>DG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reitsma</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ioannidis</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macaskill</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steyerberg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>EW</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Transparent reporting of a multivariable prediction model for individual prognosis or diagnosis (TRIPOD): explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source> &#x000a0;<year>2015</year>;<volume>162</volume>:<fpage>W1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25560730</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Nakano</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimizu</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Brugada syndrome as a major cause of sudden cardiac death in Asians</article-title>. <source>JACC Asia</source> &#x000a0;<year>2022</year>;<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>412</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36339362</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Yamagata</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horie</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aiba</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ogawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aizawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ohe</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Genotype-phenotype correlation of SCN5A mutation for the clinical and electrocardiographic characteristics of probands with Brugada syndrome: a Japanese multicenter registry</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source> &#x000a0;<year>2017</year>;<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>2255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28341781</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ishikawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsuda</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hachiya</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dina</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Floriane</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nagata</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Brugada syndrome in Japan and Europe: a genome-wide association study reveals shared genetic architecture and new risk loci</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>2320</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38747976</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Behr</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>ER</given-names></string-name>
</person-group>. <article-title>Brugada syndrome: can polygenic risk scores help the clinician?</article-title> &#x000a0;<source>Eur Heart J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2024</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>2333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38860730</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Tuijnenburg</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Proost</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>VM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thollet</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barc</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Groffen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>AJA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veerman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Long-term prognosis of patients with an SCN5A loss-of-function variant and progressive cardiac conduction disorder or Brugada syndrome</article-title>. <source>Heart Rhythm</source> &#x000a0;<year>2025</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39491571</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Ishikawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kimoto</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mishima</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yamagata</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ogata</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aizawa</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Functionally validated SCN5A variants allow interpretation of pathogenicity and prediction of lethal events in Brugada syndrome</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>2854</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34219138</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Crotti</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brugada</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Calkins</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chevalier</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conte</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Finocchiaro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>G</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>From gene-discovery to gene-tailored clinical management: 25 years of research in channelopathies and cardiomyopathies</article-title>. <source>Europace</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>euad180</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37622577</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Tfelt-Hansen</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Albert</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Merino</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krahn</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marijon</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>E</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Risk stratification of sudden cardiac death: a review</article-title>. <source>Europace</source> &#x000a0;<year>2023</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>euad203</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37622576</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="euaf091-B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Collins</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>GS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dhiman</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andaur Navarro</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ma</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hooft</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reitsma</surname> &#x000a0;<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name> &#x000a0;<etal>et al</etal></person-group> &#x000a0;<article-title>Protocol for development of a reporting guideline (TRIPOD-AI) and risk of bias tool (PROBAST-AI) for diagnostic and prognostic prediction model studies based on artificial intelligence</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source> &#x000a0;<year>2021</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e048008</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>