<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sensors (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sensors (Basel)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sensors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Sensors (Basel, Switzerland)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1424-8220</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40006330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11859573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s25041101</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">sensors-25-01101</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Gravity Data Fusion and Imaging of Geological Structures in the Red River Fault Zone and Adjacent Areas</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Guiju</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Methodology" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Formal analysis" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/">Formal analysis</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; original draft" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Project administration" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project administration</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Funding acquisition" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/">Funding acquisition</role><xref rid="af1-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="c1-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Data curation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><xref rid="af1-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Hongbo</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Data curation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><xref rid="af1-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jiapei</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Data curation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Visualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/">Visualization</role><xref rid="af1-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Weihua</given-names></name><role vocab="credit" vocab-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/" vocab-term="Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref rid="af2-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Leucci</surname><given-names>Giovanni</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-sensors-25-01101"><label>1</label>Key Laboratory of Earthquake Geodesy, Institute of Seismology, CEA, Wuhan 430071, China; <email>13731310544@163.com</email> (F.Y.); <email>tanhongbo@hubdzj.gov.cn</email> (H.T.); <email>wangjiapei@hubdzj.gov.cn</email> (J.W.)</aff><aff id="af2-sensors-25-01101"><label>2</label>School of Electric &#x00026; Electronic Engineering, Wuhan Polytechnic University, Wuhan 430023, China; <email>whliu2020@whpu.edu.cn</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-sensors-25-01101"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>wuguiju@hubdzj.gov.cn</email>; Tel.: +86-153-3719-2960</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>1101</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The geological structure in the Red River fault zone (RRF) and adjacent areas is complex. Due to the lack of high-precision gravity data in the study area, it is difficult to obtain the distribution of materials within the Earth&#x02019;s crust. In this study, a gravity data-fused method is proposed. The Moho depth model data are utilized to construct the gravity anomaly trend, and the mapping relation between the gravity field model data and the measured gravity data is established. Using 934 high-precision measured gravity data as control points, the bilinear interpolation method is used to calculate high-precision grid data of the RRF. Finally, the apparent density inversion method is used to obtain clear crustal density images across the RRF. The experimental results show that the fuses data not only reflect the regional anomaly trend but also maintain the local anomaly information; the root-mean-square error of the fused data is less than 5% and the correlation coefficient is greater than 90%. Through an in-depth comparative analysis of density images, it is found that the low-density anomalous zones, with depths of ~20 km in the northern and southern sections of the RRF, are shallower than those in the middle. The data-fused method provides a new way to process geophysical data more efficiently.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Red River fault</kwd><kwd>Bouguer gravity anomaly</kwd><kwd>bilinear interpolation</kwd><kwd>gravity field model data</kwd><kwd>apparent density imaging</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)</funding-source><award-id>42074172</award-id><award-id>41774015</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source>key project of the Earthquake Spark Plan</funding-source><award-id>XH21021</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) under grants (No. 42074172 and 41774015) and the key project of the Earthquake Spark Plan under a grant (No. XH21021).</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-sensors-25-01101"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Large faults are known to be closely associated with destructive earthquakes, thereby attracting the attention of geologists and geophysicists [<xref rid="B1-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. A large strike-slip fault, the Red River fault (RRF), is located along the southwestern margin of the Sichuan&#x02013;Yunnan block and adjacent to the southeastern margin of the Qinghai&#x02013;Tibet Plateau. Since the Neogene period, the RRF has undergone a kinematic transformation, transitioning from an initial left-lateral strike-slip movement to a subsequent right-lateral strike-slip movement [<xref rid="B3-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The middle segment, extending from Yuanjiang to Yuanyang, aligns in a north&#x02013;northwest direction (60&#x000b0; N&#x02013;70&#x000b0; W), forming a concave shape restraining a big bend and exhibiting thrust components [<xref rid="B6-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In the northern and southern sections of the RRF, numerous strong M &#x02265; 6.0 earthquakes have occurred, but none have occurred in the middle section shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. These complex tectonic phenomena illustrate the intricate characteristics of the deep geophysical field surrounding the RRF. Due to the geographical constraints along and around this fault zone, high-precision geophysical data are lacking in this region. Therefore, obtaining high-precision geophysical data is of great significance for elucidating the crustal structure information from shallow to deep along the RRF, as well as for researching the conceiving and occurrence of strong earthquakes.</p><p>The results of tomographic imaging and the joint inversion of Rayleigh-wave dispersion and receiver functions have shown a low-velocity layer from the upper to middle and lower crust between Zhongdian and Xichang [<xref rid="B9-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]; other studies have indicated that there is an obvious high-velocity anomaly in the lower crust beneath the central Sichuan&#x02013;Yunnan block (SYB) [<xref rid="B14-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The results of artificial seismic sounding profiles have revealed that the low-velocity anomaly in Zhongdian may have been caused by deep upwelling magma [<xref rid="B17-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Li Yu et al. obtained Rayleigh velocity results for the SYB that showed an obvious low-velocity anomalous body in the middle and lower crust of the SYB, and the upper boundary of the low-velocity body was located at a depth of approximately 19 km [<xref rid="B19-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Electromagnetic surveys showed two main low resistance zones at depths of 20&#x02013;40 km, which may be a lower crustal &#x0201c;channel flow&#x0201d;; one of these zones runs through the SYB from NW to SE [<xref rid="B20-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B21-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Previous gravity studies have focused on the activity and direction of the north and south sections of the RRF, respectively [<xref rid="B23-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="B24-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Due to the differences in the data and methods used by researchers, as well as the obtained differences in the geophysical characteristics, considerable controversies in understanding the distribution characteristics of deep structures in the SYB and its adjacent regions are still present.
<fig position="anchor" id="sensors-25-01101-f001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic map of the geological structure (modified after [<xref rid="B26-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]). F1: Nujiang fault; F2: Nantinghe fault; F3: Lantsang fault; F4: Wuliangshan fault; F5: Weixi&#x02013;Weishan fault; F6: Binchuan&#x02013;Yongsheng fault; F7: Red River fault; F8: Huanan&#x02013;Chuxiong&#x02013;Jianshui fault; F9: Anninghe fault; F10: Puduhe fault; F11: Xiaojiang fault; SYB: Sichuan&#x02013;Yunnan block; BKB: Bayankala block; QB: Qiangtang block; S-YB: South Yunnan block; W-YB: West Yunnan block.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01101-g001" position="float"/></fig>
</p><p>In this study, the mapping relation between the gravity model data and the measured gravity data is obtained by taking the measured gravity data as the control point and the Moho surface fluctuation as the trend. The high-precision grid data in the study area were calculated via the bilinear interpolation method (BIM). Then, the apparent density method was used to identify the across-depth structural characteristics of the RRF. The seismogenic structural characteristics of strong earthquakes along the RRF and the formation mechanism of seismic gaps in the middle of the RRF were analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-sensors-25-01101"><title>2. Material and Methods</title><sec id="sec2dot1-sensors-25-01101"><title>2.1. Study Area</title><p>The study region spans the South Yunnan and Sichuan&#x02013;Yunnan blocks from west to east (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The main faults studied in this paper are oriented NW&#x02013;SE, such as the Qujiang fault (F9), Red River fault (F7), Wuliangshan fault (F4), and Lantsang fault (F3); several faults are oriented N&#x02013;S: the Nujiang fault (F1), Anninghe fault (F9), Puduhe fault (F10), and Xiaojiang fault (F11). The strata in the whole study region are mainly Jurassic, Triassic, Permian, and Cretaceous, accompanied by older Proterozoic, upper Paleozoic, and lower Paleozoic, and the intruded granites are Variscian and Yanshanian and are located to the west of F3. The strata along F7 from north to south are mainly Permian, Triassic, Jurassic, and Proterozoic. F7 marks the southwestern boundary of the SYB and extends southeast from Tibet to the South China Sea [<xref rid="B28-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B29-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. It is also a major intracontinental fault with right&#x02013;lateral slip movements, fit for the South China block, which extrudes to the southeast [<xref rid="B30-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B31-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="B32-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="B33-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Due to the collision and compression between the Indian Plate and the Eurasian Plate, the eastward movement of materials in the middle and lower crust is blocked by the rigid South China block, which leads to the thickening of the lower crust beneath the SYB [<xref rid="B34-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. But the crustal thickness on both sides of the RRF does not change abruptly; instead, it varies significantly along the RRF, with the northern and southern segments being thinner than the middle segment [<xref rid="B35-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Strong earthquakes of M &#x02265; 6.0 all occurred in the northern and southern sections of F7, but none occurred in the middle section of F7. In other words, there are seismic gaps in the middle section of F7. Is this phenomenon caused by the clockwise rotation and overall motion of the SYB towards the SE due to the eastward flow of material from the Qinghai&#x02013;Tibet Plateau? To answer this question, it is of great scientific significance and reference value to study the deep structural characteristics of this region for strong earthquake generation mechanisms and regional disaster prediction.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-sensors-25-01101"><title>2.2. Bouguer Gravity Anomalies&#x02019; Data</title><p>In this study, three kinds of data were utilized for gravity data fusion: gravity base stations&#x02019; data, gravity profiles&#x02019; data, and the Earth global gravity model EGM2008 [<xref rid="B36-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. As shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, there are 225 gravity base stations, and they are relatively evenly distributed throughout the study area (blue circles in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). A total of 5 gravity profiles were measured, with an average measuring point distance of approximately 2.5 km and a total of 709 (blue stars in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). These measuring points were measured using two gravimeters (CG&#x02013;5/CG&#x02013;6 Autograv<sup>TM</sup>, Scintrex, ON, Canada); the built-in software of the gravimeters was used for tide correction. A total of 5 data points were recorded at each gravity measuring point, and one data point was recorded per 60 s, with an accuracy of 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup> m&#x000b7;s<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>, and the average value of the 5 data points was the final measured value of the points. In the measurement process, the initial measuring point on the second day was the end measuring point on the previous day. The average distance of the gravity base stations is about 40 km, and the average distance between adjacent points of the measured gravity profiles is approximately 2.5 km, but the data coverage is too limited to provide a clear image of the physical distribution characteristics of the subsurface region.</p><p>The Bouguer gravity anomaly (BGA) grids of the EGM2008 exhibit dramatic variations across the study, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. These anomalies were computed using the spherical harmonic coefficients of the EGM2008 and the density for the topographic correction is 2.67 g/cm<sup>3</sup>. They mainly reflect the relief of terrain and are consistent with the patterns of the topographic relief, and the density value used for topographic correction is not suitable for all regions. Furthermore, the grid data distance is averaged over 6.0 km &#x000d7; 6.0 km; the data resolution is too low to fully understand the crustal tectonic characteristics in the study area.</p><p>The coordinate systems utilized for the three kinds of gravity data are inconsistent, leading to differing longitude and latitude coordinates for each gravity data point. Furthermore, there are significant differences in elevation values even for the same points, which results in significant variations in the gravity data. In order to obtain more comprehensive, accurate, and reliable gravity anomaly data, it is necessary to unify these three kinds of gravity data into the same coordinate system. In this paper, the gravity profile data and the gravity base station data are selected as the control points to find the difference between the gravity model data and the measured data.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot3-sensors-25-01101"><title>2.3. Incomplete Mapping Relation</title><p>The Moho surface undulation of CRUST1.0 is used to fit the unknown polynomials and the coefficients of their gravity profile [<xref rid="B37-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The least square method is applied in this paper. The number of points is <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>; the multinomial (<italic toggle="yes">m</italic> &#x02212; 1) formula is fitted as follows:<disp-formula id="FD1-sensors-25-01101"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="mm1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> &#x02264; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>. In the actual calculation process, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> needs to be transformed in order to prevent operation overflow.<disp-formula id="FD2-sensors-25-01101"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="mm2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The form of the fitting polynomial is as follows:<disp-formula id="FD3-sensors-25-01101"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="mm3" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Then, the coefficients of the unknown polynomial (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">a</italic><sub>2</sub>, &#x02026;) are determined. The incomplete mapping relation between the measured data and the gravity model data is as follows:<disp-formula id="FD4-sensors-25-01101"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="mm4" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.308</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>There, <italic toggle="yes">G<sub>m</sub></italic> is the corrected the BGAs of the EGM2008 based on the measured gravity data and the GPS results from co-located observations [<xref rid="B38-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]; <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> is the altitude difference between the elevation of the model digital terrain and the measured elevation at the same point, and <italic toggle="yes">f</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">h</italic>) is the approximate difference function between measured data and the gravity model data,<disp-formula id="FD5-sensors-25-01101"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="mm5" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.00002679</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0003116</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01288</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.6612</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where the coefficients of the least square method in Formula (5) are fitted according to the Moho surface undulation. Based on the empirical formula of a previous study [<xref rid="B39-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], the coefficients are modified. If the root-mean-square error (RMSE) is less than 5% and the correlation coefficient (CORREL) is greater than 90%, then the calculation ends.<disp-formula id="FD6-sensors-25-01101"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="mm6" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="FD7-sensors-25-01101"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="mm7" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">G<sub>obs</sub></italic> is the measured Bouguer gravity data, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm8" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the average value of the measured Bouguer gravity data, <italic toggle="yes">G<sub>mi</sub></italic> is the Bouguer of gravity model data, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm9" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the average value of the Bouguer gravity model data. Finally, BIM is used to obtain high-precision grid data in the study area.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot4-sensors-25-01101"><title>2.4. Bilinear Interpolation Method</title><p>The BIM is a two-dimensional application of linear interpolation [<xref rid="B40-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="B41-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. This method calculates the pixel value of the target pixel by considering the four nearest neighboring pixels surrounding it and using linear weights to perform a weighted average on them. It not only can provide relatively smooth reconstruction results but also avoid abrupt changes in pixel values, making the interpolated image smoother and more natural. In this paper, the value of the output BGAs is the weighted average of the input BGAs in the nearest 2 &#x000d7; 2 neighborhoods. Firstly, a 2.5 km &#x000d7; 2.5 km grid is built, and the corrected BGAs data and the BGAs of measured data are filled into the grid; meanwhile, the BGAs of the measured data are used as the control points. The BGA values of the vertex coordinates of the square region and their coordinates are <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub>11</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub>1</sub>), <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub>21</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub>1</sub>), <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub>12</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub>2</sub>), and <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub>22</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub>2</sub>), as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>.</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) of any point in the square can be obtained using BIM. <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub>1</sub>) is obtained by interpolating points <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub>11</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub>21</sub> in the <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> direction,<disp-formula id="FD8-sensors-25-01101"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="mm10" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><italic toggle="yes">g</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub>2</sub>) is obtained by interpolating points <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub>12</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub>22</sub> in the <italic toggle="yes">x</italic> direction,<disp-formula id="FD9-sensors-25-01101"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="mm11" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
and <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) is obtained by interpolating points <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub>1</sub>) and <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub>2</sub>) in the <italic toggle="yes">y</italic> direction,<disp-formula id="FD10-sensors-25-01101"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="mm12" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Formulas (8) and (9) are substituted into Formula (10). Finally, <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) is as follows:<disp-formula id="FD11-sensors-25-01101"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="mm13" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace linebreak="newline"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2dot5-sensors-25-01101"><title>2.5. Apparent Density Imaging Methodology</title><p>The apparent density imaging is a method of dividing the underground medium into a multi-layer and multi-block density model, establishing the objective function in the spatial domain, and solving it with the optimization inversion method so as to obtain the heterogeneous distribution of the density of the underground medium with depth. In this study, suppose there are an observational gravity anomaly profile <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> = {<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>2</sub>, &#x02026;, <italic toggle="yes">d<sub>M</sub></italic>} and an unknown residual density model, <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> = {<italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub>2</sub>, &#x02026;, <italic toggle="yes">m<sub>N</sub></italic>}, which are related by <disp-formula id="FD13-sensors-25-01101"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="mm14" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm15" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a sensitivity matrix called the kernel matrix, and the element <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm16" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the gravity anomaly weight generated via the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>th density cell at the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>th data point.</p><p>In general, the number of residual density cells, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>, is much larger than the number of observational gravity anomaly data points, <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>, and Equation (12) cannot be solved directly [<xref rid="B42-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The inverse problem (density imaging) can be transformed into an optimization problem by introducing some a priori constraints and using regularization. We follow the Li and Oldenburg scheme in this study [<xref rid="B43-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and the global objective functions are given by<disp-formula id="FD14-sensors-25-01101"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="mm17" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="&#x02016;" close="&#x02016;" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="&#x02016;" close="&#x02016;" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The first term of Equation (13) is the data misfit function, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm18" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is an initial reference density model, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm19" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a weighting matrix of the data [<xref rid="B44-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].<disp-formula id="FD15-sensors-25-01101"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="mm20" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mfenced open="{" close="" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="" close="}" separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm21" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the standard deviation in the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>th data point.</p><p>The second term of Equation (13) represents the objective function of the model, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm22" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is fixed regularization parameter that can be controlled via the objective function and the data misfit function. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm23" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the model weighting matrix, which consists of four matrices, and the form of any of the four matrices is as follows:<disp-formula id="FD16-sensors-25-01101"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="mm24" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm25" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm26" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a coefficient that gives relative weighting to each matrix. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm27" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm28" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in this study. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm29" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a diagonal matrix with weighting for each cell, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm30" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm31" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm32" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are diagonal matrices with weighting for each interface in their corresponding direction; Ds is a diagonal matrix with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm33" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> on its diagonal, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm34" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm35" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm36" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are derivative operators for the respective direction. The depth weighting function <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic> is given by<disp-formula id="FD17-sensors-25-01101"><label>(16)</label><mml:math id="mm37" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p><italic toggle="yes">Z</italic> is the depth of the residual density cell center, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm38" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm39" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the study [<xref rid="B38-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B43-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p><p>The third term of Equation (13) is an additional regularization term that imposes the positivity of the tail effect using a logarithmic barrier method. <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bb;</italic> is the logarithmic constant, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm40" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the density of the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>th cell, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm41" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the maximum possible residual density.</p><p>The optimal residual density model is solved through iteration until two stopping criteria are met: if <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bb;</italic> is sufficiently small or nearly zero, the logarithmic term has almost no contribution to Equation (13), and the change in the objective function in the previous iteration is less than 1%. Finally, the apparent density imaging method is used to invert the data from the five gravity profiles. In the paper, the constraint range for apparent density is from &#x02212;1 g/cm<sup>3</sup> to 1 g/cm<sup>3</sup>, based on the results of artificial seismic wave velocity measurements [<xref rid="B34-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3-sensors-25-01101"><title>3. Results</title><sec id="sec3dot1-sensors-25-01101"><title>3.1. The Result of Data Fusion</title><p><xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref> displays a comparison of the BGA data from the actually measured profiles at the same data locations and the fused data. As can be seen from <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>, along profile L1, profile L2 and, profile L4, the BGAs gradually decrease from the northwest to the southeast, and the overall trend remains consistent across all points. Along the NS profile L3, the BGAs also gradually decrease from south to north. Along profile 5, the overall trend of the BGAs exhibits a descending&#x02013;ascending&#x02013;descending pattern. The fused data appear smoother and denser, not only reflecting regional anomaly trends but also preserving local anomaly information. In the calculation, the RMSE is 2.96, and the CORREL is 0.91. This demonstrates the correctness of the mapping relationship established, providing more accurate data for crustal structure analysis.</p><p>The overall fused data of BGAs in the study area are shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>. The BGAs of high-precision grid data are averaged over 2.5 km &#x000d7; 2.5 km. The entire BGAs in the study area are negative and decrease gradually from south to north. Compared to <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, the fused data not only retain useful information but also eliminate the influence of terrain. The amplitude is &#x02212;100&#x02013;&#x02212;380 mGal. M &#x02265; 6.0 earthquakes are usually distributed in the transition zone of the BGAs, and the faults in the regions are also developed. Upon comparing the stratigraphic and seismic distribution (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) with the results of fused BGAs (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>), it is found that strong earthquakes often correspond to regions with scattered stratigraphic formations or stratigraphic boundary zones. These regions also coincide with the transition zones of BGAs, especially along the southern segment of F1, F4, the northern segment of F7, and F11.</p><p>In order to analyze the crustal density structure characteristics of the RRF, five gravity profiles crossing it are analyzed. The BGAs is a comprehensive reaction of underground materials. The BGAs of four measured gravity profiles (L1, L2, L4, and L5) and one extractive profile (L<italic toggle="yes">m</italic>) were analyzed, and then the apparent density method was used to obtain the across-depth structural characteristics of the RRF, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot2-sensors-25-01101"><title>3.2. The Result of Density Imaging</title><p>To accurately reveal the structural anomalies in the study region, the five gravity profiles were calculated in more detail using the apparent density imaging method, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>. Profile L1 spans the F1, F3, F4, F5, F7, and F6 faults from southwest to northeast. The values of residual density contrasts are alternately positive and negative along the profile (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>a). When faults are projected onto L1, they intersect at approximately 30, 75, 110, 150, 180, and 220 km from the beginning (southwest of profile L1) of the x-axis along profile L1 in the NE direction. These faults all correspond to the negative anomalous area of the density contrasts. The dip angles of these anomalies are very steep, with angles &#x0003e; 50&#x000b0; (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, the negative anomalous areas extend downwards to a depth greater than 20 km, and the anomalous areas even penetrate downwards to a depth greater than 35 km at 30, 75, and 110 km in profile L1.</p><p>Profile L2 spans the F2, F3, F4, F7, and F6 faults from southwest to northeast, and the southwestern part of profile L2 is distributed along F2. The values of density contrast along profile L2 are mainly negative, except for two positive anomalous areas at approximately 30 and 150 km (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>b). F2, F3, F4, F7, and F6 are projected onto the gravity profile L2 along the x-axis. These faults are located at ~95 and 165 km, respectively. Anomalous areas close to each other near 180 km along the x-axis intersect at a depth of ~15 km. In other words, the surfaces of F6 and F7 are close together, with dip angles &#x0003e; 50&#x000b0; (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), and the large range of negative anomalous areas penetrates to &#x0003e;40 km in depth.</p><p>Profile L<italic toggle="yes">m</italic> spans the F4, F7, and F8 faults from southwest to northeast. The values of the density contrast along profile L2 are mainly alternating positive&#x02013;negative distributions, especially a negative anomalous area at approximately 140 and 170 km (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>c). Four negative anomalous areas are observed at approximately 50, 80, 110, and 150 km from the beginning (west of profile L<italic toggle="yes">m</italic>) of the x-axis, with depths greater than 30 km along the profile. F4, F7, and F8 are projected onto gravity profile L<italic toggle="yes">m</italic> along the x-axis, and these faults correspond to the three anomalies from west to east at 70, 110, and 165 km, respectively. The dip angles of the three anomalies are steep. Between 140 km and 170 km, the negative anomaly penetrates to &#x0003e;35 km in depth. It can be inferred that this negative anomaly corresponds to the southern boundary of SYB, and on either side of it, crustal structures are positive density contrasts.</p><p>Profile L5 is the longest with a distance &#x0003e; 400 km; it is in the W&#x02013;E direction and spans F2, F3, F4, F7, the southern Sichuan&#x02013;Yunnan block (SYB), and F10 from west to east. The density contrast imaging map is shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>d. Six negative anomalies are observed at approximately 30, 100, 160, 240, 320, and 380 km from the beginning (east of profile L5) of the x-axis, with depths greater than 20 km along the profile. F2, F3, F4, F7, F8, and F11 are projected onto gravity profile L5 along the x-axis, and these faults correspond to the six anomalies from west to east. The dip angles of the six anomalies are steep, and on either side of the F11 crustal structures are positive density contrasts.</p><p>Using the same method, two negative anomalous areas are inferred at 90 and 150 km from the beginning (southwest of profile L4) of the x-axis, with depths greater than 20 km along profile L4 (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>e). Another negative anomaly is also indicated at approximately 70 km along the x-axis; it converges with the negative anomaly at 90 km on the x-axis at a depth of approximately 35 km. It can be inferred that this negative anomaly corresponds to F7, and F7 is wider. The dip angles of the three negative anomalies are &#x0003e;70&#x000b0; (<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Two positive anomalous areas are located between 60 and 110 km, with depths &#x0003e; 35 km. On two sides of F8, positive anomalies with depths &#x0003e; 35 km are also present. One negative anomalous area is inferred between 190 km and 210 km, with depths greater than 35 km along profile L4. In terms of geographical location, this area is mainly distributed along F10.</p><p>In this study area, the density contrasts are within the range of plus or minus 0.8 g/cm<sup>3</sup>. The major faults are located in the negative density contrast areas along the five profiles, with dip angles &#x0003e; 50&#x000b0;. The negative apparent density areas all penetrate to &#x0003e;20 km in depth. According to the records of the China Earthquake Networks Center, the focal depths of strong earthquakes with M &#x02265; 6 within the study area are generally around 15 km. When strong earthquakes along each profile are projected onto the respective profiles, they are generally located in the zones where the density anomalies transition from positive to negative, as illustrated in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>. Furthermore, in comparison to the geological distribution depicted in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, these specific locations also align with stratigraphic boundaries.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4-sensors-25-01101"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>The high-precision BGA data in the Red River fault zone and adjacent areas were obtained. The density contrasts beneath the RRF were inversed. Therefore, we use the results of high-resolution data in space to discuss the following issues: (1) the accuracy of the fused data; (2) the characteristics of the RRF; and (3) the implications of the findings along the RRF.</p><sec id="sec4dot1-sensors-25-01101"><title>4.1. The Accuracy of the Fused Data</title><p>The BGAs represent the superposition of the effect of both deep and shallow anomaly signatures [<xref rid="B45-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="B46-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The separation of the regional component (the Moho surface fluctuating trend effect) from the BGAs is essential for studying the near-surface effect above Moho [<xref rid="B47-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The complete BGAs of EGM2008 are usually obtained through mathematical methods (such as spherical or ellipsoidal harmonics), combined with satellite observations, calculations, and processing. These data are limited by model assumptions, algorithm accuracy, data resolution, and other factors, which may not fully reflect the real situation of the Earth&#x02019;s gravity field.</p><p><xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>a shows the residual BGA results of EGM2008 after the Moho surface fluctuating trend effect is removed. Compared with the terrain shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, the region with high altitude corresponds to the positive high anomaly region, and the region with low altitude corresponds to the negative low anomaly region, the residual BGAs reflect the characteristics of relief changes in the terrain. And the positive and negative regions of the residual BGAs are scattered.</p><p><xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>b shows the residual BGAs results of the fused BGAs. The faults are mainly distributed along the high&#x02013;low gradient transition zone of the residual BGAs. At the same time, M &#x02265; 6.0 earthquakes usually occur in the negative abnormal areas. The block boundaries are also mainly distributed along the high&#x02013;low gradient transition zone, and the residual BGAs along the block boundaries are mainly negative. Compared with the geology stratum shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, the high&#x02013;low gradient transition zones of the residual BGAs also align with stratigraphic boundaries. Both the northern and southern sections of the RRF exhibit pronounced high&#x02013;low gradients of the residual BGAs, whereas the middle section displays irregular distortions with a relatively low variation. This phenomenon is relatively consistent with other research findings [<xref rid="B48-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="B49-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. These results demonstrate significant variations in rock density within the crust along the RRF, indicating a complex deep tectonic environment.</p><p>The residual BGAs are essentially a reflection of the uneven distribution of matter density inside the earth. By analyzing the distribution characteristics of residual BGAs, we can infer the strike, dip, and dip parameters of geological structures. The fused data in the research area not only reflect the regional anomaly feature but also retain the local anomaly information.</p></sec><sec id="sec4dot2-sensors-25-01101"><title>4.2. Characterizing Crossing the RRF</title><p>From north to south along F4 and F7, the apparent densities at depths &#x02264; 20 km are low and complex. The apparent densities are high-density anomalies on both sides of F4 and F7, and the anomalies, all penetrate downwards to greater than 20 km in depth. The locations and shapes of the low-density anomalous zones along F7 correspond to those of the low-speed zones [<xref rid="B50-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="B51-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="B52-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B53-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="B54-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The apparent densities along F7 at depths greater than 30 km are high&#x02013;low&#x02013;high from north to south.</p><p>In the northern section of F7, profiles L1 and L2 span this section, the low-density anomalous zones extend downwards to a depth of ~20 km, and the high-density anomalous zones on the western and eastern sides of F7 also penetrate to a depth of ~20 km, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>a,b. The high-density anomalous zones mainly correspond to the Permian and Triassic. The low-density anomalous zones are located at the junction of the two geological strata. However, M &#x02265; 6.0 earthquakes often occur in areas with low BGAs near high-low gradient transition zone, especially earthquakes with M &#x02265; 7(<xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>b).</p><p>In the middle section of F7, profiles L<italic toggle="yes">m</italic> and L5 span the section, and the low-density anomalous zones extend downwards to depths &#x02265; 35 km, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>c,d, but the downward extension depth of the high-density anomalous zone to the west of F7 is greater than 40 km. In particular, the low-density anomalous zone is obvious at approximately 35 km (in profile L5) along the x-axis, and it extends from the surface to the middle and lower crust, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>d. The low-density anomalous zones are mainly located at the junction of Proterozoic and Triassic strata, and east of F7, the apparent densities are mainly low-density anomalies corresponding to Jurassic strata. The distribution of earthquake epicenters shows that there have been no earthquakes with M &#x02265; 6.0 in the middle segment of the RRF, and even earthquakes with M &#x02265; 5.0 are rare.</p><p>In the southern section of F7, profile L4 spans the section, and the downward extension depth of the low-density anomalous zone is less than 30 km, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>e. The low-density anomalous zone is consistent with the low-resistivity zone of magnetotelluric sounding results [<xref rid="B20-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B21-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. M &#x02265; 6.0 earthquakes often occur on the east side of F7 at high densities, which correspond to Proterozoic strata.</p><p>The low apparent densities beneath F7 are mainly caused by a deep and large fault cutting through the crust. However, the low apparent densities on the east side of F7 in the middle are higher than those in its northern and southern sections, while the high-density anomaly zone in the middle section of F7 extends downwards to deeper than that in the northern and southern sections. Along F7, M &#x02265; 6.0 earthquakes usually occur in areas with older strata, where the apparent densities are high-low gradient transition zone.</p></sec><sec id="sec4dot3-sensors-25-01101"><title>4.3. Causes of the Seismic Gap in the Middle of the RRF</title><p>Since the records began, strong M &#x02265; 6.0 earthquakes have all occurred in the northern and southern sections of F7, but none have occurred in the middle section of F7. In other words, there is a seismic gap in the middle section of F7, especially between Nanjian and Mojiang. That is, the crustal material along F7 is different in the north, middle, and south sections. The results of a geodetic survey indicate that the middle segment of the RRF exhibits a higher locking degree, with weaker strain compared to its northern and southern segments [<xref rid="B55-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B56-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="B57-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</p><p>The crustal material signal reflection ratios along the RRF show that the reflectance ratios are mainly high in the middle of RRF and low in the north and south, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>a. The reflection ratios along the lower crustal are low, especially in the area above the Moho shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>a. And <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>b shows that the area of the reflection ratios in the middle of F7 are large and exhibit the effects of Moho fluctuations. The results of the average shear wave velocity (<italic toggle="yes">Vs</italic>) indicate that, in the depth range of 5&#x02013;20 km, the values of Vs in the middle section of F7 are higher than that in the north and south [<xref rid="B58-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="B59-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="B60-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] and lower at depths greater than 25 km. The high-density area corresponds to the high-speed belt. Low-density areas can lead to energy and material accumulation. However, the shallow to lower crust in the middle of F7 is dominated by high densities, which do not easily accumulate crustal material or energy. Research findings concerning the electrical structural characteristics of the crust indicate the presence of significant high conductors in the northern and southern segments of RRF [<xref rid="B20-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B61-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="B62-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Meanwhile, the reflection ratios are high in the middle of F7, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>b. The eastward material flow of the Qinghai&#x02013;Tibet Plateau in the crust is prevented by the SYB and moves northwards or southwards along F7, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>c. Moreover, the crustal material is high-density in the middle of F7, where the material cannot accumulate. These results lead us to conclude that strong earthquakes do not often occur in areas with high densities.</p><p>In our calculated variations in density contrast, the overall trend of the variations in density contrast is large in the northern and southern sections of F7 and is small in the middle section of F7. It is interesting that the places where the strong earthquakes occurred agree with the area where the variations in density contrast are large along F7. Although M &#x02265; 6.0 earthquakes occurred frequently in the southern and northern sections of F7, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, and their focal depths were shallow, generally lower than 15 km, this phenomenon still does not affect the rate of densities&#x02019; variation. In other words, the amplitude of the density variation is the greatest in the middle of F7. In previous studies, there was a channelized weak zone across F7, which is still under debate [<xref rid="B51-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="B63-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,<xref rid="B64-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,<xref rid="B65-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,<xref rid="B66-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,<xref rid="B67-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Some researchers have proposed that a channelized weak zone continues at depths of 20&#x02013;40 km in the southern direction across F7 and extends to northern Vietnam. Others indicated that the channelized weak zone approximately parallels F7. In terms of the obvious variation in densities, the small variation in the southern part of F7 may be due to the dipping barrier. This phenomenon seems to contradict the explanation that there exists a thick channelized weak zone parallel to F7. The eastward-moving material in the southern part of F7 and the south-eastward crustal flow material converge at the southern end of F7, which results in material accumulation.</p><p>The phenomenon is similar in the northern part of F7 that reaches the eastern Himalayas; the phenomenon may be caused by the high-density body formed by the blocking of the flow material in the crust, as shown in <xref rid="sensors-25-01101-f009" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref>. Previous results have shown that the crustal material in the north&#x02013;central SYB is rigid, which blocks the eastward flow of material from the Qinghai&#x02013;Tibet Plateau [<xref rid="B68-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. The results of the apparent densities along the northern section of F7 show that they are high. Moreover, the amplitude of the variation in gravity is large, which matches the above research. Other findings have shown that an ascending mantle material produced many intrusions, which were emplaced both inside and outside F7 [<xref rid="B69-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] and may have formed soft and low apparent densities in the crust, especially in the middle section of F7 and its adjacent area. And some research results also indicate that, due to crustal movements and stress effects, the crust in the middle segment of the RRF may have already closed or become locked, forming a localized area of continuous deformation in the NW&#x02013;SE direction [<xref rid="B70-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,<xref rid="B71-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Therefore, we suggest that another reason for the seismic gap in the middle of F7 is the migration of upwelling mantle material to the northern and southern sides of F7.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec5-sensors-25-01101"><title>5. Conclusions</title><p>The high resolution of apparent density spatial images reveals well-resolved crustal structures beneath the Red River fault and its adjacent region, and continuous temporal gravity variation maps show obvious differences in the northern, middle, and southern F7. This study provides high-accuracy BGA grid data and important insights into the causes of strong earthquake gaps in this region. The major findings of this study can be summarized as follows:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>The BGAs of high-precision grid data of 2.5 km &#x000d7; 2.5 km are obtained. The RMSE is about 2.96, and the CORREL is about 0.91. The fused data in the research area not only reflect the regional anomaly feature but also retain the local anomaly information.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The low-density anomalous zones in the northern and southern sections of F7 are shallower than those in the middle. The high-low gradient transition zones of densities are also located at the junction of geological strata and extend downwards to a depth of ~20 km, where M &#x02265; 6.0 earthquakes often occur, especially earthquakes of M &#x02265; 7.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The reflection ratios in the middle of F7 are higher than in the north and south of F7. The migration of upwelling asthenospheric material to the northern and southern sides of F7 cannot accumulate material and energy in the middle of F7, resulting in the existence of a strong earthquake gap.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to thank the editor and reviewers for their suggestions, which improved the manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Disclaimer/Publisher&#x02019;s Note:</bold> The statements, opinions and data contained in all publications are solely those of the individual author(s) and contributor(s) and not of MDPI and/or the editor(s). MDPI and/or the editor(s) disclaim responsibility for any injury to people or property resulting from any ideas, methods, instructions or products referred to in the content.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Writing&#x02014;original draft, writing&#x02014;reviewing and editing, methodology, formal analysis, project administration, and funding acquisition, G.W.; data curation for gravity measurements, F.Y. and H.T.; graphical editing and measurement of absolute gravity points, J.W.; text editing and revision, W.L. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Institutional Review Board Statement</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Informed Consent Statement</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The seismic event catalog is available through CENC (<uri xlink:href="http://www.ceic.ac.cn/history">http://www.ceic.ac.cn/history</uri>) and accessed on 8 June 2024. The complete EGM2008 Bouguer gravity anomalies data were extracted from the official Earth Gravitational Model (EGM2008) on 18 March 2020 released by the National Geospatial Intelligence Agency (NGA) (<uri xlink:href="http://bgi.obs-mip.fr/data-products/outils/egm2008-anomaly-maps-visualization/">http://bgi.obs-mip.fr/data-products/outils/egm2008-anomaly-maps-visualization/</uri>). These data accessed on 1 January 2020.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-sensors-25-01101"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Harishidayat</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Al-Shuhail</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Randazzo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muzirafuti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Reconstruction of Land and Marine Features by Seismic and Surface Geomorphology Techniques</article-title><source>Appl. Sci.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>9611</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app12199611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-sensors-25-01101"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>K&#x000e1;zm&#x000e9;r</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gaidzik</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Seismic Activity Along the Periadriatic and Sava Faults in the Past Two Millennia&#x02014;An Archaeoseismological Assessment</article-title><source>Geosciences</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>331</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/geosciences14120331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-sensors-25-01101"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Schoenbohm</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burchfiel</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Miocene to present activity along the Red River fault, China, in the context of continental extrusion, upper crustal rotation, and lower-crustal flow</article-title><source>GSA Bull.</source><year>2006</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1130/B25816.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-sensors-25-01101"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Cenozoic tectonic transition and dynamic mechanism of the Ailao Shan-Red River Fault Zone</article-title><source>Acta Geosci. Sin.</source><year>2017</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3975/cagsb.2017.s1.03</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-sensors-25-01101"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Block motion, slip rates, and earthquake hazard assessment of boundary faults in the Sichuan-Yunnan region, China</article-title><source>Acta Gophysica</source><year>2024</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>3831</fpage><lpage>3848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11600-024-01319-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-sensors-25-01101"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Seismic and geological characteristics of Honghe fault zone</article-title><source>Yunnan Geol.</source><year>1983</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-sensors-25-01101"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Tectonic evolution of southeast Asia and the Ailao-Honghe Tectonic Belt</article-title><source>Geol. Rev.</source><year>1999</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-sensors-25-01101"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Complex structural fault system and distributed deformation across the Big Bend of the Red River fault, Yunnan, China</article-title><source>Phys. Earth Planet. Inter.</source><year>2022</year><volume>333</volume><fpage>106942</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pepi.2022.106942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-sensors-25-01101"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Z.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Tomography research of the Zhefang-Binchuan and Menglian-Malong wide-angle seismic profiles in Yunnan province</article-title><source>Chin. J. Geophys.</source><year>2004</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cjg2.484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-sensors-25-01101"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tromp</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lenardic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Lithospheric founding and underthrusting imaged beneath Tibet</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>15659</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms15659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28585571</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-sensors-25-01101"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Fine structure of Pn velocity beneath Sichuan-Yunnan region</article-title><source>Sci. China Ser. D Earth Sci.</source><year>2003</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1360/03dz0016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-sensors-25-01101"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The crust and upper mantle structure beneath Yunnan from joint inversion of receiver functions and Rayleigh wave dispersion data</article-title><source>Phys. Earth Planet. Inter.</source><year>2008</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pepi.2008.08.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-sensors-25-01101"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Badal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Deformation of crust and upper mantle in central Tibet caused by the northward subduction and slab tearing of the Indian lithosphere: New evidence based on shear wave splitting measurements</article-title><source>Earth Planet. Sci. Lett.</source><year>2019</year><volume>514</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epsl.2019.02.037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-sensors-25-01101"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Two crustal low-velocity channels beneath SE Tibet revealed by joint inversion of Rayleigh wave dispersion and receiver functions</article-title><source>Earth Planet. Sci. Lett.</source><year>2015</year><volume>415</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epsl.2015.01.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15-sensors-25-01101"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Mapping crustal structure beneath southern Tibet: Seismic evidence for continental crustal underthrusting</article-title><source>Gondwana Res.</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1487</fpage><lpage>1493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gr.2014.01.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16-sensors-25-01101"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Upper crustal velocity of Lijiang-Qingzhen profile and its relationship with the seismogenic environment of the Ms6.5 Ludian earthquake</article-title><source>Chin. J. Geophys.</source><year>2014</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>3069</fpage><lpage>3079</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6038/cjg20140932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17-sensors-25-01101"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>L&#x000fc;</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The crustal structure under Sanjiang and its dynamic implications: Revealed by seismic reflection/refraction profile between Zhefang and Binchuan, Yunnan</article-title><source>Sci. China Ser. D Earth Sci.</source><year>2005</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1329</fpage><lpage>1336</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1360/01yd0567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18-sensors-25-01101"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Crustal and upper mantle velocity structure in Yunnan, Southwest China</article-title><source>Tectonophysics</source><year>2009</year><volume>471</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tecto.2009.02.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19-sensors-25-01101"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Phase velocity array tomography of Rayleigh waves in western Sichuan from ambient seismic noise</article-title><source>Chin. J. Geophys.</source><year>2010</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>842</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3969/j.issn.0001-5733.2010.04.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20-sensors-25-01101"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Unsworth</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meju</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Crustal deformation of the eastern Tibetan plateau revealed by magnetotelluric imaging</article-title><source>Nat. Geosci.</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ngeo830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21-sensors-25-01101"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Varentsov</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lozovsky</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Electrical resistivity structure of the Xiaojiang strike-slip fault system (SW China) and its tectonic implications</article-title><source>J. Asian Earth Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jseaes.2019.01.031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22-sensors-25-01101"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>New images of the crustal structure beneath easternTibet from a high-density seismic array</article-title><source>Earth Planet. Sci. Lett.</source><year>2017</year><volume>480</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epsl.2017.09.048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23-sensors-25-01101"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Geophysical research on deep structure feature in study region of Red River fault zone</article-title><source>Prog. Geophys.</source><year>2005</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3969/j.issn.1004-2903.2005.03.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24-sensors-25-01101"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Robust inversion analysis of local gravity anomalies caused by geological dislocation model of faults</article-title><source>Acta Seismol. Sin.</source><year>1998</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02650460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25-sensors-25-01101"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Collation and stipulation of the core science problems and theoretical concept in the geoscience study on the Tibetan plateau</article-title><source>Chin. J. Geophys.</source><year>2015</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6038/cjg20150109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26-sensors-25-01101"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Active tectonics and earthquake activities in China</article-title><source>Earth Sci. Front.</source><year>2003</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3321/j.issn:1005-2321.2003.z1.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27-sensors-25-01101"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Active tectonic blocks and strong earthquakes in the continent of China</article-title><source>Sci. China Ser. D Earth Sci.</source><year>2003</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1360/03dz0002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28-sensors-25-01101"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Role of the Red River Shear zone, Yunnan and Vietnam, in the continental extrusion of SE Asia</article-title><source>J. Geol. Soc.</source><year>2006</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>1025</fpage><lpage>1036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1144/0016-76492005-144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29-sensors-25-01101"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Burchfiel</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Interpretation of Cenozoic tectonics in the right-lateral accommodation zone between the Ailao Shan shear zone and the eastern Himalayan syntaxis</article-title><source>Int. Geol. Rev.</source><year>1997</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00206819709465267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30-sensors-25-01101"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Leloup</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lacassin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tapponnier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;rer</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trinh</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Ailao Shan-Red river shear zone (Yunnan, China), tertiary transform boundary of Indochina</article-title><source>Tectonophysics</source><year>1995</year><volume>251</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0040-1951(95)00070-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31-sensors-25-01101"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Replumaz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lacassin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tapponnier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leoup</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Large river offsets and Plio-Quaternary dextral slip rate on the Red River fault (Yunnan, China)</article-title><source>J. Geophys. Res. Solid. Earth</source><year>2001</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2000JB900135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32-sensors-25-01101"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tapponnier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peltzer</surname><given-names>G.L.D.A.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Le Dain</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Armijo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cobbold</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Propagating extrusion tectonics in Asia: New insights from simple experiments with plasticine</article-title><source>Geology</source><year>1982</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1130/0091-7613(1982)10&#x0003c;611:PETIAN&#x0003e;2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33-sensors-25-01101"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tapponnier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lacassin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leloup</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;rer</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Ailao Shan/Red River metamorphic belt: Tertiary left-lateral shear between Indochina and South China</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1990</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/343431a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34-sensors-25-01101"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Study on the lithospheric structure and earthquakes in North-South Tectonic Belt</article-title><source>Chin. J. Geophys.</source><year>2015</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>3867</fpage><lpage>3901</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6038/cjg20151101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35-sensors-25-01101"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Crustal thicknesses and Poisson&#x02019;s ratios beneath the Chuxiong-Simao Basin in the Southeast Margin of the Tibetan Plateau</article-title><source>Earth Planet. Phys.</source><year>2019</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26464/epp2019008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36-sensors-25-01101"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pavlis</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Factor</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The development and evaluation of the Earth Gravitational Model 2008 (EGM2008)</article-title><source>J. Geophys.Res. Solid Earth</source><year>2012</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>B04406</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2011JB008916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37-sensors-25-01101"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Tenzer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tsoulis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bagherbandi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;berg</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nov&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Analysis of the refined CRUST1. 0 crustal model and its gravity field</article-title><source>Surv. Geophys.</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10712-014-9299-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38-sensors-25-01101"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Imaging the crustal structure beneath the Yinchuan Basin in the western North China Craton using normalized full gradient and 3D gravity inversion</article-title><source>J. Asian Earth Sci.</source><year>2022</year><volume>226</volume><fpage>105087</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jseaes.2022.105087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39-sensors-25-01101"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Gravity data fusion and deep-shallow structure characteristics in Changning of Sichuan Province and its periphery</article-title><source>Acta Geosci. Sin.</source><year>2024</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>977</fpage><lpage>988</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3975/cagsb.2024.011602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40-sensors-25-01101"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>An alternative bilinear interpolation method between spherical grids</article-title><source>Atmosphere</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>123</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/atmos10030123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41-sensors-25-01101"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Press</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teukolsky</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vetterling</surname><given-names>W.T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flannery</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Numerical Recipes in C: The Art of Scientific Computing</source><edition>2nd ed.</edition><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc><year>1992</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><isbn>0-521-43108-5</isbn></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42-sensors-25-01101"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>VanDecar</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snieder</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Obtaining smooth solutions to large, linear, inverse problems</article-title><source>Geophysics</source><year>1994</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1190/1.1443640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43-sensors-25-01101"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Fast inversion of large-scale magnetic data using wavelet transforms and a logarithmic barrier method</article-title><source>Geophys. J. Int.</source><year>2003</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-246X.2003.01766.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44-sensors-25-01101"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>3-D inversion of gravity data</article-title><source>Geophysics</source><year>1998</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1190/1.1444302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45-sensors-25-01101"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ganguli</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maurya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Gravity and magnetic survey in southwestern part of cuddapah basin, india and its implication for shallow crustal architecture and mineralization</article-title><source>J. Geol. Soc. India</source><year>2019</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12594-019-1196-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46-sensors-25-01101"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Ganguli</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Gravity&#x02013;magnetic appraisal at the interface of cuddapah basin and nellore schist belt (nsb) for shallow crustal architecture and tectonic settings</article-title><source>J. Earth Syst. Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>92</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12040-020-1354-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47-sensors-25-01101"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Sub-surface structure of a craton&#x02013;mobile belt interface: Evidence from geological and gravity studies across the rengali province&#x02013;eastern ghats belt boundary, eastern India</article-title><source>Tectonophysics</source><year>2015</year><volume>662</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tecto.2015.01.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48-sensors-25-01101"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><source>Red River Active Fault Zone</source><publisher-name>Ocean Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Beijing, China</publisher-loc><year>2001</year><comment>(In Chinese)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49-sensors-25-01101"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mooney</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Badal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Mantle origin of the Emeishan large igneous province (South China) from the analysis of residual gravity anomalies</article-title><source>Lithos</source><year>2014</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lithos.2014.02.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50-sensors-25-01101"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Crustal anisotropy and deformation of the southeastern margin of the Tibetan Plateau revealed by Pms splitting</article-title><source>J. Asian Earth Sci.</source><year>2016</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jseaes.2016.02.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51-sensors-25-01101"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Crustal structure of Southwest China and northern Vietnam from ambient noise tomography: Implication for the large-scale material transport model in SE Tibet</article-title><source>Tectonics</source><year>2018</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1492</fpage><lpage>1506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2018TC004957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52-sensors-25-01101"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Gravity variations preceding the large earthquakes in the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau from 21st century</article-title><source>Chin. Sci. Bull.</source><year>2020</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1360/TB-2019-0153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53-sensors-25-01101"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Crustal shear wave velocity and radial anisotropy in the Xiaojiang fault zone system (SE Tibet) revealed by ambient noise interferometry</article-title><source>Tectonophysics</source><year>2020</year><volume>792</volume><fpage>228594</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tecto.2020.228594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54-sensors-25-01101"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Crustal and upper mantle structure and deep tectonic genesis of large earthquakes in North China</article-title><source>Sci. China Earth Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>821</fpage><lpage>857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11430-016-9009-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B55-sensors-25-01101"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W.B.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Contemporary crustal movement of southeastern Tibet: Constraints from dense GPS measurements</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>45348</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep45348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28349926</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B56-sensors-25-01101"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Z.K.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Present-day crustal deformation of continental China derived from GPS and its tectonic implications</article-title><source>J. Geophys. Res.-Solid. Earth</source><year>2020</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>e2019JB018774</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2019JB018774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B57-sensors-25-01101"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Comprehensive determination for the late stage of the interseismic period of major faults in the boundary zone of active tectonic blocks in Chinese mainland</article-title><source>China J. Geophys.</source><year>2022</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>4643</fpage><lpage>4658</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6038/cjg2022P0489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B58-sensors-25-01101"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Preliminary analysis of crustal shear-wave splitting in the Sanjiang lateral collision zone of the southeast margin of the Tibetan Plateau and its tectonic implications</article-title><source>Geophys. Prospect.</source><year>2019</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>2432</fpage><lpage>2449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2478.12870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B59-sensors-25-01101"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The community velocity model, V.1.0 of southwest China, constructed from joint body- and surfacewave travel-time tomography</article-title><source>Seism. Res. Lett.</source><year>2021</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>2972</fpage><lpage>2987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1785/0220200318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B60-sensors-25-01101"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The high-resolution community velocity model V2.0 of southwest China, constructed by joint body and surface wave tomography of data recorded at temporary dense arrays</article-title><source>Sci. China Earth Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>2368</fpage><lpage>2385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11430-022-1161-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B61-sensors-25-01101"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Unsworth</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>New insights into crustal and mantle flow beneath the Red River Fault Zone and adjacent areas on the southern margin of the Tibetan Plateau revealed by a 3-D magnetotelluric study</article-title><source>J. Geophys. Res.-Solid. Earth</source><year>2020</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>e2020JB019396</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2020JB019396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B62-sensors-25-01101"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The influence of the Ailaoshan-Red River shear zone on the mineralization of the Beiya deposit on the southeastern margin of the Tibetan Plateau revealed by a 3-D magnetotelluric survey</article-title><source>J. Geophys. Res.-Solid. Earth</source><year>2022</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>e2021JB022923</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2021JB022923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B63-sensors-25-01101"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Badal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Crustal anisotropy from Moho converted Ps wave splitting analysis and geodynamic implications beneath the eastern margin of Tibet and surrounding regions</article-title><source>Gondwana Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>946</fpage><lpage>957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gr.2012.04.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B64-sensors-25-01101"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Massive lithospheric delamination in southeastern Tibet facilitating continental extrusion</article-title><source>Natl. Sci. Rev.</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>nwab174</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nsr/nwab174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35386921</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="B65-sensors-25-01101"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Badal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Comprehensive crustal structure and seismological evidence for lower crustal flow in the southeastern margin of Tibet revealed by receiver functions</article-title><source>Gondwana Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gr.2017.11.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B66-sensors-25-01101"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Three dimensional P-wave velocity structure around Xiaojiang fault system and its tectonic implications</article-title><source>Chin. J. Geophys.</source><year>2013</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>2257</fpage><lpage>2267</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6038/cjg20130713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B67-sensors-25-01101"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The lithospheric structure beneath southeast Tibet revealed by P and S receiver functions</article-title><source>J. Asian Earth Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jseaes.2017.02.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B68-sensors-25-01101"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Characteristics of the lithosphere physical structure in eastern margin of the Qinghai-Tibet plateau and their deep tectonic implications</article-title><source>Chin. J. Geophys.</source><year>2017</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2500</fpage><lpage>2511</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6038/cjg20170637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B69-sensors-25-01101"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Eocene granulite-facies metamorphism prior to deformation of the Mianhuadi mafic complex in the Ailao Shan-Red River shear zone, Yunnan Province, SW China</article-title><source>J. Asian Earth Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jseaes.2017.06.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B70-sensors-25-01101"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Seismic anisotropy in the southeastern margin of the Tibetan Plateau and its deep tectonic significances</article-title><source>Chin. J. Geophys.</source><year>2020</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>802</fpage><lpage>816</lpage><comment>(In Chinese)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.6038/cjg2020O0003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B71-sensors-25-01101"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Seismic Anisotropy in the upper crust beneath the Sanjiang lateral collision zone in the southeastern margin of the Tibetan Plateau revealed by S wave splitting from a temporary array</article-title><source>Ann. Geophys.</source><year>2023</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>SE212</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4401/ag-8867</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01101-f002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Topographic relief and distribution of observation stations map. The blue stars indicate the measured gravity profiles (709 points). The blue circles indicate the gravity base stations (225 points). Cities are marked with solid gray circles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01101-g002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01101-f003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The BGAs of EGM2008 in the study area.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01101-g003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01101-f004"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Diagram of the bilinear interpolation method.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01101-g004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01101-f005"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>A comparison of the data before and after fusion along the measured profiles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01101-g005" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01101-f006"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The BGAs after fusion in the study area.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01101-g006" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01101-f007"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Density contrast results along five profiles beneath crossing the RRF from north to south. Subfigures (<bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>e</bold>) sequentially represent the density contrast results for L1, L2, L<italic toggle="yes">m</italic>, L5, and L4. The black lines indicate faults. The red circles indicate the projected locations of earthquakes with M &#x02265; 6 that occurred along the profiles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01101-g007" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01101-f008"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>The residual BGAs of the research region, obtained by subtracting the regional values. (<bold>a</bold>) The residual BGAs of EGM2008; (<bold>b</bold>) the residual BGAs of the fused BGAs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01101-g008" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="sensors-25-01101-f009"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>A simplified diagram of material distribution and crustal material flow along the RRF. (<bold>a</bold>) The reflection ratio of the residual BGAs; (<bold>b</bold>) the reflection ratio of the fused BGAs. The white lines with arrows indicate deep material flow in the middle of the RRF; (<bold>c</bold>) a cartoon diagram of crustal material flow along the RRF. The black lines with arrows mark the eastward-moving material. The red lines with arrows mark the upwelling mantle material, and the area with blue wavy lines indicates a high-density area. The purple lines with arrows mark indicate lower crust flow [<xref rid="B14-sensors-25-01101" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="sensors-25-01101-g009" position="float"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="sensors-25-01101-t001"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">sensors-25-01101-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Major fault information.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fault Name</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proneness</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dip Angle</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fault Strike</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fault Property</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nujiang fault (F1)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~70&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strike&#x02212;slip reverse fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nantinghe fault (F2)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80~90&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lantsang fault (F3)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~52&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N30&#x000b0;W</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wuliangshan fault (F4)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60~70&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NNE</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weixi&#x02013;Weishan fault (F5)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SW</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~70&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NNW</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Binchuan&#x02013;Yongsheng fault (F6)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;50&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nearly NS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip, normal fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Northern Red River fault (F7)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60~85&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N70&#x000b0;W</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip, dip&#x02212;slip reverse fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern Red River fault (F7)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NE</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60~85&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N45&#x000b0;W</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip, dip&#x02212;slip normal fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Western Qujiang fault (F8)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50~75&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N60&#x000b0;W</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip, dip&#x02212;slip reverse fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eastern Qujiang fault (F8)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NW</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60~80&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N60&#x000b0;W</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip, dip&#x02212;slip reverse fault</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anninghe fault (F9)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70~80&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puduhe fault (F10)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70~80&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left&#x02212;lateral reverse strike&#x02212;slip </td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xiaojiang fault (F11)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70~80&#x000b0;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left&#x02212;lateral strike&#x02212;slip, dip&#x02212;slip normal fault</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>