<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="ejsc12237" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Sport Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Sport Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)1536-7290</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EJSC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Journal of Sport Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1746-1391</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-7290</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39644506</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681613</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejsc.12237</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">EJSC12237</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>ORIGINAL PAPER</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Applied Sport Science</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance in 10&#x02010;years&#x02010;old&#x02010;and&#x02010;under athletes in short course national competition</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="ejsc12237-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Gregory A.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9928-217X</contrib-id><xref rid="ejsc12237-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>brownga@unk.edu</email></address></contrib><contrib id="ejsc12237-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>Brandon S.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2285-8361</contrib-id><xref rid="ejsc12237-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ejsc12237-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>Ina</given-names></name><xref rid="ejsc12237-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="ejsc12237-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Physical Activity and Wellness Laboratory</named-content>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Kinesiology and Sports Science</named-content>
<institution>University of Nebraska at Kearney</institution>
<city>Kearney</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Nebraska</named-content>
<country country="US">USA</country>
</aff><aff id="ejsc12237-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">School of Sport</named-content>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Rehabilitation and Exercise Sciences</named-content>
<institution>University of Essex</institution>
<city>Colchester</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Essex</named-content>
<country country="GB">UK</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence</bold>
<break/>
Gregory A. Brown, Department of Kinesiology and Sport Sciences, University of Nebraska at Kearney, 1410 w 26th street, Kearney, NE 68849, USA.<break/>
Email: <email>brownga@unk.edu</email>
<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue seq="20">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejsc.v25.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e12237</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2024 The Author(s). European Journal of Sport Science published by Wiley&#x02010;VCH GmbH on behalf of European College of Sport Science.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2024 The Author(s). European Journal of Sport Science published by Wiley&#x02010;VCH GmbH on behalf of European College of Sport Science.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:EJSC-25-e12237.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The need for sex&#x02010;segregated youth swimming is debated. A previous report indicates that male swimmers aged 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under are 1%&#x02013;2% faster than females in long course freestyle, butterfly, backstroke, and individual medley (IM), but not breaststroke events. Another report indicates that at age 10 males are 1%&#x02013;2.5% faster than females in long course freestyle events. However, there are no evaluations for short course competitions. Therefore, the top eight performances for both sexes from the National Club Swimming Association Age Group Championships (a short course meet) for the years 2016&#x02013;2023 in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group were analyzed. Males were 1.16%&#x02013;2.63% faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; effect sizes 0.376&#x02013;0.596) than females in the 50&#x000a0;yards (yd; 45.7&#x000a0;m), 100 yd (91.4&#x000a0;m), and 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100 and 200 yd IM. There were no significant sex&#x02010;based differences in the 500&#x000a0;yd (457.2&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 50&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, or 50&#x000a0;yd butterfly. The individual fastest time for a female was faster than for a male in the 50, 100, and 500 yd freestyle, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100&#x000a0;yd IM. Although in eight out of 12 events the individual fastest times were from females, in eight out of 12 events the average male times were significantly faster. The present data suggest that although some exceptional individual 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under female swimmers do exist, their performance is not representative of the typical sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="highlights"><title>Highlights</title><p>
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Males in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group were 1.16%&#x02013;2.63% significantly faster than females in the 50&#x000a0;yards (yd; 45.7&#x000a0;M), 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m), and 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd individual medley (IM).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The individual fastest time for a female was faster than for a male in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m), 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m), and 500&#x000a0;yd (457.2&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100&#x000a0;yd IM.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The performance of the fastest under 10&#x000a0;years old female swimmers may not be representative of the overall sex&#x02010;based differences in prepubertal swimming performance.</p></list-item></list>
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd id="ejsc12237-kwd-0001">athletic performance</kwd><kwd id="ejsc12237-kwd-0002">child</kwd><kwd id="ejsc12237-kwd-0003">female</kwd><kwd id="ejsc12237-kwd-0004">humans</kwd><kwd id="ejsc12237-kwd-0005">male</kwd><kwd id="ejsc12237-kwd-0006">sex characteristics</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="1"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="6974"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.1 mode:remove_FC converted:28.12.2024</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body id="ejsc12237-body-0001"><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0010"><label>1</label><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The rationale and need for sex&#x02010;segregated sports has become a controversial topic in recent years. An argument against sex&#x02010;segregated sports is that sex&#x02010;segregation in sports propagates outdated gender stereotypes and is an unnecessary holdover of archaic social factors (Leong &#x00026; Bartlett,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). An argument for sex&#x02010;segregated sports is that the biological differences between males and females gives males inherent athletic advantages, thus sex&#x02010;segregated sports are necessary to protect the safety of female athletes and to provide for fair competition (Hilton &#x00026; Lundberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Hunter et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). The arguments for and against sex segregated sports become even more contentious when prepubertal children are involved because the focus on sports for these children is often recreation, physical activity, character building, and basic skill development rather than competition (Wells &#x00026; Arthur&#x02010;Banning,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0031" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). It is also unclear whether there are inherent differences in physical fitness between prepubertal males and females that influence competitive outcomes.</p><p>Success in athletic competitions can be influenced by physical fitness. Although it has been reported that there are not sex&#x02010;based differences in physical fitness before puberty (Ervin et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), there are a number of other studies indicating that prepubertal males perform better than prepubertal females on tests of muscular strength and endurance, running speed, and aerobic endurance (Catley &#x00026; Tomkinson,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Emeljanovas et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Tambalis et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Tomkinson et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>, <xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Although enhanced physical fitness can contribute to improved swimming performance (Geladas et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Gomez&#x02010;Bruton et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), swimming is a learned skill that requires access to coaching and access to facilities to a much greater extent than do the more innate skills of running, jumping, throwing, and other commonly used activities in physical fitness tests (Olaisen et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).</p><p>In an evaluation of United States of America (USA) Swimming Age Group AAAA long course time standards for all events from 1981 to 2016, Handelsman&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) indicates that males in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group were &#x0223c;1&#x02013;2% faster than females in freestyle, backstroke, butterfly, and individual medley (IM) events, but there was no sex&#x02010;based difference for breaststroke. The data from Handelsman indicates that sex&#x02010;based differences for all events increase precipitously from age 11 onwards leading him to conclude that it is not until after the onset of puberty and concomitant increase in testosterone that causes male sex&#x02010;based athletic advantages emerge. In the only other evaluation of pre&#x02010;pubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in competitive swimming performance, Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) evaluated the all&#x02010;time top 100 ranked U.S. freestyle swimming performance times for both males and females ages 5&#x02013;18&#x000a0;years in the 50&#x02013;1500&#x000a0;m events and concluded that in children under age 10 the top 5 females were faster than the top 5 males, and there were no differences between the 10th&#x02013;50th place females. However, at age 10, the top 5 males were 2.5% faster than females and the 10th&#x02013;50th ranked males were 1.0% faster than females. Neither of these evaluations included the short course events, Senefeld only evaluated freestyle events, and neither of these evaluations focused on race times for swimmers at the same swim meet.</p><p>Therefore, given the ongoing debate about whether there are sex&#x02010;based differences in athletic performance before puberty necessitating sex segregated sport, the limited scholarly evaluations of swimming performance in prepubertal children, and a lack of scholarly evaluation of short course swimming times in children aged 10 and under, an evaluation of competitive swimming performance in short course events in prepubescent children is warranted. The purpose of this project was to determine if there are sex&#x02010;based differences in short course swimming events in athletes ages 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under (who can reasonably be assumed to be prepubertal) in a National Championship meet. The primary hypothesis was that males swim faster than females in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group in short course national championship competition. A secondary purpose of this project was to compare the differences between finishing order within males and within females to the difference in performance between males and females. The secondary hypothesis was that the percent difference between sexes is greater than the difference within sexes in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group swim in short course national championship competition.</p></sec><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0020"><label>2</label><title>METHODS</title><p>The eight fastest finalist times for males and females for each event each year in the National Club Swimming Association (NCSA,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>) Age Group Championships for the years 2016&#x02013;2023 were downloaded in one&#x02010;year brackets from the NCSA webpage (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.gomotionapp.com/team/recndncsa/page/past--archived-meet-results/past--archived-meet-results2" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gomotionapp.com/team/recndncsa/page/past&#x02010;&#x02010;archived&#x02010;meet&#x02010;results/past&#x02010;&#x02010;archived&#x02010;meet&#x02010;results2</ext-link>) between August 30 and December 31, 2023. The NCSA Age Group Championships were selected because of the easily accessible records for past swim meets found on their website, it was desirable to compare athletes swimming at the same swim meets, and the NCSA Age Group Championships is a national event with athletes required to make certified qualifying times to be eligible to compete, therefore this meet should represent some of the best under age 10 swimmers in the USA. The eight fastest finalist times were selected as these should correspond to the finalist heat in NCSA Age Group Championship events. The NCSA Age Group Championship started in 2016 and was not held in 2020 due to the COVID 19 pandemic, so the present data represents all available data in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group to date for this swim meet.</p><p>Times for 56 males and 56 females were available for the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m), 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m), and 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50&#x000a0;yd butterfly, 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd IM. There were times available for 47 males and 51 females for the 500&#x000a0;yd (457.2&#x000a0;m) freestyle due to there being only two male competitors and three female competitors in 2021, and only five male competitors in 2016. There were times available for 52 males and 56 females for the 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke due to there being only five male competitors in 2021, and one of those was disqualified. There were times available for 55 males and 55 females for the 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke due to there being only seven male and seven female competitors in 2021. There were times available for 56 males and 55 females in the 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly due to there being only seven female competitors in 2021.</p><p>All procedures for this project accessed public information and did not require ethical review in accordance with the Code of Federal Regulations, 45 CFR 46.102, and the Declaration of Helsinki.</p><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0030"><label>2.1</label><title>Calculations and Statistics</title><p>Data are presented as means&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation. When necessary, times were converted from minutes:seconds to seconds and all times are reported in seconds. Data for times for all males and females in each event were compared using a two&#x02010;tailed two&#x02010;sample unequal variance <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02010;test (SigmaStat 4.0, Systat Software). Effect size was calculated using Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> when the sample sizes in each sex were the same, and Hedges' <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> when the sample sizes were not. Percent difference between the male and female performances in each event were calculated using the equation described by Millard&#x02010;Stafford (Millard&#x02010;Stafford et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).
<disp-formula id="ejsc12237-disp-0001">
<mml:math id="jats-math-1" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Male</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>time</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>female</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>time</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Male</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>time</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p><p>For comparison of first versus second, second versus third, third versus fourth, and so on through eighth place, the percent difference between the finishing places in each event were calculated using the equation
<disp-formula id="ejsc12237-disp-0002">
<mml:math id="jats-math-2" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Time</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>second</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>place</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>time</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>first</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>place</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Time</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>first</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>place</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0040"><label>3</label><title>RESULTS</title><p>Males were faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) by 1.69&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.46% than females in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m), 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m), and 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd IM. There were no significant differences between males and females in 500&#x000a0;yd (4572&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 50&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, 50&#x000a0;yd butterfly. The individual fastest time for a female was faster than the individuals fastest time for a male in the 50, 100, and 500&#x000a0;yd freestyle, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100&#x000a0;yd IM, whereas the individual fastest time for a male was faster than the individual fastest time for a female in the 200&#x000a0;yd freestyle, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, and 200&#x000a0;yd IM.</p><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0050"><label>3.1</label><title>Freestyle</title><p>Males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 27.72&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.64&#x000a0;s) were 1.34% faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.012; Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.439) than females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 28.09&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.87&#x000a0;s) in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m) freestyle event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). One female (25.76&#x000a0;s) was faster than the fastest male (26.01&#x000a0;s) in the 50&#x000a0;yd freestyle event.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="ejsc12237-fig-0001"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>Box plots depicting the finishing times for the 8 finalists in the freestyle events for the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group in the National Club Swimming Association Age Group Championships during the years 2016&#x02013;2023*. The boxes include the first and third quartiles, with the median shown as a solid black line. The whiskers represent the range of data within 1.5* the interquartile range beyond the box boundaries. The solid lines between boxes connect the means. (A). 50 yards (45.7&#x000a0;m) freestyle. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.012 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56), effect size (Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.439 (B). 100 yards (91.4&#x000a0;m) freestyle. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.049 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56), effect size (Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.376 (C). 200 yards (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.014 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56), effect size (Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.472 (D). 500 yards (457.2&#x000a0;m) freestyle. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.125 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;47) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;47), effect size (Hedges' <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.313. *This swimming meet was not held in 2020 due to the COVID&#x02010;19 pandemic.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EJSC-25-e12237-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig><p>Males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 60.59&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.78&#x000a0;s) were 1.16% faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.049; Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.376) than females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 61.29&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.94&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m) freestyle event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). One female (56.91&#x000a0;s) was faster than the fastest male (57.06&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd freestyle event.</p><p>Males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 132.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.43&#x000a0;s) were 1.56% faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.014; Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.472) than females <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; (134.33&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.12&#x000a0;s) in the 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle event (Figure&#x000a0;[<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>]). Two males (124.48 and 124.69&#x000a0;s) were faster than the fastest female (125.3&#x000a0;s) in the 200&#x000a0;yd freestyle event.</p><p>There were no significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.125; Hedges' <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.313) between males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;47; 352.57&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.37&#x000a0;s) and females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;51; 355.61&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;10.79&#x000a0;s) in the 500&#x000a0;yd (457.2&#x000a0;m) freestyle event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1D</xref>). Four females (331.80, 332.08, 332.55, and 334.39&#x000a0;s) were faster than the fastest male (335.86&#x000a0;s) in the 500&#x000a0;yd freestyle event.</p></sec><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0060"><label>3.2</label><title>Backstroke and breaststroke</title><p>There were no significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.055; Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.372) between males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 31.69&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.95&#x000a0;s) and females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 32.07&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.09&#x000a0;s) in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m) backstroke event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>). One female (28.63&#x000a0;s) was faster than the fastest male (29.38&#x000a0;s) in the 50 yd backstroke event.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="ejsc12237-fig-0002"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Box plots depicting the finishing times for the eight finalists in the backstroke and breaststroke events for the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group in the National Club Swimming Association Age Group Championships during the years 2016&#x02013;2023*. The boxes include the first and third quartiles, with the median shown as a solid black line. The whiskers represent the range of data within 1.5* the interquartile range beyond the box boundaries. The solid lines between boxes connect the means. (A). 50 yards (45.7&#x000a0;m) backstroke. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.055 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56), effect size (Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.372 (B). 100 yards (91.4&#x000a0;m) backstroke. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.040 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55), effect size (Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.396 (C). 50 yards (45.7&#x000a0;m) breaststroke. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.049 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;52) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56), effect size (Hedges' <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.382 (D). 100 yards (91.4&#x000a0;m) breaststroke. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.449 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55), effect size (Cohen's d)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.145. *This swimming meet was not held in 2020 due to the COVID&#x02010;19 pandemic.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EJSC-25-e12237-g003" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig><p>Males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55; 68.36&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.64&#x000a0;s) were 1.44% faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.004; Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.396) than females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55; 69.35&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.35&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m) freestyle event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2B</xref>). One female (61.92&#x000a0;s) was faster than the fastest male (63.12&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke event.</p><p>Males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;52; 36.20&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.45&#x000a0;s) were 1.72% faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.049; Hedges' <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.382) than females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 36.82&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.77&#x000a0;s) in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m) breaststroke event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2C</xref>). Two males (32.90 and 33.06&#x000a0;s) were faster than the fastest female (33.11&#x000a0;s) in the 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke event.</p><p>There were no significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.449; Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.145) between males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55; 80.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.12&#x000a0;s) and females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55; 79.92&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.28&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m) breaststroke event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2D</xref>). Two males (70.67 and 71.11&#x000a0;s) were faster than the fastest female (72.13&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke event.</p></sec><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0070"><label>3.3</label><title>Butterfly and individual medley</title><p>There were no significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.267; Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.207) between males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 30.48&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.95&#x000a0;s) and females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 30.71&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.25&#x000a0;s) in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m) butterfly event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). Two females (28.53 and 28.57&#x000a0;s) were faster than the fastest male (28.72&#x000a0;s) in the 50&#x000a0;yd butterfly event.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="ejsc12237-fig-0003"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Box plots depicting the finishing times for the eight finalists in the butterfly and individual medley (IM) events for the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group in the National Club Swimming Association Age Group Championships during the years 2016&#x02013;2023*. The boxes include the first and third quartiles, with the median shown as a solid black line. The whiskers represent the range of data within 1.5* the interquartile range beyond the box boundaries. The solid lines between boxes connect the means. (A). 50 yards (45.7&#x000a0;m) butterfly. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.267 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56), effect size (Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.207 (B). 100 yards (91.4&#x000a0;m) butterfly. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55), effect size (Hedges' <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.590 (C). 100 yards (91.4&#x000a0;m) IM. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.006 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56), effect size (Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.532 (D). 200 yards (182.9&#x000a0;m) IM. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.004 for males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56) versus females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56), effect size (Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.550. *This swimming meet was not held in 2020 due to the COVID&#x02010;19 pandemic.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EJSC-25-e12237-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5"/></fig><p>Males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 67.77&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.38&#x000a0;s) were 2.63% faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002; Hedges' <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.590) than females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;55; 69.55&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.55&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m) butterfly event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>). One female (62.33&#x000a0;s) was faster than the fastest male (62.73&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly event.</p><p>Males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 69.13&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.00&#x000a0;s) were 1.67% faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.006; Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.532) than females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 70.29&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.35&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m) IM event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3C</xref>). One female (64.79&#x000a0;s) was faster than the fastest male (64.94&#x000a0;s) in the 100&#x000a0;yd IM.</p><p>Males (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 149.06&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.31&#x000a0;s) were 2.03% faster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.004; Cohen's <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.550) than females (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56; 152.09&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.71&#x000a0;s) in the 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) IM event (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3D</xref>). Two males (138.91 and 139.15&#x000a0;s) were faster than the fastest female (139.74&#x000a0;s) in the 200&#x000a0;yd IM event.</p></sec><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0080"><label>3.4</label><title>Percentage differences between finishing positions</title><p>The percentage differences in finishing times between those individuals who would receive medals (i.e., first&#x02010;second place, and second&#x02010;third place) were 1.46%&#x02013;1.58% (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The percentage differences in finishing times between the slowest medalist and the first non&#x02010;medalist (i.e., third&#x02010;fourth place) were 1.27%&#x02013;1.33%. In contrast the percentage differences in finishing times between the non&#x02010;medalists (i.e., fourth&#x02010;fifth, fifth&#x02010;sixth, sixth&#x02010;seventh, seventh&#x02010;eighth) were 0.60%&#x02013;0.85%.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="ejsc12237-tbl-0001" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Percent differences in placing times for the finalists in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group at the National Club Swimming Association Age Group Championships for the years 2016&#x02013;2023<xref rid="ejsc12237-note-0002" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref> for all events pooled together.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Place comparison</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All swimmers</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Females</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Males</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First&#x02013;second</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.54%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.62%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.48%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Second&#x02013;third</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.60%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.71%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.50%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Third&#x02013;fourth</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.45%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.39%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.53%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fourth&#x02013;fifth</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.28%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.37%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fifth&#x02013;sixth</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.29%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.20%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.36%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sixth&#x02013;seventh</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.32%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.26%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.34%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Seventh&#x02013;eighth</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.22%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.26%</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.18%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot id="ejsc12237-ntgp-0001"><fn id="ejsc12237-note-0001"><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Note</italic>: Data are means&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviation.</p></fn><fn id="ejsc12237-note-0002"><label>
<sup>a</sup>
</label><p>This swim meet was not held in 2020 due to the COVID&#x02010;19 pandemic.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0090"><label>4</label><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The present data indicate that at a national level short course youth swimming meet over seven years of competition when the 8 fastest times in each event for the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group are evaluated, males were 1.16%&#x02013;2.63% significantly faster than females in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7), 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4), and 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd IM. There were no significant sex&#x02010;based differences in the 500&#x000a0;yd (457.2&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 50&#x000a0;yd butterfly, 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, or 50&#x000a0;yd backstroke (although male times in the 50&#x000a0;yd backstroke were nearly significantly faster at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.055). Therefore, because males were faster than females in most, but not all, events, the primary hypothesis that in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group males swim faster than females in short course national championship competition can be partially, but not fully, accepted. The individual fastest time for a female was faster than for a male in the 50, 100, and 500&#x000a0;yd freestyle, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100&#x000a0;yd IM, but there were no events in which the female times were significantly faster than male times. Therefore, the outstanding performance of some individual very talented female swimmers at a national level short course youth swimming meet may not be representative of the overall sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance in children.</p><p>In the present data, males were 1.16%&#x02013;2.63% significantly faster than females in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m), 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m), and 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd IM, with no sex&#x02010;based differences in the 500&#x000a0;yd (457.2&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 50&#x000a0;yd butterfly, 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, or 50&#x000a0;yd backstroke. The within sex differences were 1.27%&#x02013;1.58% for first through fourth place and were 0.63%&#x02013;0.83% for fourth through eighth place. Therefore, the secondary hypothesis that between sex differences are greater than within sex differences in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group in short course national championship competition can be partially, but not fully, accepted. The data of Handelsman&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) mostly agree with the present data in that he found that males in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group were &#x0223c;1&#x02013;2% faster than females in long course freestyle, backstroke, butterfly, and IM events, but there were no sex&#x02010;based differences for breaststroke. Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) did not break down the data for each event, but indicates that in long course freestyle events the top five ranked females under 10&#x000a0;years old were faster than the top five ranked males under age 10, and there were no differences between the 10th&#x02013;50th ranked males and females under age 10. However, Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) indicate that at age 10 the top five ranked males were 2.5% faster than the top five ranked females, and the 10th&#x02013;50th ranked males were 1% faster than the 10th&#x02013;50th ranked females, which is similar to the present data showing that males in the 10 and under age group were significantly 1.16%&#x02013;1.56% 50, 100, and 200&#x000a0;yd freestyle events. Although not statistically significant, in the present data for the 500&#x000a0;yd freestyle the times for males were 0.90% faster than the times for females, which closely approximates the overall sex&#x02010;based difference in freestyle performance reported by Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Based on the present, and previous data, males in the 10 and under&#x02010;age group swim faster than females of the same age in most, but not all, swimming events and distances.</p><p>The USA Swimming records for all&#x02010;time short course best performances in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group (as of January 8, 2024), indicate that males are 1.64&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.88% faster than females in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m), 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m), 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m), and 500&#x000a0;yd (457.2&#x000a0;m) freestyle, the 50&#x000a0;yd backstroke, the 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, the 50 and 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and the 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd IM (USA Swimming,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). These records also indicate that the all&#x02010;time best performance for a female in the 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke is 1.13% faster than the all&#x02010;time performance for a male. The USA Swimming records for all&#x02010;time long course best performances in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group (as of January 8, 2024), indicate that males are 1.94%&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.25% faster than females in the 50, 100, 200, and 400&#x000a0;m freestyle, the 50 and 100&#x000a0;m backstroke, the 50&#x000a0;m breaststroke, the 100&#x000a0;m butterfly, and the 200&#x000a0;yd IM (USA Swimming,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>). These same records indicate that all&#x02010;time best performances for a female are 1.56&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.17% faster than the all&#x02010;time best performance for a male in the 100&#x000a0;m breaststroke and 50&#x000a0;m butterfly. In addition to records of all&#x02010;time best performances, USA Swimming produces a chart of motivational times (USA Swimming,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>) based upon historical performance data that sets times for swimmers in both sexes and every age group in every swimming event, which can then be used to classify the swimmers into progressively faster categories of B, BB, A, AA, AAA, and AAAA. The motivational times can be used by athletes to help them progress into higher levels of competition and can also be used by meet directors to limit participation to swimmers of specific categories. For the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group in all categories across 11 long course events and 12 short course events the boys' motivational times are faster than girls' by an average 1.8%, with the exceptions of the 50 yd backstroke where the girls' times are 0.4% faster for the long course and 1.0% faster for the short course. Collectively, the evaluations of Handelsman&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), Senefeld (Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), the records for all&#x02010;time best performances from USA Swimming (USA Swimming,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0029" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>), the motivational times from USA Swimming (USA Swimming,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>), and the present data all indicate that in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group males swim faster than females in the majority of events. It is particularly common for males in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group to swim faster than females in freestyle and IM events.</p><p>In the present and previous data, the sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance in prepubertal children are between 1.0% and 3.5% with males swimming faster than females in most, but not all, events. Hilton and Lundberg report that adult males swim 11%&#x02013;13% faster than adult females, but did not differentiate by event (Hilton &#x00026; Lundberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>). Millard&#x02010;Stafford indicates that in US Olympic swimming trials, adult males swim 11.2%&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.7% faster than adult females, with greater sex&#x02010;based differences in the sprinting rather than endurance events (Millard&#x02010;Stafford et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Hunter et&#x000a0;al.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>) concurs with Millard&#x02010;Stafford that in adults, the sex&#x02010;based performance differences are largest in sprint swimming events with the difference being 13.2% for 50&#x000a0;m events and decreasing to 5.7% for 1500&#x000a0;m events. These adult male advantages, particularly in short distance swimming events, are attributed to male having up to twice as much muscular power than females which is facilitated by up to twice as much muscle mass in males (Hunter et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). In prepubescent children males have approximately 10% more lean body mass than females (McManus &#x00026; Armstrong,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Staiano &#x00026; Katzmarzyk,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) which corresponds to smaller sex&#x02010;based differences in muscle power than in adults (Catley &#x00026; Tomkinson,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Tomkinson et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), which helps explain why the sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance are much smaller in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group than in adults.</p><p>In adults, the sex&#x02010;based differences in competitive running and swimming performance are similarly in the 5%&#x02013;13% range for both running and swimming (Hilton &#x00026; Lundberg,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">2021</xref>; Hunter et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>; Millard&#x02010;Stafford et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). In contrast, it has recently been reported that prepubescent males run 3%&#x02013;6% faster in track competition than same aged females (Atkinson et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>; Brown et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">2024</xref>), and yet the present and previous data indicate that the sex&#x02010;based difference in swimming performance in prepubescent children is 1%&#x02013;3.5%.</p><p>In comparison to running, the smaller prepubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming may be partially explained by noting that swimming is a learned skill (Olaisen et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Young swimmers' performance is a multifactorial phenomenon where different factors, such as anthropometry, kinematics, and efficiency, contribute at varying levels (Morais et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). However, at an early age, there may be individualized variation in kinematic measures, based on training levels (Morais et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), and varying levels of access to facilities and coaching to a much greater extent than does the innate skill of running (Olaisen et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). As such, Duke et&#x000a0;al.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>) observed that in addition to sex, school type was a major factor influencing swimming skills since some schools, particularly smaller or less affluent schools, lack aquatic facilities. Those authors also observed that frequency of participation in aquatic activity and prior negative aquatic experiences also contributed to the smaller prepubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance than other sports. It also appears that more females participate in competitive swimming as children than do males (Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), which can increase the talent pool and level of competition resulting in better performance. It is also speculated that females are more likely to focus solely on swimming and are more likely to enjoy training for competitive swimming (Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), which may also result in better performance. Therefore, it is plausible that increasing the time and type of swimming practice may allow females to overcome some, but not all, of the prepubertal sex&#x02010;based anatomical and physiological differences causing sex&#x02010;based differences in athletic performance. This evidence suggests that other environmental factors, rather than intrinsic ones (i.e., anthropometrics, such as arm span), are important determinants (Morais et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) that could allow for some individual under 10 female athletes to excel at such early ages in swimming. In addition, there is evidence that the changes of these determinants over time occur in a nonlinear fashion may account for the reason for only some exceptional performances in individual under 10 female athletes (Morais et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Despite these outliers of exceptionally performing individual under 10 female athletes, there is evidence indicating that when male and female children engage in the same amount and intensity of physical activity the males develop greater physical fitness (Dencker et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Eiberg et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), which may predispose males to better athletic performance.</p><p>It has been suggested that the prepubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in physical fitness and athletic performance are due to males participating in a greater amount of physical activity, higher intensity physical activity, and more sports than do females (Hunter et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). Supporting this suggestion, Chen et&#x000a0;al. (Chen et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) observed in fifth&#x02010;grade children that males spend more time engaged in unstructured physical activity than females, but there was not a sex&#x02010;based difference in time spent in organized physical education classes, sports, and dance. Hyde et&#x000a0;al.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) reported that 60.9% of male children and 54.4% of female children engaged in organized sports whereas Belcher et&#x000a0;al.&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) reported that in children 6 to 11&#x02010;years&#x02010;old, males participate in more moderate to vigorous physical activity than do females. Collectively, these sources support the notion that prepubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in athletic performance can at least be partially explained by higher levels of sport participation and more strenuous physical activity in males than in females. However, in 6 to 7&#x02010;year&#x02010;old children (Eiberg et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) and in 8 to 11&#x02010;year&#x02010;old children (Dencker et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), the sex&#x02010;based differences in maximal oxygen consumption and body composition were not entirely explained by differences in physical activity. Although greater engagement in physical activity and sports is likely to contribute to better sports performance (providing that overtraining syndrome is avoided), and there are some data that indicate male children engage in more sports and physical activity than females, it is not possible to disregard prepubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in anatomy and physiology also as causative factors for prepubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in athletic performance.</p><p>In the present data, evaluating 7&#x000a0;years of national level children's short course swimming competition, the males were 1.16%&#x02013;2.63% significantly faster than females in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7&#x000a0;m), 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4&#x000a0;m), and 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd IM. Also, in the present data the percentage differences in finishing times between those individuals who would receive medals were 1.46%&#x02013;1.58%. The percentage difference in finishing times between the non&#x02010;medalists was smaller (0.60%&#x02013;0.85%) than the difference between medalists. Collectively, these data indicate that the time differences between males and females in the 50, 100, and 200&#x000a0;yd freestyle, 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd IM are equal to or larger than the time differences between medalists, and are two&#x02010;to&#x02010;three times larger than the differences between non&#x02010;medalists suggesting that the between sex time differences are larger than the within sex differences.</p><p>Strengths of the current research are that it represents an evaluation of real&#x02010;world competition data for swimming performance in presumably elite prepubertal females and males in short&#x02010;course events. The data from the male and female athletes were obtained from the same swim meets which should eliminate possible differences due to seasonal variation (i.e., early, mid, or late season) in performance times. Aside from head&#x02010;to&#x02010;head competition, these data provide the next best possibility for evaluating sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance in these athletes and events. The present data also represent, to our knowledge, the first scholarly evaluation of sex&#x02010;based differences in short&#x02010;course competition in elite prepubertal females and males.</p><p>Limitations of the current research are that the present data are based on swim meet records, which offer no insight into the anthropometric characteristics of the athletes other than sex and age. The event records also must be taken at face value, with no knowledge of the accuracy and precision of the timing used for each event. However, the swim meets all occurred under the auspices of NCSA, which has standards for timing and for athlete eligibility. Although these swim meets were labeled as national championships, it is not clear that the best juvenile athletes from across the country are represented among the participants (which is a common challenge in children's sports due to travel costs and family circumstances associated with attending an event outside the immediate local area). However, these above&#x02010;mentioned limitations can also be applied to the data evaluated by Handelsman&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) and Senefeld (Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and are inherent to the records of best performance for any sport.</p><p>Although the current data indicate that prepubertal males swim faster than females in most, but not all, short course events, these data do not provide insight into why these sex&#x02010;based differences in performance occur. For example, the lack of sex&#x02010;based differences in the 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke (91.4&#x000a0;m), 500&#x000a0;yd freestyle (457.2&#x000a0;m), and 50&#x000a0;yd butterfly (45.7&#x000a0;m) are intriguing, but difficult to explain. Handelsman&#x000a0;(<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) also observed no sex&#x02010;based differences in the 100&#x000a0;m breaststroke in the 10&#x02010;and&#x02010;under age group, whereas there were &#x0223c;1% sex&#x02010;based differences in all other events. However, the analysis of Handelsman did not include freestyle events over 200&#x000a0;m and only included 100&#x000a0;m for backstroke, breaststroke, and butterfly. The determinants of swimming performance such as swimming economy and energy requirements, propulsive force capacity, and drag force have been extensively studied and could be analyzed to determine why there are and are not sex&#x02010;based based differences in prepubertal swimmers (Vilas&#x02010;Boas,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0030" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>). For example, females are thought to have buoyancy advantages due to higher percent body fat and are also more fatigue resistant than males (Hunter et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>), which may provide advantages for long duration and energy intense events such as the 500 yd freestyle and 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke. Furthermore, the better technique of young female swimmers due to more practice (Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) may allow young female swimmers to compensate for the strength and power advantages of males in the 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke and 500&#x000a0;yd freestyle. But the concept of greater fatigue resistance in young female swimmers does not explain the lack of sex&#x02010;based differences in 50&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and conflicts with the presently observed sex&#x02010;based differences in the 100 yd butterfly, 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd freestyle, 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd IM all of which have similar of longer durations than the 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke. Future research investigating the causative factors for the prepubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance could evaluate differences in body composition, anthropometrics, time dedicated to swimming specific training, and skill factors that influence swimming performance. Furthermore, the present and previous investigations (Handelsman,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Senefeld et&#x000a0;al.,&#x000a0;<xref rid="ejsc12237-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) of prepubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance have been limited to data from the USA. Therefore, evaluations for prepubertal sex&#x02010;based differences in swimming performance in other countries would be extremely valuable for informing discussion regarding the necessity (or lack thereof) for sex segregated youth swimming competition. From a practical standpoint, the current research provides coaches and sport scientists with another source of information that can be used to help athletes establish target times to help determine the likelihood of success in a national championship swim meet. The present data can also help inform policy discussions on the&#x000a0;necessity of maintaining sex segregated youth swimming competitions.</p></sec><sec id="ejsc12237-sec-0100"><label>5</label><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>The present data indicates that prepubertal males swim 1.16%&#x02013;2.63% significantly faster than females in the 50&#x000a0;yd (45.7), 100&#x000a0;yd (91.4), and 200&#x000a0;yd (182.9&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 100&#x000a0;yd backstroke, 50&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, 100&#x000a0;yd butterfly, and 100 and 200&#x000a0;yd IM, but not in the 500&#x000a0;yd (457.2&#x000a0;m) freestyle, 50&#x000a0;yd butterfly, 100&#x000a0;yd breaststroke, or 50&#x000a0;yd backstroke (although the differences in the 50&#x000a0;yd backstroke approached significance). The present data do not explain why there are sex&#x02010;based differences in some, but not all, of these events. Based on the present and previous data indicating that prepubertal males swim faster than prepubertal females in most events, there seems to be little justification to eliminate sex segregated competition in youth swimming. Furthermore, this study serves as a valuable contribution to our comprehension of the intricate interplay between sex differences and swimming performance in prepubertal children. Although further research is imperative to refine and expand upon our current understanding, the findings presented here underscore the significance of considering sex&#x02010;specific factors in the assessment of swimming performance in prepubertal children. Acknowledging and investigating these differences not only advances our knowledge in sports science but also holds potential implications for training strategies tailored to individual needs. As we delve deeper into this realm, the multifaceted nature of sex&#x02010;related influences on swimming performance in prepubertal children becomes increasingly apparent, allowing for more targeted and effective approaches in the pursuit of athletic safety, inclusion, and excellence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="ejsc12237-sec-0120"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</title><p>Dr. Brandon Shaw and Dr. Ina Shaw have no conflicts of interest to declare. Dr. Greg Brown declares that he is currently serving as an expert witness in seven different legal cases in the United States regarding the inclusion of transgender identified males (i.e., trans women) in female sports. No funding that supported this project as part of service as an expert witness was received, his declarations as an expert witness do not include the data presented in this manuscript, and his service as an expert witness is not reliant upon publishing this manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="ejsc12237-sec-0110"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>No funding or outside support was provided for this project.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="ejsc12237-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Atkinson</surname>, <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. J.</given-names>
<surname>James</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. E.</given-names>
<surname>Quinn</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. W.</given-names>
<surname>Senefeld</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. K.</given-names>
<surname>Hunter</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Sex Differences in Track and Field Elite Youth</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Medicine &#x00026; Science in Sports &#x00026; Exercise</source>
<volume>56</volume>(<issue>8</issue>): <fpage>1390</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1397</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0000000000003423</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38595163</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Belcher</surname>, <given-names>B. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Berrigan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. W.</given-names>
<surname>Dodd</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. A.</given-names>
<surname>Emken</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.&#x02010;P.</given-names>
<surname>Chou</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Spruijt&#x02010;Metz</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Physical Activity in US Youth: Effect of Race/Ethnicity, Age, Gender, and Weight Status</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Medicine &#x00026; Science in Sports &#x00026; Exercise</source>
<volume>42</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>2211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2221</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0b013e3181e1fba9</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21084930</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Brown</surname>, <given-names>G. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. S.</given-names>
<surname>Shaw</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Shaw</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2024</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Sex&#x02010;Based Differences in Track Running Distances of 100, 200, 400, 800, and 1500 m in the 8&#x02010;and&#x02010;Under and 9&#x02010;10&#x02010;Year&#x02010;Old Age Groups</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>European Journal of Sport Science</source>
<volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejsc.12075</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Catley</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>G. R.</given-names>
<surname>Tomkinson</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Normative Health&#x02010;Related Fitness Values for Children: Analysis of 85347 Test Results on 9&#x02010;17&#x02010;Year&#x02010;Old Australians since 1985</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>British Journal of Sports Medicine</source>
<volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>98</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>108</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2011-090218</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22021354</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Hammond&#x02010;Bennett</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Hypnar</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Mason</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Health&#x02010;Related Physical Fitness and Physical Activity in Elementary School Students</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>BMC Public Health</source>
<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>195</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-018-5107-4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29378563</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Dencker</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>O.</given-names>
<surname>Thorsson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. K.</given-names>
<surname>Karlsson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Lind&#x000e9;n</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Eiberg</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Wollmer</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L. B.</given-names>
<surname>Andersen</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2007</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Gender Differences and Determinants of Aerobic Fitness in Children Aged 8&#x02013;11 Years</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>European Journal of Applied Physiology</source>
<volume>99</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-006-0310-x</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17024465</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Duke</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Calverley</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Petrass</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Peters</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Moncrieff</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Konjarski</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Matthews</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2023</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>A Systematic Review of Demographic and Background Factors Associated With The Development of Children's Aquatic Competence</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Injury Epidemiology</source>
<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>42</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40621-023-00447-4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37553586</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Eiberg</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Hasselstrom</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Gronfeldt</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Froberg</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Svensson</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L. B.</given-names>
<surname>Andersen</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2005</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Maximum Oxygen Uptake and Objectively Measured Physical Activity in Danish Children 6&#x02013;7 Years of Age: The Copenhagen school Child Intervention Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>British Journal of Sports Medicine</source>
<volume>39</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>730</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsm.2004.015230</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16183768</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Emeljanovas</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Mieziene</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V. J.</given-names>
<surname>Cesnaitiene</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Fjortoft</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Kj&#x000f8;nniksen</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Physical Fitness and Anthropometric Values Among Lithuanian Primary School Children: Population&#x02010;Based Cross&#x02010;Sectional Study</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>The Journal of Strength and Conditioning Research</source>
<volume>34</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>414</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>421</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1519/JSC.0000000000003387</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31725558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Ervin</surname>, <given-names>R. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. D.</given-names>
<surname>Fryar</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.&#x02010;Y.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>I. M.</given-names>
<surname>Miller</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>C. L.</given-names>
<surname>Ogden</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Strength and Body Weight in US Children and Adolescents</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Pediatrics</source>
<volume>134</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>e782</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e789</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2014-0794</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25157016</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Geladas</surname>, <given-names>N. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G. P.</given-names>
<surname>Nassis</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Pavlicevic</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2005</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Somatic and Physical Traits Affecting Sprint Swimming Performance in Young Swimmers</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Sports Medicine</source>
<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>144</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2004-817862</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15726490</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Gomez&#x02010;Bruton</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Matute&#x02010;Llorente</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Pardos&#x02010;Mainer</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Gonzalez&#x02010;Aguero</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Gomez&#x02010;Cabello</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
<surname>Casajus</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Vicente&#x02010;Rodriguez</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2016</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Factors Affecting Children and Adolescents 50 Meter Performance in Freestyle Swimming</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>The Journal of Sports Medicine and Physical Fitness</source>
<volume>56</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>1439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1447</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26398204</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Handelsman</surname>, <given-names>D. J.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Sex Differences in Athletic Performance Emerge Coinciding With the Onset of Male Puberty</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Clinical Endocrinology</source>
<volume>87</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cen.13350</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28397355</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Hilton</surname>, <given-names>E. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>T. R.</given-names>
<surname>Lundberg</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2021</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Transgender Women in the Female Category of Sport: Perspectives on Testosterone Suppression and Performance Advantage</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Sports Medicine</source>
<volume>51</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>214</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-020-01389-3</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33289906</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Hunter</surname>, <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>S Angadi</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Bhargava</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Harper</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. L.</given-names>
<surname>Hirschberg</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>D Levine</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>L. Moreau</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2023</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Biological Basis of Sex Differences in Athletic Performance: Consensus Statement for the American College of Sports Medicine</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Medicine &#x00026; Science in Sports &#x00026; Exercise</source>
<volume>55</volume>(<issue>12</issue>): <fpage>2328</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2360</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/MSS.0000000000003300</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37772882</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Hyde</surname>, <given-names>E. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. D.</given-names>
<surname>Omura</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
<surname>Fulton</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. M.</given-names>
<surname>Lee</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. L.</given-names>
<surname>Piercy</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. A.</given-names>
<surname>Carlson</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2020</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Disparities in Youth Sports Participation in the U.S., 2017&#x02010;2018</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>American Journal of Preventive Medicine</source>
<volume>59</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>e207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e210</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2020.05.011</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32741540</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Leong</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Bartlett</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Sex Segregation in Sports as a Public Health Issue</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Cardazzo Law Review</source>
<volume>40</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>44</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>McManus</surname>, <given-names>A. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Armstrong</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Physiology of Elite Young Female Athletes</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Medicine and Sport Science</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000320626</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21178365</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Millard&#x02010;Stafford</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. E.</given-names>
<surname>Swanson</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. T.</given-names>
<surname>Wittbrodt</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Nature versus Nurture: Have Performance Gaps Between Men and Women Reached an Asymptote?</article-title>&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Sports Physiology and Performance</source>
<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>530</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2017-0866</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29466055</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Morais</surname>, <given-names>J. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
<surname>Silva</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. A.</given-names>
<surname>Marinho</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V. P.</given-names>
<surname>Lopes</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>T. M.</given-names>
<surname>Barbosa</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Determinant Factors of Long&#x02010;Term Performance Development in Young Swimmers</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Sports Physiology and Performance</source>
<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>198</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>205</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2015-0420</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27196954</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="ejsc12237-cit-0021">
<collab collab-type="authors">National Club Swimming Association</collab>
. <year>2024</year>. <article-title>Meets and Results</article-title>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.gomotionapp.com/team/recndncsa/page/events#/team-events/past" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.gomotionapp.com/team/recndncsa/page/events#/team&#x02010;events/past</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Olaisen</surname>, <given-names>R. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Flocke</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Love</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Learning to Swim: Role of Gender, Age and Practice in Latino Children, Ages 3&#x02013;14</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Injury Prevention</source>
<volume>24</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>134</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/injuryprev-2016-042171</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28446511</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Senefeld</surname>, <given-names>J. W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. J.</given-names>
<surname>Clayburn</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. E.</given-names>
<surname>Baker</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. E.</given-names>
<surname>Carter</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. W.</given-names>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. J.</given-names>
<surname>Joyner</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2019</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Sex Differences in Youth Elite Swimming</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>14</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <elocation-id>e0225724</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0225724</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31756208</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Staiano</surname>, <given-names>A. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P. T.</given-names>
<surname>Katzmarzyk</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Ethnic and Sex Differences in Body Fat and Visceral and Subcutaneous Adiposity in Children and Adolescents</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>International Journal of Obesity</source>
<volume>36</volume>(<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>1261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1269</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ijo.2012.95</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22710928</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Tambalis</surname>, <given-names>K. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. B.</given-names>
<surname>Panagiotakos</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Psarra</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Daskalakis</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. A.</given-names>
<surname>Kavouras</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N.</given-names>
<surname>Geladas</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Tokmakidis</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L. S.</given-names>
<surname>Sidossis</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L. S.</given-names>
<surname>Sidossis</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2016</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Physical Fitness Normative Values for 6&#x02010;18&#x02010;Year&#x02010;Old Greek Boys and Girls, Using the Empirical Distribution and the Lambda, Mu, and Sigma Statistical Method</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>European Journal of Sport Science</source>
<volume>16</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>736</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>746</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2015.1088577</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Tomkinson</surname>, <given-names>G. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. D.</given-names>
<surname>Carver</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Atkinson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N. D.</given-names>
<surname>Daniell</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L. K.</given-names>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. S.</given-names>
<surname>Fitzgerald</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. J.</given-names>
<surname>Lang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F. B.</given-names>
<surname>Ortega</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>F. B.</given-names>
<surname>Ortega</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2018</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>European Normative Values for Physical Fitness in Children and Adolescents Aged 9&#x02010;17 years: Results From 2 779 165 Eurofit Performances Representing 30 Countries</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>British Journal of Sports Medicine</source>
<volume>52</volume>(<issue>22</issue>): <fpage>1445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14563</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2017-098253</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29191931</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Tomkinson</surname>, <given-names>G. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. J.</given-names>
<surname>Lang</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. S.</given-names>
<surname>Tremblay</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Dale</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. G.</given-names>
<surname>LeBlanc</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Belanger</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F. B.</given-names>
<surname>Ortega</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>L&#x000e9;ger</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Leger</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2017</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>International Normative 20 m Shuttle Run Values From 1 142 026 Children and Youth Representing 50 Countries</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>British Journal of Sports Medicine</source>
<volume>51</volume>(<issue>21</issue>): <fpage>1545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1554</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2016-095987</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27208067</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="ejsc12237-cit-0028">
<collab collab-type="authors">USA Swimming</collab>
. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>2021&#x02010;2024 National Single Age Motivational Times Short Course Meters</article-title>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.usaswimming.org/docs/default-source/timesdocuments/time-standards/2024/2021-2024-national-single-age-motivational-times.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.usaswimming.org/docs/default&#x02010;source/timesdocuments/time&#x02010;standards/2024/2021&#x02010;2024&#x02010;national&#x02010;single&#x02010;age&#x02010;motivational&#x02010;times.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="ejsc12237-cit-0029">
<collab collab-type="authors">USA Swimming</collab>
. <year>2024</year>. <article-title>National Age Group Records</article-title>. <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.usaswimming.org/times/popular-resources/national-age-group-records" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.usaswimming.org/times/popular&#x02010;resources/national&#x02010;age&#x02010;group&#x02010;records</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Vilas&#x02010;Boas</surname>, <given-names>J. P.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2023</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>Swimming Biomechanics: From the Pool to the Lab. and Back</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Sports Biomechanics</source>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14763141.2023.2237003</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ejsc12237-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ejsc12237-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Wells</surname>, <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. G.</given-names>
<surname>Arthur&#x02010;Banning</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2008</year>. &#x0201c;<article-title>The Logic of Youth Development: Constructing a Logic Model of Youth Development through Sport</article-title>.&#x0201d; <source>Journal of Park and Recreation Administration</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>202</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>