<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Allergy</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Allergy</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Allergy</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Allergy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2673-6101</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2673-6101</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40012569</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11861185</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/falgy.2025.1558724</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Allergy</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: T and B cell immune dynamics in allergic response</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>Mrinmoy</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2123143/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Keswani</surname><given-names>Tarun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1262060/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label><sup>1</sup></label><institution>Division of Immunology, Boston Children&#x02019;s Hospital and Department of Pediatrics Harvard Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Boston, MA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label><sup>2</sup></label><institution>Center for Immunology and Inflammatory Diseases, Division of Rheumatology, Allergy, and Immunology, Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Boston, MA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><bold>Edited and Reviewed by:</bold> Rosemarie DeKruyff, Stanford University, United States</p></fn><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Tarun Keswani <email>tkeswani@mgh.harvard.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>1558724</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2025 Das and Keswani.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Das and Keswani</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY)</ext-link>. The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>allergy</kwd><kwd>T cell</kwd><kwd>B cells</kwd><kwd>inflammation</kwd><kwd>IgA</kwd><kwd>IgG</kwd><kwd>IgE</kwd><kwd>immune response</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="8"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="0"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Mechanisms in Allergy</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" id="RA1" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/56763/T-and-B-cell-immune-dynamics-in-allergic-response" ext-link-type="uri" journal-id="Front. Allergy" journal-id-type="nlm-ta"><bold>Editorial on the Research Topic</bold>
<article-title>T and B cell immune dynamics in allergic response</article-title></related-article><p>Globally, Allergic diseases poses a significant public health threat, affecting millions worldwide (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Although considerable progress has been made in allergy research, there is still a pressing need for: Effective, definitive treatments to manage allergic diseases and a deeper understanding of the complex mechanisms governing T and B cell responses in allergic reactions. Elucidating the underlying immunological processes will be crucial for developing innovative, targeted therapies to improve patient outcomes and quality of life.</p><p>Allergic diseases occur when the immune system mounts an exaggerated response to typically harmless environmental substance, such as aeroallergens and food proteins. This overreaction is driven by the components of the innate and adaptive immune responses, such as innate lymphoid cells type 2 (ILC2) mast cells, basophils, eosinophils, as well as activated T helper type 2 (Th2) cells and B cells that have switched to the production of immunoglobulin type E (IgE). Immune regulatory mechanisms play a crucial role in maintaining tolerance to allergens and preventing allergic reactions. Genetic and immunological evidence also reinforce the idea of a pivotal role for FOXP3 expressing regulatory T (Treg) cells in promoting tolerance to allergens and preventing allergic disorder (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). T regulatory type (Tr1) cells represent a distinct population of T cells that do not constitutively express FOXP3 and are induced in the periphery upon antigen exposure under tolerogenic conditions. Tr1 cells modulate allergic reactions by releasing IL-10 and TGF-&#x003b2;, but their role is not fully understood (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Further research on Tr1 cells could lead to new allergy treatments. A large body of evidence shows that B cells are key players in allergic responses, primarily through the production of IgE antibodies that trigger allergic reactions. In addition to their pivotal role in the pathogenesis of allergies, B cells are also involved in regulation of immune response through antigen presentation, producing IgG and IgA antibodies, immunosuppressive cytokines such as IL-10, IL-35 and TGF-&#x003b2;. By understanding the biology of B cells, including their development, types, and functions, researchers can uncover new ways to promote immune tolerance and treat allergic diseases (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). This editorial will summarize recent efforts that have been published in the research topic T and B Cell Immune Dynamics in Allergic Response in the journal Frontiers in Allergy.</p><p>Researchers led by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/falgy.2023.1129248" ext-link-type="uri">Pablo-Torres et al.</ext-link>, uncovered a link between severe allergies, metabolic problems, and impaired immune function. Their study revealed that severe allergic asthma patients have distinct T-cell gene expression profiles, marked by metabolic and immune pathways disruptions, reduced energy production, and increased inflammation. Specifically, genes involved in energy production (oxidative phosphorylation, fatty acid oxidation, and glycolysis) were downregulated, while genes coding for inflammatory cytokines (IL-19, IL-23A, and IL-31) were upregulated. Additionally, genes involved in TGF-&#x003b2; pathway, as well as Tregs percentage were downregulated indicating impaired regulatory function in these cohorts of severe allergic asthmatic patients. Notably, in cases of food allergy, the deletion of TGF-&#x003b2;1 in Tregs impaired the differentiation of ROR&#x003b3;t&#x02009;+&#x02009;Treg cells, leading to mast cell expansion in the gut and increased susceptibility to food allergy development (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). These findings shed new light on the complex relationships between immune regulation, metabolism, and severe allergic inflammation, paving the way for novel therapeutic approaches.</p><p><ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/falgy.2024.1462579" ext-link-type="uri">Stichova et al.</ext-link>, investigated the function of CD46's, particularly in allergic eosinophilic asthma, and the influence of calcitriol (vitamin D). The study revealed: CD46 plays a critical role in regulating immune cell responses. It regulates the switch from Th1 cells, which produce IFN-&#x003b3;, to Tr1 cells, known for IL-10 production, which is crucial for balancing immune responses. Vitamin D (calcitrol) enhances immune regulation by promoting specific immune cells (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Research has shed light on the crucial role of TR1 cells in regulating immune responses in asthma. By promoting TR1 cell development and increasing IL-10 levels, scientists may have uncovered a promising therapeutic strategy for managing asthma. Eosinophils contribute to asthma inflammation through CD46. Elevated eosinophil cationic protein (ECP) levels during pollen exposure impact CD46 expression and influence T cell responses in AEA (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). In addition, these interactions during clinical studies may contribute to understanding asthma pathophysiology, including exploring vitamin D supplementation to and regulate inflammation.</p><p>Researchers <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/falgy.2024.1389669" ext-link-type="uri">Furiness et al.</ext-link> reviewed the therapeutic potential of IgA and IgG antibodies specific to allergens in food allergy management. These antibodies may counterbalance the severe reactions triggered by IgE antibodies by inhibiting mast cell activation, offering a promising approach to preventing and alleviating allergy symptoms through oral immunotherapy. Although advancements in diagnosing and managing food allergies have been made, no curative treatments are currently available. Recent findings from oral Immunotherapy studies suggest that IgA and IgG antibodies specific to allergens might inhibit the effects of IgE on mast cells. The review highlights the dual role of mast cells in food allergies: they are responsible for immediate allergic reactions and help develop adaptive immune responses, particularly those driven by Th2 cells. These antibodies may regulate the immune system, decrease allergic responses, and block pathways that lead to allergy symptoms. A more comprehensive understanding of the regulatory role of IgA and IgG in food allergy may provide insights into physiologic regulation of immune responses to ingested antigens and could seed novel strategies to mitigate allergic disease (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>A rare medical condition, insulin-induced Type III hypersensitivity reactions (HSRs), is characterized by immune complexes formed by insulin and IgG antibodies, leading to symptoms like subcutaneous nodules and severe insulin resistance. An extensive review by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/falgy.2024.1357901" ext-link-type="uri">Meredith et al.</ext-link> of 16 similar cases reveals that Type 1 diabetes patients tend to have a more aggressive disease course compared to Type 2 patients, and while immunosuppressive therapy provides temporary relief, its long-term benefits are uncertain, warranting further research. Adding to these discoveries, a case study of a 43-year-old woman with Type 1 diabetes mellitus highlights the challenges of diagnosing and managing this condition. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/falgy.2024.1357901" ext-link-type="uri">Meredith et al.</ext-link>, demonstrated the treatment approaches, including therapeutic plasma exchange and immunosuppression, but long-term effectiveness is uncertain. Further research is necessary to understand insulin-induced Type III HSRs mechanisms and develop consistent treatment guidelines.</p><p>Recent studies Integrating the key players in immune regulation, including Tr1 cells, B cells, IgA, IgG, and CD46, holds promise for addressing the unmet clinical needs in allergy research. Furthermore, these contributors work in concert to modulate immune responses, maintain tolerance, and prevent excessive inflammation. Elucidating the interplay between these key contributors may lead to the development of novel therapeutic strategies, improved diagnostics, and enhanced understanding of allergic diseases. The studies offer groundbreaking insights and potential pathways for developing novel, innovative therapies to combat allergies, asthma, and autoimmune diseases. These studies have far-reaching implications, offering hope for millions of people worldwide affected by allergies, asthma, and autoimmune diseases.</p></body><back><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>MD: Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. TK: Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s2"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="s4"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that no Generative AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s3"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Collaborators</surname><given-names>GBDAD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Global, regional, and national burden of allergic disorders and their risk factors in 204 countries and territories, from 1990 to 2019: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2019</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>78</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2232</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/all.15807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37431853</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrientos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephen-Victor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Regulatory T cells and their role in allergic disease</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>. (<year>2025</year>) <volume>80</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/all.16326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeborn</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Strubbe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roncarolo</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Type 1 regulatory T cell-mediated tolerance in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1032575</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.1032575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36389662</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rispens</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijbers</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The unique properties of IgG4 and its roles in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>763</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-023-00871-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37095254</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephen-Victor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivas</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Gadir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Regulatory T cell-derived TGF-&#x003b2;1 controls multiple checkpoints governing allergy and autoimmunity</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>53</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1214.e6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2020.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33086036</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghaseminejad-Raeini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghaderi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharafi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nematollahi-Sani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Moossavi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Derakhshani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Immunomodulatory actions of vitamin D in various immune-related disorders: a comprehensive review</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>950465</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.950465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37520529</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Eosinophils in mucosal immune responses</article-title>. <source>Mucosal Immunol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mi.2015.2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25807184</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheurer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Junker</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Toda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of IgA in the manifestation and prevention of allergic immune responses</article-title>. <source>Curr Allergy Asthma Rep</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>600</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11882-023-01105-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37610671</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>