<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40188268</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11972322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">96660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-96660-w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Inflammatory signaling pathways play a role in SYK inhibitor resistant AML</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tausch</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Villinger</surname><given-names>Christina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alexe</surname><given-names>Gabriela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>Daniel J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>Dominique</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vischedyk</surname><given-names>Jonas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scheich</surname><given-names>Sebastian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Serve</surname><given-names>Hubert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Matthew D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stegmaier</surname><given-names>Kimberly</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oellerich</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>Anjali</given-names></name><address><email>a.cremer@med.uni-frankfurt.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03f6n9m15</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411088.4</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0578 8220</institution-id><institution>Department of Medicine, Hematology/Oncology, </institution><institution>University Hospital Frankfurt, Goethe University, </institution></institution-wrap>Theodor-Stern Kai 7, 60594 Frankfurt am Main, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05bx21r34</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.511198.5</institution-id><institution>Frankfurt Cancer Institute (FCI), </institution></institution-wrap>Frankfurt am Main, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02jzgtq86</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.65499.37</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2106 9910</institution-id><institution>Department of Pediatric Oncology, Harvard Medical School, </institution><institution>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute and Boston Children&#x02019;s Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Boston, MA USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05a0ya142</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.66859.34</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0546 1623</institution-id><institution>The Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard, </institution></institution-wrap>Cambridge, MA USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/01cwqze88</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.94365.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2297 5165</institution-id><institution>Division of Preclinical Innovation, National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences, </institution><institution>National Institutes of Health, </institution></institution-wrap>Rockville, MD USA </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04cdgtt98</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7497.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0492 0584</institution-id><institution>German Cancer Consortium (DKTK) and German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), </institution></institution-wrap>Heidelberg, Frankfurt am Main, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>5</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>11673</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Trials have shown promising clinical activity of the selective SYK inhibitor entospletinib in patients with high expressing <italic>HOXA9/MEIS1</italic> acute leukemias. As the development of resistance mechanisms is a common problem in the use of targeted drugs, we performed a chemical library screen to identify drug sensitivities in SYK inhibitor resistant AML cells. We identified that SYK inhibitor resistant cells displayed an increased sensitivity to glucocorticoids. Glucocorticoids are potent immunosuppressants which work in part by inhibiting the transcription of cytokine genes. RNA sequencing of entospletinib resistant cells revealed a strong enrichment of inflammatory response and TNF&#x003b1; signaling via NF-&#x003ba;B gene sets in comparison to naive cells. Naive AML cells treated with entospletinib showed a strong downregulation of the same gene sets which were upregulated in the resistant state. Our data suggest that inflammatory signaling pathways play a role in entospletinib resistant AML cells.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-96660-w.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Acute myeloid leukemia cells</kwd><kwd>Resistance</kwd><kwd>Inflammatory pathways</kwd><kwd>Glucocorticoids</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Acute myeloid leukaemia</kwd><kwd>High-throughput screening</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Universit&#x000e4;tsklinikum Frankfurt (8916)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Acute myeloid leukemia (AML) is a heterogenous disease that arises from uncontrolled proliferation of clonal hematopoietic cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. For patients with certain gene expression signatures, e.g. high <italic>HOXA9</italic> and <italic>MEIS1</italic> expressing leukemias outcome is still poor, with a 5-year overall survival of less than 25%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. This gene expression signature can be found in leukemias harboring rearrangements of the gene lysine methyltransferase 2A (<italic>KMT2A</italic>), previously known as mixed-lineage leukaemia (<italic>MLL</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> or mutations in <italic>NPM1</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Recently, Menin-Inhibitors have been evaluated in clinical trials and show increased remission rates in patients with <italic>MLL</italic>r acute leukemia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. However, not all patients respond. Hence, new targeted therapies for this difficult to treat patient subgroup have to be evaluated. Spleen tyrosine kinase (SYK) has been identified as a therapeutic target in AML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, especially in <italic>HOXA9</italic> and <italic>MEIS1</italic> high expressing leukemias<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. SYK is rarely mutated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> and is activated by integrin and Fc receptor signaling in AML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. High SYK activation in the bone marrow of patients with AML has also been associated with poor therapeutic outcomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The first clinical trials testing SYK inhibitors in patients with AML showed promising results for <italic>HOXA9</italic> and <italic>MEIS1</italic> high expressing leukemias<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. One of the main challenges of targeted therapies is the development of acquired resistance. One common mechanism of acquired resistance is the activation of important signaling hubs in the cell as a compensatory mechanism to the inhibited drug target<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. We have previously identified activation of RAS/MAPK/ERK signaling as a major resistance mechanism to SYK inhibition in AML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">While immune modulating drugs have revolutionized treatment regimens in acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, the use of these drugs in patients with AML has not been established. There is increasing evidence that the activation of pro-inflammatory pathways plays an important role in AML disease progression and resistance to chemotherapy. Interferon-&#x003b3; response and inflammatory response related mRNA profiles predicted therapeutic resistance to standard &#x0201c;7&#x02009;+&#x02009;3&#x0201d; chemotherapy in patients with AML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Analysis of longitudinal bone marrow samples from patients with AML from primary diagnosis to relapse or in cases of primary resistance confirmed these results, indicating an association of upregulated tumor-promoting inflammatory genes with a short event-free survival, as well as relapse in these patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Activated inflammatory pathways in leukemia cells can even be exploited as &#x0201c;self-directed immunotherapy,&#x0201d; leading to leukemic blast cell death, thus underscoring the complexity and importance of inflammation in AML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The role of inflammation in response to SYK targeted therapies in AML has not been studied to date. In this study, we set out to characterize resistance mechanisms to SYK inhibitors and the potential link between SYK signaling and activation of inflammatory pathways in more detail.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Cells with acquired SYK inhibitor resistance show increased sensitivity to glucocorticoids</title><p id="Par4">First, we set out to systematically identify drugs to which entospletinib-resistant AML cells have an increased sensitivity. We screened SYKi resistant MV4-11 cells, which were previously generated by our lab and not found to possess any new pathogenic mutations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, against the Mechanism Interrogation PlatE (MIPE)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> library of ~&#x02009;1900 oncology focused compounds (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). Entospletinib resistant cells showed an increased sensitivity towards glucocorticoids (e.g., betamethasone dipropionate and budesonide) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). Additionally, entospletinib resistant cells showed an increased sensitivity towards smac mimetics in our drug library screen. However, in this manuscript we focus on glucocorticoids, as the observed underlying mechanisms based on our preliminary data are most likely independent from each other. Glucocorticoids are potent repressors of many genes involved in inflammatory and immune responses, including cytokines and chemokines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. After treatment of resistant and parental cells with dexamethasone, we detected a shift in sensitivity in comparison to the naive state (IC<sub>50</sub> MV4-11 naive: 11.9 &#x000b5;mol/l; MV4-11 resistant: 0.2 &#x000b5;mol/l) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C). We observed a similar but more modest effect upon prednisolone treatment (IC<sub>50</sub> MV4-11 naive: 18.5 &#x000b5;mol/l; MV4-11 resistant: 4.8 &#x000b5;mol/l) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D). The shift in sensitivity to dexamethasone could also be observed in naive and resistant MOLM14 cells (IC<sub>50</sub> MOLM14 naive: 28.08 &#x000b5;mol/l; MOLM14 resistant: 2.4 &#x000b5;mol/l) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>A).</p><p id="Par5">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Comparative analysis of drug sensitivity between MV4-11 naive and SYKi-resistant cell lines. Scatter plot showing the correlation of AUC (Area Under the dose-response Curve) values for all compounds from the NCATS screening library tested in MV4-11 naive versus resistant cell lines. Each point represents an individual compound, with color intensity and size reflecting potency and differential response (where a stronger red represents greater differential killing between the two cell lines). The black diagonal line represents y&#x02009;=&#x02009;x (equal response in both cell lines), while additional solid and dashed lines indicate&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5 standard deviations (SD) and &#x000b1;&#x02009;SD from the diagonal. Lower AUC values indicate more potent and efficacious compounds. (<bold>B</bold>) Annotated version of the scatter plot displaying all tested glucocorticoid compounds with differences in AUC between the naive and resistant cell lines. Data points are labeled with the drug/compound names, with those above or below the y&#x02009;=&#x02009;x line indicating potential resistance or hypersensitivity in the resistant MV4-11 cells. Viability analysis using an ATP-based luminescent assay with increasing concentrations of dexamethasone (<bold>C</bold>) and prednisolone (<bold>D</bold>) in MV4-11 naive and SYKi resistant cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_96660_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e452"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par6">An increased sensitivity to glucocorticoids has been previously reported in AML cells with acquired resistance to cytarabine and FLT3 inhibitors, as well as in patient AML cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, via upregulation of the glucocorticoid receptor encoded by <italic>NR3C1</italic>. A similar mechanism could explain the shift of glucocorticoid sensitivity in the SYKi resistant cells. Indeed, NR3C1 protein (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A) and transcript levels were increased (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B), as evaluated by immunoblot or qPCR, respectively, in the SYKi resistant state compared to control in both cell lines. Next, we evaluated the effect of treatment of SYKi resistant cells with dexamethasone versus a DMSO control. We could detect a greater upregulation of BIM expression in the resistant cells in comparison to naive cells as detected by immunoblot (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C). Upregulation of the pro-apoptotic BH3-only protein BIM induces apoptosis and is a marker for glucocorticoid sensitive cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, suggesting increased apoptosis of SYKi resistant cells after dexamethasone treatment.</p><p id="Par7">To evaluate whether upregulation of <italic>NR3C1</italic> is a non-specific phenomenon in MV4-11 cell lines subjected to long-term culture under continuous drug exposure, protein levels of NR3C1 were evaluated in MV4-11 and MOLM14 cell lines with acquired resistance to venetoclax. Venetoclax resistant cell lines showed no NR3C1 upregulation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>D).</p><p id="Par8">In order to determine whether upregulation of <italic>NR3C1</italic> alone confers resistance to SYK inhibitors in AML cell lines, <italic>NR3C1</italic> was overexpressed in wildtype MV4-11 cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>E). NR3C1 overexpression did not have an impact on total SYK protein expression levels in comparison to the control cells, however we detected a slight decrease in phospho SYK expression (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>E). As expected, overexpression of <italic>NR3C1</italic>, lead to an increased sensitivity to dexamethasone treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>F). Subsequently <italic>NR3C1</italic> overexpressing cells were treated with entospletinib for 14 days. Overexpression of the glucocorticoid receptor alone was not able to confer resistance to SYK inhibition in AML cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>G), indicating that observed upregulation of <italic>NR3C1</italic> alone is not driving entospletinib resistance.</p><p id="Par9">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Immunoblot showing NR3C1 overexpression in MV4-11 resistant cells. Burkitt lymphoma cell line Ramos, was used as a positive control for NR3C1 expression. GAPDH was used as a loading control. Representative images of three independent replicates are shown. (<bold>B</bold>) Confirmation of NR3C1 mRNA fold-change upregulation in resistant versus naive MV4-11 cells by qpCR (***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.001, Mann-Whitney test). (<bold>C</bold>) Immunoblot showing upregulation of BIM in dexamethasone treated, entospletinib resistant MV4-11 cells. Vinculin was used as a loading control. Representative images of two independent replicates are shown. (<bold>D</bold>) Immunoblot showing NR3C1 expression in naive and venetoclax resistant MV4-11 cells in comparison to Ramos control cells. GAPDH was used as a loading control. Representative images of three independent replicates are shown. (<bold>E</bold>) Immunoblot confirming overexpression of NR3C1 ORF in MV4-11 cells, as well as SYK expression. Alpha tubulin was used as a loading control. Original Blots are presented in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>. (<bold>F</bold>) Viability analysis using an ATP-based luminescent assay with increasing concentrations of dexamethasone in NR3C1 ORF expressing MV4-11 cells. (<bold>G</bold>) Long-term viability assay in MV4-11 cells overexpressing NR3C1 ORF and treated with vehicle or 3 &#x000b5;mol/L entospletinib (Ento).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_96660_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e555"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>SYK Inhibition leads to reduced NF-&#x003ba;B response after TNF&#x003b1; stimulation</title><p id="Par10">SYK is known to be a mediator of immunoreceptor signaling in B-cells. After B-cell receptor engagement, SYK is recruited and activated, mediating downstream signal transduction towards NF-&#x003ba;B<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. There is evidence that SYK and NF-&#x003ba;B signaling are also connected in AML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. After <italic>MLL1(KMT2A); MLL2(KMT2D)</italic> knockout in <italic>MLL-AF9</italic> leukemia cells, RNAseq analysis revealed a reduction in the components of three major pathways, namely NF-&#x003ba;B, integrin beta-3 (in which SYK is an intracellular signaling component<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>) and interleukin-3 (IL-3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Interestingly, <italic>IL3RA</italic> transcript was also confirmed to be reduced in <italic>MLL1/MLL2</italic> double knockout leukemia cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. MLL2-deficient leukemia cells could be partially rescued by culturing cells in the presence of high (10 ng/mL) IL-3, whereas the double knockout cells could only be slightly rescued<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. It was previously described that treatment involving the combination of the IkB kinase inhibitor VII, targeting NF-&#x003ba;B signaling, a SYK inhibitor and reduced IL-3 had a synergistic effect in leukemia cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">In line with these observations, a genome-scale, lentiviral ORF library screen, previously performed by our lab, identified IL-3 overexpression as a major resistance mechanism to SYK inhibition in AML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Overexpression of the <italic>IL3</italic> gene in the screen conveyed resistance to treatment with the SYK inhibitor entospletinib in the two <italic>FLT3</italic> mutant AML cell lines, MOLM14 and MV4-11. In order to validate our findings, we re-expressed an <italic>IL3</italic> ORF in MV4-11 and MOLM14 cells. Overexpression was confirmed by using antibodies specific to IL-3 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). Next, these cells were treated with either entospletinib or DMSO as a control to determine whether the overexpressed genes could rescue the effects of SYK inhibitor treatment. Overexpression of <italic>IL3</italic> promoted resistance to entospletinib-mediated cell death (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B), confirming the ORF screen data. In addition, we observed that cells overexpressing <italic>IL3</italic> had increased colony forming potential in comparison to control cells treated with entospletinib (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C). This finding was confirmed by adding IL-3 to methylcellulose in wildtype MV4-11 cells and MOLM14 cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>D). These findings are in line with the previous observation that IL-3 can rescue the effects of <italic>MLL1</italic> and <italic>MLL1/MLL2</italic> knockout in leukemia cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, which is consistent given the fact that SYK inhibition results in the downregulation of the same gene expression signature as <italic>HOXA9/MEIS1</italic>-driven leukemia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par12">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Immunoblot confirming overexpression of IL3 ORF in MV4-11 cells. Vinculin was used as a loading control. Representative images of three independent replicates are shown. Original Blots are presented in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Long-term viability assay in MV4-11 (left) and MOLM14 (right) cells overexpressing the indicated ORFs and treated with vehicle or 3 &#x000b5;mol/L entospletinib (Ento) (****<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.0001, two-way ANOVA test, multiple comparisons) (<bold>C</bold>) Colony forming assay in MV4-11 (left) and MOLM14 (right) cells overexpressing the indicated ORFs and treated with increasing concentrations of entospletinib (Ento). (*<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05, ****<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.0001, two-way ANOVA test, multiple comparisons) (<bold>D</bold>) Colony forming assay with vehicle or IL3 addition (10 ng/ml) to methylcellulose in MV4-11 (left) and MOLM14 (right) cells treated with increasing concentrations of entospletinib (****<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.0001, two-way ANOVA test, multiple comparisons).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_96660_Fig3_HTML" id="d33e694"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par13">To investigate which signaling pathways are activated in the entospletinib resistant state, bulk RNA sequencing of entospletinib resistant MV4-11 cells was performed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Here, we observed a strong correlation between the SYKi resistant cell state and inflammatory response (Normalized enrichment score (NES)&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.44, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01), and TNF&#x003b1; signaling via NF-&#x003ba;B (NES&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.14, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) in GSEA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A, left). Leading edge genes that were upregulated in both pathways in SYKi resistant cells included known NF-&#x003ba;B target genes such as <italic>ICAM1</italic>,<italic> REL</italic>, and <italic>EGR1</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B<italic>)</italic>. This data suggests that the upregulation of NF-&#x003ba;B signaling might play a role in conferring resistance to SYK inhibition in AML. Subsequently, we investigated whether inhibition of SYK by entospletinib treatment of naive AML cells led to a downregulation of inflammatory pathways in AML cells via RNAseq analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. GSEA on this data revealed a strong correlation between entospletinib treatment and the downregulation of the gene sets &#x0201c;Inflammatory response&#x0201d; (NES= -1.4, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) and &#x0201c;TNF&#x003b1; signaling via NF-&#x003ba;B&#x0201d; (NES= &#x02212; 1.6, FDR&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A, right). These gene sets were also found to be upregulated in the SYKi resistant state (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A, left).</p><p id="Par14">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) GSEA demonstrating enrichment of signatures upregulated in resistant cells in comparison with naive cells, as well as in cells treated with entospletinib (<bold>B</bold>). Shown is a heatmap of leading edge genes that were included in both gene sets &#x0201c;Inflammatory response&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;TNF&#x003b1; signaling via NF-kB&#x0201d; in resistant cells in comparison with naive cells. Significance was assessed based on NES&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1.5, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.01. (<bold>C</bold>) Relative luciferase activity in MV4-11 cells harboring a NF-kB luciferase reporter assay after TNFa stimulation or entospletinib treatment or both (combo). DMSO was used as a control. (<bold>D</bold>) CD83 expression measured by FACS in MV4-11 and MOLM14 cells after entospletinib treatment. (<bold>E</bold>) Immunoblot confirming increased IKKB and reduced IKB alpha after overexpression of wildtype or mutant IKK2 in MV4-11 cells. Vinculin was used as a loading control. Representative images of two independent replicates are shown. Original Blots are presented in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>. (<bold>F</bold>) Long-term viability assay in MV4-11 cells overexpressing the indicated wildtype or mutant IKK2 and treated with vehicle or 3 &#x000b5;mol/L entospletinib (Ento).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_96660_Fig4_HTML" id="d33e778"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par15">NF-&#x003ba;B represents a family of transcription factors that are normally kept inactive in the cytoplasm through interaction with inhibitory molecules of the I&#x003ba;B family<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Upon activation via inflammatory cytokines or other types of cell stress, I&#x003ba;B molecules become subject to proteasomal degradation. Consequently, NF-&#x003ba;B translocates to the nucleus and activates the transcription of genes that participate in inflammatory response, growth control, and protection against apoptosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. One of the most potent activators of NF-&#x003ba;B is TNF&#x003b1;, and it has been reported that TNF&#x003b1;-induced NF-&#x003ba;B activation is mediated via SYK activation in a T-cell leukemia cell line<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Based on our RNAseq data we hypothesized that SYK inhibition leads to reduced activation of NF-&#x003ba;B signaling in AML. To investigate this, we first established a NF-&#x003ba;B luciferase reporter assay<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> in MV4-11 and MOLM14 cells. When cells were treated with TNF&#x003b1; for 3&#x000a0;h (h) at a concentration of 20 ng/ml, we could detect an upregulation of NF-&#x003ba;B signaling (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C). After combining TNF&#x003b1; treatment with entospletinib treatment, a decreased response to TNF&#x003b1; in MV4-11 (not significant) and MOLM14 (**<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0068) cells was observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D). Analysis of the expression of CD83, a known NF-&#x003ba;B target gene, in wildtype MOLM14 cells treated with SYKi revealed a decrease of CD83 expression in comparison to the control (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D, right); however, we could not observe a decrease in CD83 expression in MV4-11 cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D, left).</p><p id="Par16">We next investigated whether constitutively active NF-&#x003ba;B signaling alone can mediate resistance to entospletinib in wildtype MV4-11 cells. Therefore, wildtype IKK-2 and a double mutant form of IKK-2 (S177E, S181E)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> leading to constitutive active IKK-2 was overexpressed by lentivirus in MV4-11 cells. Overexpression of IKK-2 and the double mutant was confirmed by immunoblot (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>E). As expected, overexpression of IKK-2 lead to increased degradation of IKB alpha as detected by immunoblot, confirming activation of NF-&#x003ba;B<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. However, when we treated the cells with entospletinib or DMSO as a control we could not detect a difference in doubling times of the cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>F), indicating that constitutively activated NF-&#x003ba;B signaling by overexpression of IKK-2 alone does not convey resistance to SYK inhibition in wildtype MV4-11 cells. These data suggest that prior continuous exposure with a SYK inhibitor facilitates activation of NF-&#x003ba;B signaling in AML cells.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par17">AML is a heterogenous disease with an estimated 5-year OS of 30%. Prognosis differs greatly between age groups, reaching 50% in younger patients but is less than 10% in patients older than age of 60<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Due to the approval of 11 new drugs or combinations since 2017 [31&#x02013;35] (e.g. midostaurin, gilteritinib, ivosidenib, venetoclax) outcome of patients with AML will most likely improve in the near future. It is known that one of the greatest challenges of targeted therapies is the emergence of intrinsic or acquired resistance to these drugs. Understanding the underlying mechanisms of resistance (e.g. mutations, rewiring of signaling hubs) is important to propose potential strategies to overcome them.</p><p id="Par18">Inflammation is a critical component of tumor progression. Many cancers arise from sites of infection, chronic irritation and inflammation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. NF-<italic>&#x003ba;</italic>B is a transcription factor that can be activated by a variety of cytokines and plays a key role in inflammatory processes. In transformed cancer cells, it is usually kept active and can regulate the cell cycle and apoptosis process by activating genes encoding related proteins, thereby inducing survival and promoting cancer progression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The role of activation of inflammatory signaling pathways in drug resistance in AML has not been studied in detail yet.</p><p id="Par19">This study shows that SYKi resistant cells display an upregulation of inflammatory pathways by RNAseq analysis. Chemical SYK inhibition in SYKi naive AML cells results in a dampened TNFa- induced NF-kB activation, implying that the pathway is involved in SYK signaling in AML cells. Our data provide evidence that upregulation of the glucocorticoid receptor is not only restricted to the selective pressure induced by cytarabine or FMS-like tyrosine kinase III (FLT3) inhibitor resistance in AML as reported previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, but can be also observed in cells with acquired resistance to SYK inhibition, leading to an increased sensitivity to glucocorticoids in two SYKi resistant AML cell lines. The preemptive identification of resistance mechanisms to targeted therapies have the potential to better inform clinical trials and improve outcomes for patients in the future.</p><p id="Par20">Our experiments were conducted in vitro using AML cell lines, which is a limitation of this study, as cell line models are not able to take the complex in vivo bone marrow microenvironment of AML patients into account, which is important in regulation and response to cytokines and chemokines secreted by immune cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. However, to study acquired resistance mechanisms that are not conveyed by genetic mutations it is still the best model there is, as patient cells can not be maintained for a longer period of time in cell culture without the addition of various cytokines to cell culture media that alter signaling pathways in itself.</p><p id="Par21">In summary, our study demonstrates that inflammatory signaling pathways play a role in conferring resistance to entospletinib, which can be reversed in part by treatment with anti-inflammatory drugs. However, whether observed effects are direct or indirect, as well as the exact underlying mechanism remains elusive and will require further investigation in the future.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cell lines</title><p id="Par22">MV4-11 and MOLM14 cells were previously provided by Scott Armstrong. Both cell lines were maintained in RPMI 1640 (Cellgro) supplemented with 1% penicillin/streptomycin (PS; Cellgro) and 10% FBS (Sigma-Aldrich) at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Ramos cells were provided by Thomas Oellerich and were maintained in RPMI 1640 (Cellgro) supplemented with 1% penicillin/streptomycin (PS; Cellgro) and 20% FBS (Sigma-Aldrich) at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. The 293T cells were maintained in Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified Eagle&#x02019;s medium (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% FBS (Invitrogen) and 1% PS. All cell lines were tested negative for <italic>Mycoplasma</italic> and were authenticated using short tandem repeat (STR) profiling.</p><p id="Par23"><italic>Generation of entospletinib resistant cells</italic> To generate cells that were resistant to SYK inhibition, MV4-11 were treated for 5 months with gradually increasing concentrations of entospletinib (500 nM&#x02013;5 &#x000b5;M). Cells were considered entospletinib-resistant when they were able to maintain a 90&#x02013;100% viability in the presence of entospletinib at a 10-fold higher concentration than the IC<sub>50</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Chemicals</title><p id="Par24">Compounds used for high-throughput screening were sourced from the NCATS compound library. All compounds for in vitro experiments were obtained from Selleck.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Lentiviral/Retrovirus production and transduction</title><p id="Par25">Lentivirus was generated by transfecting HEK-293T cells with the indicated vectors and the packaging plasmids, delta8.9 and VSVG, following the X-tremeGENE HP DNA Transfection Reagent protocol (Roche). AML cells were infected with 2 mL of virus and 8&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL polybrene.</p><p id="Par26">Retrovirus was generated by using the packaging plasmids, &#x003c8;Eco and RV. Primary murine bone marrow cells were infected by spin-infection in a centrifuge with 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of virus and 8&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/mL polybrene in a 96-well plate, at 1500&#x000a0;rpm for 2&#x000a0;h at room temperature (RT). Cells were selected with puromycin containing media 48&#x000a0;h after infection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Validation of ORF hits</title><p id="Par27">Lentiviral infected cells expressing candidate ORF hits from the primary screen were seeded in TC25 flasks in technical duplicate and were treated with DMSO or 3 &#x000b5;M entospletinib. Cumulative population doublings were calculated by manually counting cells every 3&#x02013;4 days for a total of 21 days.</p></sec><sec id="Sec958"><title>RNA-sequencing</title><p id="Par28">RNA was extracted from cells with the RNeasy Kit and on-column DNA digestion (Qiagen).</p><p id="Par29">For RNA-sequencing of MV4-11 cells, polyA mRNA was isolated and libraries were prepared using the TruSeq Stranded mRNA Kit (Illumina) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. All samples were sequenced on a NextSeq500 instrument with single-end 75&#x000a0;bp reads to a depth of 30-50&#x000a0;M reads/sample. RNAseq was performed after SYKi resistant cells were cultured for 24&#x000a0;h in drug free media.</p></sec><sec id="Sec741"><title>Plasmids</title><p id="Par30"><italic>IKK-2</italic> WT and <italic>IKK-2</italic> S177E S181E were a gift from Anjana Rao (Addgene plasmid #11103 and #11105). pHAGE NFkB-TA-LUC-UBC-GFP-W was a gift from Darrell Kotton (Addgene plasmid #49343). The NF-&#x003ba;B reporter assay contains four tandem copies of the NF-&#x003ba;B consensus sequence located upstream of the minimal TA promoter (Tap) the TAT box of the HSV-TK promoter, downstream from the Tap is the firefly luciferase reporter gene as well as a ubiquitously expressed GFP reporter under the control of the constitutive mammalian ubiquitin C (UBC) promoter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec951"><title>Genome-scale ORF screens</title><p id="Par31">The ORFeome barcoded library contains 17,255 barcoded ORFs overexpressing 10,135 distinct human genes with at least 99% nucleotide and protein match. Screening-scale infections of the ORFeome library were performed with cells sufficient to achieve a representation of at least 1000 cells per ORF (~&#x02009;2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>7</sup> surviving cells containing 17,255 ORFs). Infections were performed with the pre-determined virus volume in the 12-well format, as the viral titration described above, and pooled 24&#x000a0;h post-infection. Approximately 24&#x000a0;h after infection, all wells within a replicate were pooled and 48&#x000a0;h after infection, cells were selected with puromycin. After selection was completed, 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>7</sup> cells were divided into drug treated (3 &#x000b5;M entospletinib for MV4-11 and MOLM14) and vehicle treated arms. Cells were passaged in drug or fresh media containing drug every 3&#x02013;4 days, and throughout the screen an average representation of 1000 cells per ORF construct was maintained. Cells were harvested 21 days after initiation of treatment. For both ORF screens, genomic DNA (gDNA) was isolated using Maxi (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>7</sup>&#x02013;1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>8</sup> cells) or Midi (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup>&#x02013;3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>7</sup> cells) kits according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol (Qiagen). PCR and sequencing were performed as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec852"><title>RT-PCR</title><p id="Par32">The expression of <italic>NR3C1</italic> was quantified utilizing RT-PCR with a taqman probe specific for <italic>NR3C1</italic> (ThermoFisher Scientific, Assay-ID Hs00353740_m1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9634"><title>Western blotting</title><p id="Par33">Proteins were extracted using Lysis Buffer (Cell Signaling Technology) supplemented with Complete, Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA)-free Protease Inhibitor Cocktail (Roche Diagnostics) and Phosphatase Inhibitor Cocktail (Roche Diagnostics). Protein samples were separated by SDS-PAGE and subsequently transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membranes, which were blocked in 5% BSA and incubated with primary antibodies against NR3C1 (D6H2L) XP (Cell Signaling Technology, Cat. No. 12041), BIM (Epitomics, Cat. No. 1036-1), IKK&#x003b2;/IKK2 (D30C6) (Cell Signaling, Cat. No. 8943), I&#x003ba;B&#x003b1; (L35A5) (Cell Signaling Technology, Cat. No. 4814), IL-3 (Santa Cruz, Cat. No. sc-28342), phospho- SYK Y525/Y526 (Cell Signaling Technology, No. 2711), SYK (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, No. sc-1240),GAPDH (D16H11) XP (Cell Signaling Technology, Cat. No. 5174), &#x003b1;-Tubulin (11H10) (Cell Signaling Technology, Cat. No. 2125), or Vinculin (Sigma, Cat. No. V9131). Membranes were washed in TBS-T and incubated with the appropriate horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibodies. Signal was detected by enhanced chemi-luminescence (ThermoFisher Scientific). Image acquisition was performed using ChemiDoc Imaging System (BIO-RAD). Protein concentration of three or two independent replicates was statistically quantified using ImageJ.</p></sec><sec id="Sec456"><title>Cell viability assay</title><p id="Par34">Cells were resuspended at 15,000 cells/mL and seeded at 40 &#x000b5;L/well into 384-well plates. Cells were then treated with a single agent or DMSO as a control and analyzed for cell viability on days 0 and 3 post-treatment using the CellTiter-Glo Luminescent Assay Kit (Promega) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Luminescence was read on a TECAN reader.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6214"><title>Long term viability assay</title><p id="Par35">To determine long term viability of cells, 1E6 cells per 10&#x000a0;ml medium were seeded into a T25 culture flask. Cells were treated with 3&#x000b5;M/mL Entospletenib, or DMSO as control. Cell count and viability was determined every 4 days with a TC20 automated cell counter (Bio-Rad), using these values cumulative population doublings were calculated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec987"><title>High-throughput viability screen</title><p id="Par36">A high-throughput screen was conducted in 1536-well white flat bottom plates (Corning). Using a MultiDrop Combi (Thermofisher Scientific), 2 &#x000b5;L of media were added to the plates. Compounds from four drug screening libraries (MIPE 5.0, NPC, NPACT, and Kinase Library) totalling 13,72 compounds were dissolved in DMSO and then added to plates using an acoustic dispenser. Cell lines were seeded into plates at a final density of 500 cells in 5 &#x000b5;L of media per well (MultiDrop Combi). After 72&#x000a0;h of compound incubation, 3 &#x000b5;L of Cell-TiterGlo reagent (Promega) was added to each well. Following a 10&#x000a0;min incubation, luminescence was read using the Viewlux microplate reader (PerkinElmer). Primary screening data is publicly available with PubChem AIDs 1,963,823 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioassay/1963823">https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioassay/1963823</ext-link>) and 1,963,824 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioassay/1963824">https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioassay/1963824</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7563"><title>Quantification and statistical analyses</title><p id="Par37">GSEA v2.1.0, GraphPad PRISM 7, R 3.2.3 and Python 2.7.2 software packages were used to perform the statistical analyses. Statistical tests used are specified in the figure legends. Errors bars represent standard deviation, unless otherwise stated. The threshold for statistical significance is p-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05, unless otherwise specified.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_96660_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>A.C. was supported by the Max-Eder Program of the German Cancer Aid. K.S. was supported by P50 CA206963 and a National Cancer Institute R35 CA283977. This research was supported by the Intramural Research Program of the National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences, NIH. A.C. thanks S.C., H.U., F.F. for discussion and advice.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conception and design: S.T., T.O., K.S., A.C.: Acquisition of data: S.T., G.A., C.V., D.J., M.S., D.U. J.V., A.C.&#x000a0;Analysis and interpretation of data: S.T., G.A., D.U., M.H., S.S., H.S., T.O., K.S., A.C.&#x000a0;Writing and/or revision of manuscript: S.T., S.S., T.O., K.S., A.C.&#x000a0;Study supervision: T.O., K.S., and A.C.&#x000a0;All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Chemical drug library screen data is available with PubChem AIDs (https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioassay/1963823) and (https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioassay/1963824). RNA-seq data was deposited at the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) under accession number GSE129698.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par39">K.S. received grant funding from the DFCI/Novartis Drug Discovery Program and is a member of the SAB and has stock options with Auron Therapeutics on topics unrelated to this work. All other authors have no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimony</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute myeloid leukemia: 2023 update on diagnosis, risk-stratification, and management</article-title><source>Am. J. Hematol.</source><year>2023</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>502</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajh.26822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36594187</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Shimony, S., Stahl, M. &#x00026; Stone, R. M. Acute myeloid leukemia: 2023 update on diagnosis, risk-stratification, and management. <italic>Am. J. Hematol.</italic><bold>98</bold>, 502&#x02013;526. 10.1002/ajh.26822 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36594187</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krivtsov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MLL translocations, histone modifications and leukaemia stem-cell development</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc2253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17957188</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Krivtsov, A. V. &#x00026; Armstrong, S. A. MLL translocations, histone modifications and leukaemia stem-cell development. <italic>Nat. Rev. Cancer</italic>. <bold>7</bold>, 823&#x02013;833. 10.1038/nrc2253 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17957188</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hoxa9 and Meis1 cooperatively induce addiction to syk signaling by suppressing miR-146a in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>562e511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccell.2017.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28399410</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Mohr, S. et al. Hoxa9 and Meis1 cooperatively induce addiction to Syk signaling by suppressing miR-146a in acute myeloid leukemia. <italic>Cancer Cell</italic><bold>31</bold>, 549&#x02013;562e511, (2017). 10.1016/j.ccell.2017.03.001<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28399410</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alcalay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute myeloid leukemia bearing cytoplasmic nucleophosmin (NPMc&#x02009;+&#x02009;AML) shows a distinct gene expression profile characterized by up-regulation of genes involved in stem-cell maintenance</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2005</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2005-02-0560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831697</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Alcalay, M. et al. Acute myeloid leukemia bearing cytoplasmic nucleophosmin (NPMc&#x02009;+&#x02009;AML) shows a distinct gene expression profile characterized by up-regulation of genes involved in stem-cell maintenance. <italic>Blood</italic><bold>106</bold>, 899&#x02013;902. 10.1182/blood-2005-02-0560 (2005).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831697</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Issa</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Menin Inhibition WithRevumenib for KMT2A-Rearranged Relapsed or Refractory Acute Leukemia(AUGMENT-101)</article-title><source>J. Clin.Oncol.</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.24.00826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39121437</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Issa, G. C. et al. Menin Inhibition with revumenib for KMT2A-Rearranged relapsed or refractory acute leukemia (AUGMENT-101). <italic>J. Clin. Oncol.</italic>. 10.1200/JCO.24.00826 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39121437</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic and genetic approaches identify Syk as an AML target</article-title><source>Cancer Cell.</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2009.08.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19800574</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Hahn, C. K. et al. Proteomic and genetic approaches identify Syk as an AML target. <italic>Cancer Cell.</italic><bold>16</bold>, 281&#x02013;294. 10.1016/j.ccr.2009.08.018 (2009).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19800574</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuno</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Constitutive kinase activation of the TEL-Syk fusion gene in myelodysplastic syndrome with t(9;12)(q22;p12)</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2001</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1050</fpage><lpage>1055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood.v97.4.1050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11159536</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Kuno, Y. et al. Constitutive kinase activation of the TEL-Syk fusion gene in myelodysplastic syndrome with t(9;12)(q22;p12). <italic>Blood</italic><bold>97</bold>, 1050&#x02013;1055. 10.1182/blood.v97.4.1050 (2001).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11159536</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TEL-Syk fusion constitutively activates PI3-K/Akt, MAPK and JAK2-independent STAT5 signal pathways</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.leu.2403266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14749700</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Kanie, T. et al. TEL-Syk fusion constitutively activates PI3-K/Akt, MAPK and JAK2-independent STAT5 signal pathways. <italic>Leukemia</italic><bold>18</bold>, 548&#x02013;555. 10.1038/sj.leu.2403266 (2004).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14749700</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oellerich</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>beta2 integrin-derived signals induce cell survival and proliferation of AML blasts by activating a Syk/STAT signaling axis</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2013</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>3889</fpage><lpage>3899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2012-09-457887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23509157</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Oellerich, T. et al. beta2 integrin-derived signals induce cell survival and proliferation of AML blasts by activating a Syk/STAT signaling axis. <italic>Blood</italic><bold>121</bold>, 3889&#x02013;3899. 10.1182/blood-2012-09-457887 (2013). S3881-3866.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23509157</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boros</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased SYK activity is associated with unfavorable outcome among patients with acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>25575</fpage><lpage>25587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.4669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26315286</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Boros, K. et al. Increased SYK activity is associated with unfavorable outcome among patients with acute myeloid leukemia. <italic>Oncotarget</italic><bold>6</bold>, 25575&#x02013;25587. 10.18632/oncotarget.4669 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26315286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Entospletinib in combination with induction chemotherapy in previously untreated acute myeloid leukemia: Response and predictive significance of HOXA9 and MEIS1 expression</article-title><source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>5852</fpage><lpage>5859</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-20-1064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32820015</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Walker, A. R. et al. Entospletinib in combination with induction chemotherapy in previously untreated acute myeloid leukemia: Response and predictive significance of HOXA9 and MEIS1 expression. <italic>Clin. Cancer Res.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 5852&#x02013;5859. 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-20-1064 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32820015</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentires-Alj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism-based cancer therapy: Resistance to therapy, therapy for resistance</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2015</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>3617</fpage><lpage>3626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/onc.2014.314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25263438</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Ramos, P. &#x00026; Bentires-Alj, M. Mechanism-based cancer therapy: Resistance to therapy, therapy for resistance. <italic>Oncogene</italic><bold>34</bold>, 3617&#x02013;3626. 10.1038/onc.2014.314 (2015).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25263438</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resistance mechanisms to SYK Inhibition in acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Cancer Discov.</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-19-0209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31771968</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Cremer, A. et al. Resistance mechanisms to SYK Inhibition in acute myeloid leukemia. <italic>Cancer Discov.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 214&#x02013;231. 10.1158/2159-8290.CD-19-0209 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31771968</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kantarjian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Blinatumomab versus chemotherapy for advanced acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><year>2017</year><volume>376</volume><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1609783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28249141</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Kantarjian, H. et al. Blinatumomab versus chemotherapy for advanced acute lymphoblastic leukemia. <italic>N. Engl. J. Med.</italic><bold>376</bold>, 836&#x02013;847. 10.1056/NEJMoa1609783 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28249141</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vadakekolathu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immune landscapespredict chemotherapy resistance and immunotherapy response in acutemyeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Sci. TranslMed.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.aaz0463</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Vadakekolathu, J. et al. Immune landscapes predict chemotherapy resistance and immunotherapy response in acute myeloid leukemia. <italic>Sci. Transl Med.</italic>. 10.1126/scitranslmed.aaz0463 (2020).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stratmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis reveals proinflammatory signatures associated with acute myeloid leukemia progression</article-title><source>Blood Adv.</source><year>2022</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/bloodadvances.2021004962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34619772</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Stratmann, S. et al. Transcriptomic analysis reveals proinflammatory signatures associated with acute myeloid leukemia progression. <italic>Blood Adv.</italic><bold>6</bold>, 152&#x02013;164. 10.1182/bloodadvances.2021004962 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34619772</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellegast</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unleashing cell-Intrinsic inflammation as a strategy to kill AML blasts</article-title><source>Cancer Discov.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1760</fpage><lpage>1781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-21-0956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35405016</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Ellegast, J. M. et al. Unleashing cell-Intrinsic inflammation as a strategy to kill AML blasts. <italic>Cancer Discov.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1760&#x02013;1781. 10.1158/2159-8290.CD-21-0956 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35405016</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A High-Throughput screen of a library of therapeutics identifies cytotoxic substrates of P-glycoprotein</article-title><source>Mol. Pharmacol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.119.115964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31515284</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Lee, T. D. et al. A High-Throughput screen of a library of therapeutics identifies cytotoxic substrates of P-glycoprotein. <italic>Mol. Pharmacol.</italic><bold>96</bold>, 629&#x02013;640. 10.1124/mol.119.115964 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31515284</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cidlowski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiinflammatory action of glucocorticoids-new mechanisms for old drugs</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><year>2005</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>1711</fpage><lpage>1723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra050541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236742</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Rhen, T. &#x00026; Cidlowski, J. A. Antiinflammatory action of glucocorticoids-new mechanisms for old drugs. <italic>N. Engl. J. Med.</italic><bold>353</bold>, 1711&#x02013;1723. 10.1056/NEJMra050541 (2005).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236742</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced sensitivity to glucocorticoids in cytarabine-resistant AML</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1187</fpage><lpage>1195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/leu.2016.314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27833094</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Malani, D. et al. Enhanced sensitivity to glucocorticoids in cytarabine-resistant AML. <italic>Leukemia</italic><bold>31</bold>, 1187&#x02013;1195. 10.1038/leu.2016.314 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27833094</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gebru</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glucocorticoids enhance the antileukemic activity of FLT3 inhibitors in FLT3-mutant acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2020</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood.2019003124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32396937</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Gebru, M. T. et al. Glucocorticoids enhance the antileukemic activity of FLT3 inhibitors in FLT3-mutant acute myeloid leukemia. <italic>Blood</italic><bold>136</bold>, 1067&#x02013;1079. 10.1182/blood.2019003124 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32396937</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BIM is a prognostic biomarker for early prednisolone response in pediatric acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title><source>Exp. Hematol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exphem.2010.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21130142</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Jiang, N. et al. BIM is a prognostic biomarker for early prednisolone response in pediatric acute lymphoblastic leukemia. <italic>Exp. Hematol.</italic><bold>39</bold>, 321&#x02013;329. 10.1016/j.exphem.2010.11.009 (2011).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21130142</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulze-Luehrmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antigen-receptor signaling to nuclear factor kappa B</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2006.10.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17098202</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Schulze-Luehrmann, J. &#x00026; Ghosh, S. Antigen-receptor signaling to nuclear factor kappa B. <italic>Immunity</italic><bold>25</bold>, 701&#x02013;715. 10.1016/j.immuni.2006.10.010 (2006).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17098202</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting NF-kappaB pathway for the therapy of diseases: Mechanism and clinical study</article-title><source>Signal. Transduct. Target. Ther.</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>209</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-020-00312-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32958760</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Yu, H., Lin, L., Zhang, Z., Zhang, H. &#x00026; Hu, H. Targeting NF-kappaB pathway for the therapy of diseases: Mechanism and clinical study. <italic>Signal. Transduct. Target. Ther.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 209. 10.1038/s41392-020-00312-6 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32958760</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MLL2, Not MLL1, plays a major role in sustaining MLL-rearranged acute myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-020-00312-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28609655</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Chen, Y. et al. MLL2, Not MLL1, Plays a major role in sustaining MLL-rearranged acute myeloid leukemia. <italic>Cancer Cell</italic><bold>31</bold>, 755&#x02013;770. 10.1016/j.ccell.2017.05.002 (2017).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28609655</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vivo RNAi screening identifies a leukemia-specific dependence on integrin beta 3 signaling</article-title><source>Cancer Cell.</source><year>2013</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2013.05.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23770013</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Miller, P. G. et al. In vivo RNAi screening identifies a leukemia-specific dependence on integrin beta 3 signaling. <italic>Cancer Cell.</italic><bold>24</bold>, 45&#x02013;58. 10.1016/j.ccr.2013.05.004 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23770013</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shared principles in NF-kappaB signaling</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2008.01.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18267068</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Hayden, M. S. &#x00026; Ghosh, S. Shared principles in NF-kappaB signaling. <italic>Cell</italic><bold>132</bold>, 344&#x02013;362. 10.1016/j.cell.2008.01.020 (2008).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18267068</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TNF activates Syk protein tyrosine kinase leading to TNF-induced MAPK activation, NF-kappaB activation, and apoptosis</article-title><source>J. Immunol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.173.2.1066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15240695</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Takada, Y. &#x00026; Aggarwal, B. B. TNF activates Syk protein tyrosine kinase leading to TNF-induced MAPK activation, NF-kappaB activation, and apoptosis. <italic>J. Immunol.</italic><bold>173</bold>, 1066&#x02013;1077. 10.4049/jimmunol.173.2.1066 (2004).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15240695</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lentiviral delivery of RNAi for in vivo lineage-specific modulation of gene expression in mouse lung macrophages</article-title><source>Mol. Ther.</source><year>2013</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mt.2013.19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23403494</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Wilson, A. A. et al. Lentiviral delivery of RNAi for in vivo lineage-specific modulation of gene expression in mouse lung macrophages. <italic>Mol. Ther.</italic><bold>21</bold>, 825&#x02013;833. 10.1038/mt.2013.19 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23403494</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mercurio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IKK-1 and IKK-2: Cytokine-activated IkappaB kinases essential for NF-kappaB activation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>278</volume><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.278.5339.860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9346484</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Mercurio, F. et al. IKK-1 and IKK-2: Cytokine-activated IkappaB kinases essential for NF-kappaB activation. <italic>Science</italic><bold>278</bold>, 860&#x02013;866. 10.1126/science.278.5339.860 (1997).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9346484</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coussens</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Werb</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammation and cancer</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>420</volume><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490959</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Coussens, L. M. &#x00026; Werb, Z. Inflammation and cancer. <italic>Nature</italic><bold>420</bold>, 860&#x02013;867. 10.1038/nature01322 (2002).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490959</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viatour</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Merville</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bours</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chariot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation of NF-kappaB and IkappaB proteins: Implications in cancer and inflammation</article-title><source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source><year>2005</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibs.2004.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653325</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Viatour, P., Merville, M. P., Bours, V. &#x00026; Chariot, A. Phosphorylation of NF-kappaB and IkappaB proteins: Implications in cancer and inflammation. <italic>Trends Biochem. Sci.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 43&#x02013;52. 10.1016/j.tibs.2004.11.009 (2005).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653325</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tumor microenvironment-driven non-cell-autonomous resistance to antineoplastic treatment</article-title><source>Mol. Cancer</source><year>2019</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>69</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12943-019-0992-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30927928</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Qu, Y. et al. Tumor microenvironment-driven non-cell-autonomous resistance to antineoplastic treatment. <italic>Mol. Cancer</italic><bold>18</bold>, 69. 10.1186/s12943-019-0992-4 (2019).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30927928</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doench</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optimized SgRNA design to maximize activity and minimize off-target effects of CRISPR-Cas9</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26780180</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Doench, J. G. et al. Optimized SgRNA design to maximize activity and minimize off-target effects of CRISPR-Cas9. <italic>Nat. Biotechnol.</italic><bold>34</bold>, 184&#x02013;191. 10.1038/nbt.3437 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26780180</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>