<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" id="deo270093" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">DEN Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">DEN Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2692-4609</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">DEO2</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>DEN Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-4609</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40066176</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11891260</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/deo2.70093</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">DEO270093</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A comparative assessment of contamination rates in gastrointestinal endoscope reprocessing: sterilization versus high&#x02010;level disinfection</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">CHANTAROJANASIRI <sc>et&#x000a0;al</sc>.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="deo270093-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chantarojanasiri</surname><given-names>Tanyaporn</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5781-8696</contrib-id><xref rid="deo270093-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>chtunya@gmail.com</email></address></contrib><contrib id="deo270093-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rungrueangmaitree</surname><given-names>Rachanikorn</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270093-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="deo270093-aff-0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270093-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thongsri</surname><given-names>Siriporn</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270093-aff-0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270093-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jampa&#x02010;ngern</surname><given-names>Urasa</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270093-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="deo270093-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ratanachu&#x02010;Ek</surname><given-names>Thawee</given-names></name><xref rid="deo270093-aff-0003" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="deo270093-aff-0001">
<label>
<sup>1</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Internal Medicine</named-content>
<institution>Rajavithi Hospital, College of Medicine, Rangsit University</institution>
<city>Bangkok</city>
<country country="TH">Thailand</country>
</aff><aff id="deo270093-aff-0002">
<label>
<sup>2</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Internal Medicine</named-content>
<institution>Charoenkrung Pracharak Hospital</institution>
<city>Bangkok</city>
<country country="TH">Thailand</country>
</aff><aff id="deo270093-aff-0003">
<label>
<sup>3</sup>
</label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Surgery</named-content>
<institution>Rajavithi Hospital</institution>
<city>Bangkok</city>
<country country="TH">Thailand</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo">
<label>*</label>
<bold>Correspondence</bold>
<break/>Tanyaporn Chantarojanasiri, Rajavithi Hospital, 2 Phayathai Road, Ratchathewi district, Bangkok, Thailand.<break/> Email: <email>chtunya@gmail.com</email>
<break/>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue seq="24">1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/deo2.v5.1</issue-id><elocation-id>e70093</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="rev-recd"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date>
<date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date>
</history><permissions><!--&#x000a9; 2025 John Wiley & Sons Ltd.--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2025 The Author(s). <italic toggle="yes">DEN Open</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of Japan Gastroenterological Endoscopy Society.</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:DEO2-5-e70093.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="deo270093-sec-0010"><title>Objectives</title><p>This study aimed to evaluate the disparity in culture results between sterilization and high&#x02010;level disinfection (HLD) for duodenoscopes and linear endoscopic ultrasound (EUS), and to assess the effectiveness of different bacterial contamination detection methods.</p></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0020"><title>Methods</title><p>This is a prospective randomized study, including duodenoscopes and linear EUS with adenosine triphosphate bioluminescence assay values below 200 relative light units after manual cleaning which were randomly assigned to undergo either sterilization or HLD in a 1:1 ratio. Following disinfection, all endoscopes were subjected to adenosine triphosphate bioluminescence assay testing and cultures using both swab and liquid samples from endoscope channels.</p></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0030"><title>Results</title><p>Totally 752 endoscopes (444 duodenoscopes and 308 linear EUS) were studied. After disinfection, the positive culture rates for the sterilization and HLD groups were 5.9% and 7.2%, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.460). No significant difference in contamination rates was observed between duodenoscopes and linear EUS (5.9% and 7.5%, respectively; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.379), and no significant association between contamination rates and the presence of biliary stones was seen (7.3%&#x000a0;vs. 6.9%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.613). The detection rate of bacteria from liquid samples taken from endoscope channels was 0.5%, which was significantly lower than the swabbing method (6.0%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001).</p></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0040"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study found no statistically significant difference in contamination rates between sterilization and HLD methods for gastrointestinal endoscope reprocessing. The type of endoscope and the presence of biliary stones did not influence the positive culture rate. The swabbing method showed significantly higher bacterial detection when compared with liquid samples.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="deo270093-kwd-0001">bacterial contamination</kwd><kwd id="deo270093-kwd-0002">duodenoscope</kwd><kwd id="deo270093-kwd-0003">endoscope reprocessing</kwd><kwd id="deo270093-kwd-0004">endoscopic ultrasound</kwd><kwd id="deo270093-kwd-0005">high&#x02010;level disinfection</kwd><kwd id="deo270093-kwd-0006">sterilization</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-0001"><funding-source>None.</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="3689"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>April 2025</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:6.5.4 mode:remove_FC converted:07.04.2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="deo270093-sec-0050"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Flexible endoscopes used in gastrointestinal endoscopy are classified as semi&#x02010;critical medical devices that contact with mucous membranes and might act as the vector for human&#x02010;to&#x02010;human transmission.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0002" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0004" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref> Endoscope reprocessing is one of the most important steps to prevent these endoscope&#x02010;transmitted infections to remove soil and eliminate microbial bioburden in these reusable endoscopes.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0006" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref> The minimal standard for reprocessing is high&#x02010;level disinfection (HLD),<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref> which destroys all types of vegetative non&#x02010;spore&#x02010;forming bacteria (Gram&#x02010;positive and Gram&#x02010;negative), fungi, all types of viruses (hydrophilic and lipophilic), and mycobacteria.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0003" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref> On the other hand, sterilization destroys all microorganisms including highly resistant bacterial spores.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0001" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref> The HLD technique included pre&#x02010;cleaning, manual cleaning, and reprocessing in automated endoscope reprocessors where the endoscope was soaked in an HLD disinfectant at the labeled exposure time and temperature as recommended by the company.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref> The sterilization technique contains similar steps for the cleaning as HLD as described above, but the exposure time for sterilization is longer than for disinfection in order to kill spores and spore&#x02010;forming bacteria.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0008" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref> Various sterilization methods have been proposed, such as ethylene oxide (ETO) gas sterilization, Hydrogen peroxide gas sterilization with and without plasma, and low&#x02010;temperature steam and formaldehyde sterilization.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0009" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref> Another liquid chemical sterilization included sterilization using Peracetic acid, which is more powerful than using glutaraldehyde or orthophthalaldehyde.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0010" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref> Peracetic acid is a highly biocidal oxidizer that removes surface contaminants (primarily protein) and has been used for the sterilization of medical and dental instruments in automated machines. It has the ability to inactivate gram&#x02010;positive and gram&#x02010;negative bacteria, fungi, yeasts, viruses, and bacterial spores when the equipment is exposed at different times and concentrations.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0011" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>European Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy&#x02010;European Society of Gastroenterology Nurses and Associates (ESGE&#x02010;ESGENA) guideline in 2007 stated standard testing of the endoscope which includes collection of liquid samples from endoscope channels for the bacterial culture and non&#x02010;culture method.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref> As routine bacterial cultures take around 3&#x02013;5 days for incubation, non&#x02010;culture methods such as Adenosine triphosphate (ATP) bioluminescence assay have been used more frequently as it provides a rapid measurement for micro&#x02010;organisms within a few minutes.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0005" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref> This technique estimates the ATP level, which is present in microorganisms, by using the light&#x02010;producing reaction between ATP, luciferin, and luciferase.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref> Luminometers convert the number of photons released in the reaction into relative light units (RLUs).<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0014" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref> However, ATP has limitations in discriminating between residual microbes, cellular debris, or organic soil and cannot replace the routine bacterial culture.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0015" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>Although the sterilization technique should be safer than the standard HLD, it requires more time to process which results in a longer endoscope turnover rate. Moreover, there have been limited studies regarding the clinical significance of these two.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0012" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref> The main objective of this study was to compare the contamination rate between sterilization and high&#x02010;level disinfection for gastrointestinal endoscope reprocessing. Secondary objectives were to evaluate the detection methods for the contamination as well as other factors that determine the contamination rate.</p></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0060"><title>METHODS</title><p>This was a prospective randomized study including duodenoscopes and linear echoendoscopes the ATP level after manual cleaning was less than 200 RLUs.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0016" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref> After manual cleaning, endoscopes were randomized to be disinfected using automated endoscope reprocessors either by sterilization or HLD technique in a 1:1 ratio. Reprocessing methods were performed with ADVANTAGE PLUS Pass&#x02010;Thru Automated Endoscope Reprocessor (AER; CANTEL Medical Corp.; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) for both sterilization and HLD group, using peracetic acid as the disinfectant. For sterilization, we used peracetic acid at concentrations of 850&#x000a0;ppm, at room temperature, and kept contact time with the endoscope for 10 minutes while in In HLD group, peracetic acid at the concentrations of 850&#x000a0;ppm, room temperature, was kept in contact for 5 minutes. As the contamination in the AER is common, mostly from contaminated rinsing water,<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0017" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref> water used in our AER underwent reverse osmosis before entering the machine.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="deo270093-fig-0001"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p>The ADVANTAGE PLUS Pass&#x02010;Thru Automated Endoscope Reprocessor (CANTEL Medical Corp.) machine.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DEO2-5-e70093-g003" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-1"/></fig><p>After disinfection in an automated endoscope reprocessor, all endoscopes were evaluated for ATP and cultures. For ATP tests, we obtained samples by swabbing the elevator mechanism with 3&#x000a0;M Clean&#x02010;trace surface ATP (3&#x000a0;M Clean Trace; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) and measuring with 3&#x000a0;MClean&#x02010;trace luminometer (3&#x000a0;M Clean Tract) which displayed the test result in RLU. Specimens for culture were obtained from endoscope channels using swabs and liquid samples. For the swabs method, sterile brushes were rotated over the endoscopic elevator both in closed and open positions before being sent to bacterial culture in a sterile container. For liquid samples, 20&#x000a0;mL of sterile saline was flushed through the suction and working channels of each endoscope and collected in sterile containers before sending for bacterial culture.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="deo270093-fig-0002"><label>FIGURE 2</label><caption><p>Adenosine triphosphate bioluminescence assay test kit using 3&#x000a0;M Clean&#x02010;trace surface ATP (3&#x000a0;M Clean Trace).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DEO2-5-e70093-g002" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-3"/></fig><p>Liquid samples from endoscope channels were incubated at 30&#x000b0;C on Tryptic soy agar, brain heart infusion broths, and thioglycollate broth. Samples from the swab method were also incubated at 30&#x000b0;C in grain heart infusion (broths and Thioglycollate broth. The final report for negative culture tests was 7 days of incubation. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> demonstrates the flowchart of this study.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="FIGURE" id="deo270093-fig-0003"><label>FIGURE 3</label><caption><p>Flowchart demonstrates the study process.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="DEO2-5-e70093-g001" position="anchor" id="jats-graphic-5"/></fig><p>As the endoscopic procedure related to biliary stones might associated with bacterial infection, the presence of biliary stones and sludges as well as pancreatic duct stones in the endoscopic report were recorded and analyzed.</p><sec id="deo270093-sec-0070"><title>Outcomes</title><p>The primary outcome was to compare the contamination rate as determined by the difference of culture results between sterilization and high&#x02010;level disinfection. Secondary outcomes were the sensitivity and specificity of ATP bioluminescence assay for detecting microorganisms and the effect of the sampling method. Clinical factors associated with contamination rate were also analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0080"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The sample size was calculated based on the study from Larsen that reported the incidence of contamination rate after duodenoscope reprocessing with HLD of 0.16 and that after double HLD ETO gas sterilization of 0.09.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref> When assuming a type I error of 5% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05) and a type II error of 0.20 (80% power) a total sample size of at least 728 endoscopes needed to be enrolled in the study.</p><p>The categorical data was reported as the number and percentage. The continuous data variables were presented as a mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;standard deviations. The continuous data were compared using the student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02010;test, and the categorical data were compared using the chi&#x02010;square test and McNemar's test. Statistical significance was considered significant at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 (2&#x02010;sided). All statistical analyses were performed by using IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, version 22.0.</p></sec></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0090"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="deo270093-sec-0100"><title>Baseline characteristics of the endoscopes</title><p>Overall, 752 endoscopes in which ATP test after manual cleaning&#x000a0;&#x0003c;200 RLU, which associated with complete manual cleaning,<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0021" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref> were included. Among these, 444 (59.0%) were duodenoscopes and the remaining 308 endoscopes were linear echoendoscope. The indications include biliary drainage and stricture management in ERCP, diagnostic and tissue acquisition as well as EUS interventions in EUS procedures. Stone and sludges were presented in 302 cases (40.16%) and 237 cases (31.52%) of duodenoscope. In the remaining 65 cases of EUS in the presence of stone, EUS was performed before ERCP for the detection of choledocholithiasis. We random 376 endoscopes to the HLD group and the remaining 376 endoscopes to the sterilization group. The baseline information of endoscopes and reprocessing methods are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270093-tbl-0001" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Type of endoscopes, the presence of stone/sludge, reprocessing methods, adenosine triphosphate bioluminescence assay (ATP), and Culture results.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" rowspan="1">Culture results</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Factors</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Positive (%)</p>
<p>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;= 49)</p>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<p>Negative (%)</p>
<p>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;= 703)</p>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Reprocessing methods</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.460</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLD</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (7.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">349 (92.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sterilization</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (5.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">354 (94.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Types of endoscopes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.379</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duodenoscope</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (5.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">418 (94.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear EUS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (7.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">285 (92.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Stone and sludge (All endoscopes)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.613</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (6.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419 (93.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (7.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">284 (92.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Stone and sludge (duodenoscopes)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (5.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (94.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (5.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223 (94.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP (RLUs)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.71&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 49.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.02&#x000a0;&#x000b1; 44.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.963</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="deo270093-tbl1-note-0001"><p>Abbreviations: EUS, endoscopic ultrasound; HLD, high&#x02010;level disinfection.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0110"><title>Culture results</title><p>The overall positive culture in this study was 6.5%. The most common microorganisms were <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> (20.4%), <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus cereus</italic> (14.3%), <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> (12.2%), and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus warneri</italic> (10.2%; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). When comparing both reprocessing methods, the sterilization group had a 5.9% positive culture result, which was lower than that of the HLD group (7.2%). However, this difference was not statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.460; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Considering other factors that might affect the result of reprocessing, there was no significant correlation between positive culture results and type of endoscope and the presence of stones and sludges in the duodenoscope, with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;values of 0.379 and 0.961, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The types of organisms detected in each type of reprocessing as well as the detection method are described in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270093-tbl-0002" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Prevalence and types of organism detected according to reprocessing method and sampling techniques.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reprocessing method</th><th align="left" colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" rowspan="1">HLD</th><th align="left" colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" rowspan="1">Sterilization</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">No. of positive culture (%) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x000a0;= 57)<xref rid="deo270093-tbl2-note-0002" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detection method</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluid</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swab</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluid</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swab</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (17.54)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus cereus</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (12.28)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (10.53)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus warneri</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (8.77)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus luteus</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Morganella morganii</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus haemolyticus</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus hominis</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus pasteuri</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Aerococcus viridans</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Brevundimonas diminuta</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus pulminis</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cellulosimicrobium cellulans</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Cutibacterium spp</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter cloacae</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Moraxella osloensis</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Roseomonas mucosa</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium radiobacter</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rhizobium</italic> spp.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Serratia marcescens</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus capitis</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Stenotrophomonas maltophila</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.75)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="deo270093-tbl2-note-0001"><p>Values are represented as <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> (%).</p></fn><fn id="deo270093-tbl2-note-0003"><p>Abbreviation: HLD, high&#x02010;level disinfection.</p></fn><fn id="deo270093-tbl2-note-0002"><label>*</label><p>Multiple organisms in the same scope were counted separately.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>When compared between the culture sampling methods, liquid samples from endoscope channels resulted in positive culture in four out of 752 cultures (0.5%), which is significantly lower when compared with positive tests in 45 out of 752 culture samples (6.0%) in the swab method (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>.).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="deo270093-tbl-0003" content-type="TABLE"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Different sampling techniques and the positive culture result.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sampling methods</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" rowspan="1">Culture results (%)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluid</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">752 (100.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">748 (99.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swab</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">752 (100.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (6.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">707 (94.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd.</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0120"><title>The ATP tests</title><p>Apart from the swab culture, we performed the ATP test from the elevator mechanism of all endoscopes. The mean ATP after endoscope reprocessing was comparable in both cultures: culture&#x02010;positive group (67.7) and culture&#x02010;negative group (64.0; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.963; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="deo270093-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The area under the curve for positive bacterial contamination was 0.484. When we used the ATP cut&#x02010;off value at 40 RLU as described in the previous study,<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0018" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref> the sensitivity and specificity for positive bacterial culture were only 59.2% and 39.7%, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0130"><title>Clinical follow&#x02010;up</title><p>No outbreak of endoscopic transmitted infection was observed during the study period. Among 46 cases with a positive culture, there were two patients with post&#x02010;ERCP cholangitis including one with mild cholangitis and one with severe cholangitis. In a case with severe cholangitis, the patient developed Klebsiella septicemia which is different from Bacillus spp. which was identified from the swab.</p></sec></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0140"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>We performed the study comparing the efficacy of high&#x02010;level disinfection and sterilization using peracetic acid as the disinfectant.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0013" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref> Our study, which compared the decontamination rate between HLD and sterilization in 752 endoscopes (444 duodenoscopes and 308 linear EUS), showed no significant difference in positive culture result (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.46). To control the initial degree of contamination, we excluded the cases in which ATP level after manual cleaning more than 200 RLU since this reflects the retaining residual organic and bioburden.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0020" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref>
</p><p>There have been several studies comparing HLD and other methods such as double HLD or using ETO gas for decontamination.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0023" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0024" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>24</sup>
</xref> A systematic review and meta&#x02010;analysis by Larsen,<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref> demonstrated that the contamination rate after only using HLD was 16.14%&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.019 (95% CI: 12.43%&#x02013;19.85%) which is higher than after using either double HLD or ETO gas sterilization (9.2%&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.025 [95% CI: 12.43%&#x02013;19.85%]).<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref> When using ETO gas sterilizations of duodenoscopes,<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0022" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref> the rate of positive culture after ETO gas sterilization was 1.2%, which was improved when compared with the reported level of 2% after HLD.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref> Our study used peracetic acid as the disinfectant, which resulted in a 7.2% bacterial detection rate after disinfection. This is much lower than the 16.14% detection rate in the previous meta&#x02010;analysis.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0019" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref> The possible explanation for these differences in the detection rate is that the meta&#x02010;analysis included studies performed in various centers between the years 2010&#x02013;2020. On the contrary, our study only included those using the automatic reprocessing machine, which is now currently recommended as the standard reprocessing process.</p><p>We studied other factors that might affect the contamination rate. As most cases of ERCP deal with biliary stones, which are considered contaminated compared to EUS, the rate of positive culture observed from the duodenoscope and linear EUS were analyzed. The contamination rate between the overall duodenoscope and linear EUS did not show a statistical difference [5.9% and 7.5%, respectively, (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02010;value 0.379)]. When focusing only on the duodenoscope with or without biliary stones, there was no significant difference in the rate of positive culture in the stone group (5.9%) and the no&#x02010;stone group (5.8%). As these scopes presented variable levels of contamination, we tried to eliminate the baseline difference in bacterial load by excluding those with ATP levels above 200 RLU after manual cleaning and using the water that underwent reverse osmosis to eliminate the water&#x02010;borne contamination. The species identified in the culture included <italic toggle="yes">S. epidermidis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. warneri</italic>, which are common bacterial contaminants. Still, two cases of acute cholangitis after ERCP were observed during our study but the pathogen identified was not the same as the culture from the scope tip.</p><p>Our study also underlined the technique to detect endoscopic contamination. The liquid sample method showed a significantly lower rate of positive bacterial culture when compared with the swab method (0.5% vs. 6.0%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001). This finding is similar to the study by Cattior which showed superior results when the brush is used for detecting bacterial contamination.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0026" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>26</sup>
</xref> Also, our study did not show significant differences in ATP levels among those with positive and negative bacterial cultures which is similar to the previous studies.<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0025" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>25</sup>
</xref>, <xref rid="deo270093-bib-0027" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>27</sup>
</xref> When using an ATP cut&#x02010;off level of 40 RLU as recommended by the study by Ridtitid,<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0028" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>28</sup>
</xref> we demonstrated only 59.2% sensitivity and 39.7% specificity. These findings emphasized the importance of the method to detect bacterial contamination.</p><p>There have been several studies comparing various methods of endoscopy decontamination but still limited studies directly comparing the contamination rate between sterilization and HLD. However, there are some limitations as this study has been conducted only in a single center. Moreover, the neutralizer that is used in many studies is not available in our country, so we only use sterile water that is transferred immediately to the laboratory room for microbial incubation. Further studies in various centers should be conducted to determine the benefit of sterilization over HLD.</p><p>In conclusion, our study did not find any significant difference in bacterial contamination rates between reprocessing using HLD and sterilization. Adding time for sterilization did not show a clinical advantage over standard HLD. These results support the recommendation of the ESGE&#x02010;ESGENA guidelines,<xref rid="deo270093-bib-0007" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref> which suggest that reprocessing with HLD is a standard method currently used for the disinfection of endoscopes. Further studies are needed to confirm the validity of ATP for detecting microbial contamination in gastrointestinal endoscopes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="deo270093-sec-0160"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT</title><p>None.</p></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0170"><title>ETHICS STATEMENT</title><p>Approval of the research protocol by an Institutional Reviewer Board: N/A</p></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0180"><title>PATIENT CONSENT STATEMENT</title><p>N/A.</p></sec><sec id="deo270093-sec-0190"><title>CLINICAL TRIAL REGISTRATION</title><p>N/A.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="deo270093-sec-0150"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>The authors would like to thank the Department of Microbiology, Rajavithi Hospital, for their tireless efforts to help us evaluate the culture result.</p></ack><ref-list id="deo270093-bibl-0001"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="deo270093-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Rutala</surname>
<given-names>WA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Disinfection and sterilization: An overview</article-title>. <source>Am J Infect Control</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>S2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23622742</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Rutala</surname>
<given-names>WA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Disinfection and sterilization in health care facilities: An overview and current issues</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Clin North Am</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>609</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>637</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27515140</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Klacik</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Transitioning from high&#x02010;level disinfection to sterilization for semicritical devices</article-title>. <source>Biomed Instrum Technol</source>
<year>2019</year>; <volume>53</volume>: <fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31013121</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Kovaleva</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Peters</surname>
<given-names>FT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>van der Mei</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Degener</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Transmission of infection by flexible gastrointestinal endoscopy and bronchoscopy</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>254</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23554415</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>SP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>WH</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Recent update on microbiological monitoring of gastrointestinal endoscopes after high&#x02010;level disinfection</article-title>. <source>Clin Endosc</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26473118</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Day</surname>
<given-names>LW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Muthusamy</surname>
<given-names>VR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Collins</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Multisociety guideline on reprocessing flexible GI endoscopes and accessories</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.e6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33353611</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Beilenhoff</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Neumann</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rey</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Esge&#x02010;esgena guideline: Cleaning and disinfection in gastrointestinal endoscopy</article-title>. <source>Endoscopy</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>939</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>957</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19009486</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="deo270093-cite-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Norman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor">
<string-name>
<surname>Somchai</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group> (ed). <source>Endoscopy</source>. <publisher-loc>Rijeka</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IntechOpen</publisher-name>, <year>2013</year>; Ch. 2.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Beilenhoff</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Biering</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Blum</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Reprocessing of flexible endoscopes and endoscopic accessories used in gastrointestinal endoscopy: Position statement of the European Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy (ESGE) and European Society of Gastroenterology Nurses and Associates (ESGENA) &#x02010; update 2018</article-title>. <source>Endoscopy</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>1205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1234</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30458567</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>W&#x02010;K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>C&#x02010;L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y&#x02010;W</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Recommendations and guidelines for endoscope reprocessing: Current position statement of digestive endoscopic society of Taiwan</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Immunol Infect</source>
<year>2024</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38135645</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="deo270093-cite-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Rutala</surname>
<given-names>WA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Weber</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <collab collab-type="authors">Healthcare Infection Control Practices Advisory Committee (HICPAC)</collab>
. <article-title>Guideline for disinfection and sterilization in healthcare facilities, 2008 [Internet]</article-title>. <year>2024</year>. Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/infection-control/hcp/disinfection-and-sterilization/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/infection&#x02010;control/hcp/disinfection&#x02010;and&#x02010;sterilization/index.html</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Beilenhoff</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Neumann</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rey</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Biering</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Blum</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Schmidt</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>ESGE&#x02010;ESGENA guideline for quality assurance in reprocessing: Microbiological surveillance testing in endoscopy</article-title>. <source>Endoscopy</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17327980</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Fernando</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Collignon</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Beckingham</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>ATP bioluminescence to validate the decontamination process of gastrointestinal endoscopes</article-title>. <source>Healthc Infect</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Aiken</surname>
<given-names>ZA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pratten</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Evaluation of atp bioluminescence assays for potential use in a hospital setting</article-title>. <source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>509</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21515983</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Olafsdottir</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Whelan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>A systematic review of adenosine triphosphate as a surrogate for bacterial contamination of duodenoscopes used for endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography</article-title>. <source>Am J Infect Control</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>705</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29395506</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Parohl</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stiefenhofer</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Heiligtag</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Monitoring of endoscope reprocessing with an adenosine triphosphate (ATP) bioluminescence method</article-title>. <source>GMS Hyg Infect Control</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <elocation-id>Doc04</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28405542</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Perumpail</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Marya</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>McGinty</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Muthusamy</surname>
<given-names>VR</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Endoscope reprocessing: Comparison of drying effectiveness and microbial levels with an automated drying and storage cabinet with forced filtered air and a standard storage cabinet</article-title>. <source>Am J Infect Control</source>
<year>2019</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>1083</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1089</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30962022</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Ofstead</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Doyle</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Eiland</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Practical toolkit for monitoring endoscope reprocessing effectiveness: Identification of viable bacteria on gastroscopes, colonoscopes, and bronchoscopes</article-title>. <source>Am J Infect Control</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>815</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>819</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26952038</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Larsen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Russell</surname>
<given-names>RV</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ockert</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Rate and impact of duodenoscope contamination: A systematic review and meta&#x02010;analysis</article-title>. <source>EClinicalMedicine</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <elocation-id>100451</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32954234</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Alfa</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fatima</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>The adenosine triphosphate test is a rapid and reliable audit tool to assess manual cleaning adequacy of flexible endoscope channels</article-title>. <source>Am J Infect Control</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22975364</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Alfa</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fatima</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Validation of adenosine triphosphate to audit manual cleaning of flexible endoscope channels</article-title>. <source>Am J Infect Control</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22980510</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Naryzhny</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Silas</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Impact of ethylene oxide gas sterilization of duodenoscopes after a carbapenem&#x02010;resistant Enterobacteriaceae outbreak</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>262</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26855298</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Snyder</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Smithey</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Randomized comparison of 3 high&#x02010;level disinfection and sterilization procedures for duodenoscopes</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>153</volume>: <fpage>1018</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28711629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Gromski</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sieber</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sherman</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rex</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Double high&#x02010;level disinfection versus liquid chemical sterilization for reprocessing of duodenoscopes used for ERCP: A prospective randomized study</article-title>. <source>Gastrointest Endosc</source>
<year>2021</year>; <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>927</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>931</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32745532</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Olafsdottir</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Smithey</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Adenosine triphosphate quantification correlates poorly with microbial contamination of duodenoscopes</article-title>. <source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>678</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>684</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28414009</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Cattoir</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vanzieleghem</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Florin</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Surveillance of endoscopes: Comparison of different sampling techniques</article-title>. <source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1062</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1069</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28633677</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Kwakman</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rauwers</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Buijs</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>de Groot</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vos</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bruno</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>No relation between adenosine triphosphate after manual cleaning and presence of microorganisms on endoscopes after automated high&#x02010;level disinfection</article-title>. <source>Endosc Int Open</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>E1275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E1281</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36118629</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="deo270093-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="deo270093-cite-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Ridtitid</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pakvisal</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chatsuwan</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>
<italic toggle="yes">et&#x000a0;al.</italic>
<article-title>Performance characteristics and optimal cut&#x02010;off value of triple adenylate nucleotides test versus adenosine triphosphate test as point&#x02010;of&#x02010;care testing for predicting inadequacy of duodenoscope reprocessing</article-title>. <source>J Hosp Infect</source>
<year>2020</year>; <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>348</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>356</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32768608</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>