<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC11681919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.74669</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Internal Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pulmonology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pulmonary Alveolar Proteinosis During Intensive Immunosuppressive Treatment for Acute Exacerbation of Interstitial Pneumonia: A Case Report and Literature Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yanagisawa</surname><given-names>Atsushi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Konaka</surname><given-names>Hachiro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Masaki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ihara</surname><given-names>Shoichi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tachibana</surname><given-names>Isao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Department of Respiratory Medicine and Clinical Immunology, Nippon Life Hospital, Osaka, JPN </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Department of Respiratory Medicine and Clinical Immunology, Osaka University, Osaka, JPN </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Atsushi Yanagisawa <email>atsushi2182med@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e74669</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2024, Yanagisawa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yanagisawa et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/311482-pulmonary-alveolar-proteinosis-during-intensive-immunosuppressive-treatment-for-acute-exacerbation-of-interstitial-pneumonia-a-case-report-and-literature-review">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/311482-pulmonary-alveolar-proteinosis-during-intensive-immunosuppressive-treatment-for-acute-exacerbation-of-interstitial-pneumonia-a-case-report-and-literature-review</self-uri><abstract><p>Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis (PAP) is a rare disease characterized by the accumulation of surfactants in the alveoli. It has been suggested that immunosuppressants contribute to the development and exacerbation of PAP. Here, we report the case of a 73-year-old man who developed secondary PAP after intensive immunosuppressive treatment for acute exacerbation of interstitial pneumonia (IP). In this case, despite the improvement of the inflammatory response after immunosuppressive treatment, Krebs von den Lungen-6 (KL-6) continued to increase, leading to the diagnosis of PAP. De-escalation of immunosuppressive treatment improved the PAP, allowing him to be discharged from the hospital. Although KL-6 is a useful marker of IP, when IP appears to be refractory and KL-6 increases despite the improvement of other inflammatory markers, physicians should consider the development of PAP and perform proactive bronchoscopic evaluation.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>acute exacerbation of interstitial pneumonia</kwd><kwd>immunosuppressive treatment</kwd><kwd>krebs von den lungen-6</kwd><kwd>pulmonary alveolar proteinosis</kwd><kwd>secondary pulmonary alveolar proteinosis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis (PAP) is a rare disease characterized by alveolar accumulation of surfactants due to impaired surfactant clearance by alveolar macrophages [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. PAP is clinically classified into three distinct forms: autoimmune, secondary, and congenital [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Secondary PAP (SPAP) is defined as PAP occurring alongside an underlying condition such as hematological, infectious, autoimmune diseases, or drug toxicities, which test negative for anti-granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor antibodies (GMAb) [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Although the pathogenesis of SPAP remains unclear, it is suggested that the underlying disease causes an abnormal number and function of alveolar macrophages, resulting in impaired surfactant clearance [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. SPAP is a very rare lung disorder comprising approximately 10% of cases of acquired PAP; however, a certain number of underdiagnosed SPAP cases have not been adequately examined because of the poor general condition caused by the underlying diseases [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Here, we report a case of SPAP that developed during the intensive immunosuppressive treatment for refractory interstitial pneumonia (IP).</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A non-smoking 73-year-old man initially presented to our hospital with abnormal shadows that were incidentally detected on chest computed tomography (CT). He had no history of hematological or autoimmune diseases. Although the serum rheumatoid factor was positive at 261 U/mL, other autoantibodies were negative and no clinical signs indicative of autoimmune disease were present. His serum Krebs von den Lungen-6 (KL-6) level was high at 3,192 U/mL. Chest CT showed ground-glass and reticular opacities and peripheral traction bronchiectasis in both his lower lobes but no crazy-paving pattern characteristic of PAP (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) and transbronchial lung biopsy (first bronchoscopy) revealed non-specific interstitial changes but no evidence of PAP. Based on these findings, the patient was diagnosed with IP. A surgical lung biopsy was not performed due to its invasive nature and lack of patient consent. The patient was therefore provisionally diagnosed with unclassifiable idiopathic IPs.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Clinical course.</title><p>LDH: lactate dehydrogenase; CRP: C-reactive protein; KL-6: Krebs von den Lungen-6; CT: computed tomography; IP: interstitial pneumonia. All days are counted from the day of admission due to acute exacerbation of IP.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074669-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>Approximately five months later, the patient was admitted to the hospital with dyspnea. Chest CT on admission showed newly appeared extensive ground-glass opacities. He was diagnosed with acute exacerbation of IP, and immunosuppressive treatment was initiated (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). On day 4 after admission, his respiratory status deteriorated, necessitating ventilation.&#x000a0;BAL performed in the lingular division of the left lung under intubation (second bronchoscopy) showed no turbidity and no evidence of PAP on cytological examination. Intensive immunosuppressive treatment with high-dose steroids, tacrolimus, and cyclophosphamide was administered to control IP progression&#x000a0;(Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p>Despite improvement in inflammatory markers such as serum lactate dehydrogenase and C-reactive protein following immunosuppressive treatment, abnormal shadows in both lower lobes remained, and oxygen demand did not improve at 2 L/min. Furthermore, serum KL-6 level, which had decreased&#x000a0;slightly&#x000a0;shortly after the start of the immunosuppressive treatment, increased to 14,981 U/mL (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Bronchoscopy on day 73 (third bronchoscopy) revealed that the BAL from the lingular division of the left lung (the same area examined on day 4) was turbid. This BAL fluid showed characteristic amorphous eosinophilic materials, which were positive for periodic acid-Schiff staining, and foamy macrophages with phagocytosing granular materials, consistent with PAP (Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Serum anti-GMAb levels were within the normal range, and new-onset SPAP was diagnosed. The culture of&#x000a0;the third BAL fluid was negative for&#x000a0;bacteria,&#x000a0;acid-fast&#x000a0;bacilli, and fungi. Therefore, we considered complications of infection to be negative and did not identify any other possible underlying causes of SPAP other than immunosuppressive treatment. Considering the possibility that immunosuppressive treatment exacerbated SPAP, we carefully reduced the dose of steroids while continuing to take tacrolimus. Consequently, oxygenation gradually improved, and oxygen administration was no longer required on day 100. Serum KL-6 also decreased after the third bronchoscopy, and the ground-glass opacities on chest CT also slowly diminished (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Cytopathological examination of the BAL on day 73.</title><p>BAL on day 73 (third bronchoscopy) showed abundant extracellular granular material (A, Papanicolaou stain) that was PAS positive. PAS-positive material is also present in alveolar macrophages (B, PAS stain).</p><p>PAS: periodic acid-Schiff; BAL: bronchoalveolar lavage.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0016-00000074669-i02" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Although the etiology of SPAP remains unclear, it is possibly caused by abnormal differentiation and dysfunction of alveolar macrophages. Immunosuppressive drugs can cause SPAP [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and are also associated with progression or exacerbation of PAP [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In this case, the findings of PAP, which were not observed in the first two BALs prior to immunosuppressive treatment, were confirmed in the third BAL, leading us to suspect that immunosuppressive treatment caused the onset and exacerbation of PAP. Discontinuation of the suspected drug is important in drug-induced PAP [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In this case, we carefully reduced the dose of steroids, given concerns about a relapse of IP, and we succeeded in improving the ground-glass opacity in the chest; however, the approach for adjusting immunosuppressive drugs when PAP coexists with an exacerbation of IP for which immunosuppressive treatment is required remains unclear.</p><p>Prior to this patient, there have been 13 documented reports on the development of PAP during immunosuppressive treatment for IP (Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>-<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Among them, 10 cases (cases 1, 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 11, 12, and 13) of IP were associated with dermatomyositis. Four cases (cases 1, 4, 7, and 13) of PAP were classified as SPAP, and the others as autoimmune PAP (APAP). Except for case 4, in which SPAP was caused by chronic myeloid leukemia, intensive multidrug immunosuppressive therapy was administered in all cases. Notably, in eight cases (cases 2, 4, 6, 7, 10, 11, 12, and 13), the increase in KL-6 during immunosuppressive treatment was attributed to the exacerbation of IP rather than the onset of PAP, leading to intensified immunosuppressive treatment and subsequent exacerbation of PAP. In our case, it was difficult to decide whether to escalate immunosuppressive treatment alone based on serum biomarkers and radiological findings when serum KL-6 levels were elevated. However, bronchoscopic evaluation allowed a definitive diagnosis of PAP and an appropriate reduction in immunosuppressive treatment. To avoid unnecessary immunosuppression, bronchoscopic evaluation may be recommended in cases of refractory IP with elevated KL-6 levels in contrast to the improvement of inflammation. If PAP is diagnosed during immunosuppressive treatment, physicians should consider that immunosuppressive treatment may exacerbate PAP and titrate immunosuppressive drugs regardless of KL-6 levels if other findings show an improvement in IP.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Cases of PAP that developed during immunosuppressive treatment for IP.</title><p><sup>#</sup>Values estimated from the line graphs in the figures, although the actual values are not provided in the main text. *Specific drug name is not mentioned in the text.</p><p>IP: interstitial pneumonia; PAP: pulmonary alveolar proteinosis; KL-6: Krebs von den Lungen-6; MDA-5: melanoma differentiation-associated gene 5; Ab: antibody; DM-ILD: dermatomyositis-associated interstitial lung disease; PSL: prednisolone; CyA: cyclosporine A; IVCY: intravenous cyclophosphamide; ARS: aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase; AZA: azathioprine; CML: chronic myeloid leukemia; TAC: tacrolimus; TFB: tofacitinib.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age/sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of IP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immunosuppressive treatment for IP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of PAP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum KL-6 level before immunosuppressive treatment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest serum KL-6 levels</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whether or not immunosuppressive treatment was intensified when KL-6 was elevated because of the onset of PAP</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 1 [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58, Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-MDA5 Ab-positive DM-ILD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + CyA + IVCY</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">714 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,600 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 2 [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-ARS Ab-positive DM-ILD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + CyA + IVCY</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">847 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,270 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensified</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 3 [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassifiable idiopathic IPs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + AZA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,429 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,900 U/mL<sup>#</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 4 [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organizing pneumonia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary (CML)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 U/mL<sup>#</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;5,000 U/mL<sup>#</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensified</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 5 [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52, Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-ARS Ab-positive DM-ILD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + CyA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,100 U/mL<sup>#</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,843 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 6 [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-ARS Ab-positive DM-ILD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + TAC + IVCY</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,513 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;5,000 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensified</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 7 [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-MDA5 Ab-positive DM-ILD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + TAC + IVCY + TFB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000 U/mL<sup>#</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,683 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensified</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 8 [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-ARS Ab-positive DM-ILD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + TAC + IVCY</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,860 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,153 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 9 [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM-ILD (Ab related to DM were negative)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + TAC + immunoglobulin therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,170 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 10 [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73, Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fibrotic hypersensitivity pneumonitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + CyA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,758 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26,974 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensified</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 11 [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50, Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-MDA5 Ab-positive DM-ILD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + TAC + IVCY</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250 U/mL<sup>#</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,200 U/mL<sup>#</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensified</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 12 [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinically amyopathic DM-ILD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corticosteroid + immunosuppressive agent<sup>&#x0ff0a;</sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autoimmune</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,517 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensified</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case 13 [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70, Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-ARS Ab-positive DM-ILD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + TAC + IVCY</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,197 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,743 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensified</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Our case</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73, Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassifiable idiopathic IPs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSL + TAC + IVCY</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,192 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,981 U/mL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Serum KL-6 levels are&#x000a0;generally higher in PAP cases than in other IP cases.&#x000a0;It has been reported that&#x000a0;the cut-off value for serum KL-6 to differentiate APAP from other IPs is 2,050 U/mL [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], though low KL-6 levels do not necessarily&#x000a0;exclude the diagnosis of PAP. Furthermore, it has also been reported that serum KL-6 levels in SPAP are as high as in APAP [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].&#x000a0;In seven of the 14 cases in Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, the serum KL-6 levels before the diagnosis of PAP exceeded&#x000a0;2,050 U/mL, an atypically high level for IP. Although IP has not been established as an underlying disease for SPAP, chronic IP can have focal histological features similar to PAP, termed "PAP-like change" [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. We suspect that these patients may have had a potential predisposition to developing PAP. Further investigations are warranted to elucidate the specific features of IP that may lead to PAP following&#x000a0;immunosuppressive therapy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Here, we report a case of SPAP that developed during intensive immunosuppressive treatment for acute exacerbation of IP. In cases of refractory IP in which KL-6 increases in contrast to the improvement of inflammation, we should suspect the development of PAP and perform proactive bronchoscopic evaluation.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dr. Ryu Jokoji (Department of Pathology, Nippon Life Hospital, Osaka, Japan) for pathological consultation and Dr. Yuhei Kinehara, Dr. Ryusuke Ninomiya (Department of Respiratory Medicine and Clinical Immunology, Nippon Life Hospital, Osaka, Japan), Dr. Toru Arai, and Dr. Takayuki Takimoto (Clinical Research Center, National Hospital Organization Kinki-Chuo Chest Medical Center, Osaka, Japan) for clinical consultation.</p></ack><fn-group content-type="conflict"><title>Disclosures</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Human subjects:</bold> Consent for treatment and open access publication was obtained or waived by all participants in this study.</p><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> In compliance with the ICMJE uniform disclosure form, all authors declare the following:</p><p><bold>Payment/services info:</bold> All authors have declared that no financial support was received from any organization for the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Financial relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that they have no financial relationships at present or within the previous three years with any organizations that might have an interest in the submitted work.</p><p><bold>Other relationships:</bold> All authors have declared that there are no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Atsushi Yanagisawa</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Atsushi Yanagisawa</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Hachiro Konaka, Masaki Tanaka, Shoichi Ihara, Isao Tachibana</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Hachiro Konaka, Masaki Tanaka, Shoichi Ihara, Isao Tachibana</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Primers</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bonella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>16</fpage><volume>5</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30846703</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Secondary pulmonary alveolar proteinosis complicating myelodysplastic syndrome results in worsening of prognosis: a retrospective cohort study in Japan</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tazawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>37</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24597668</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sirolimus-induced secondary pulmonary alveolar proteinosis</article-title><source>Respir Med Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>101566</fpage><volume>35</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34976718</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Outcome of corticosteroid administration in autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Akasaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>88</fpage><volume>15</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26264717</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Two cases of autoimmune and secondary pulmonary alveolar proteinosis during immunosuppressive therapy in dermatomyositis with interstitial lung disease</article-title><source>Mod Rheumatol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Imura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yukawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Handa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>729</lpage><volume>28</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26872621</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A case of autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis diagnosed after treatment with corticosteroids for manifestations of idiopathic interstitial pneumonia (in Japanese)</article-title><source>Ann Japanese Respir Soc</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kazutaka</surname><given-names>Yoshizawa</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Katsuaki</surname><given-names>Asakawa</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takuro</surname><given-names>Sakagami</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><volume>7</volume><year>2018</year><uri xlink:href="https://is.jrs.or.jp/quicklink/journal/nopass_pdf/ajrs/007060379j.pdf">https://is.jrs.or.jp/quicklink/journal/nopass_pdf/ajrs/007060379j.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis developing during steroid treatment in a patient with organizing pneumonia in association with atypical chronic myeloid leukemia</article-title><source>Clin Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Hosoda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><volume>7</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30899476</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis developed during immunosuppressive treatment in polymyositis with interstitial lung disease: a case report</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akasaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>84</fpage><volume>20</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32252718</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis exacerbated by steroid therapy due to misdiagnosis as anti-aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase (ARS) antibody positive- interstitial pneumonia: a case report</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Ishimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>120</fpage><volume>22</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35361191</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A case of secondary pulmonary alveolar proteinosis during therapy for interstitial pneumonia associated with anti-MDA5 antibody-positive dermatomyositis (in Japanese)</article-title><source>J Jpn Soc Respir Endoscopy</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Yuko</surname><given-names>Nitta</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yoshifumi</surname><given-names>Yamamoto</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eriko</surname><given-names>Hamada</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><volume>44</volume><year>2022</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/article/jjsre/44/3/44_228/_pdf/-char/ja">https://www.jstage.jst.go.jp/article/jjsre/44/3/44_228/_pdf/-char/ja</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Unilateral autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis with polymyositis-related interstitial lung disease</article-title><source>Intern Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hagiwara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>3095</fpage><lpage>3100</lpage><volume>61</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35370233</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis during the treatment of idiopathic inflammatory myopathy</article-title><source>Intern Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Shijubou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sawai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munakata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yamazoe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><volume>62</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35831113</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A case of development of autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis during the treatment of hypersensitivity pneumonitis</article-title><source>Respir Med Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Asami-Noyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>101862</fpage><volume>44</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37251358</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A case of autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis during the course of treatment of rapidly progressive interstitial pneumonia associated with anti-MDA5 antibody-positive dermatomyositis</article-title><source>BMC Pulm Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Yatomi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akasaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>170</fpage><volume>24</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38589870</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis during the treatment of nonspecific interstitial pneumonia complicated by clinically amyopathic dermatomyositis: a case report</article-title><source>Respirol Case Rep</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Arakawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shiota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Onizawa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>12</volume><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Secondary pulmonary alveolar proteinosis development during the treatment for anti-aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase antibody-positive interstitial lung disease</article-title><source>Intern Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takigawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>2971</fpage><lpage>2976</lpage><volume>63</volume><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38522908</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>CYFRA 21-1 as a disease severity marker for autoimmune pulmonary alveolar proteinosis</article-title><source>Respirology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><volume>19</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24251830</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Comparative study of high-resolution CT findings between autoimmune and secondary pulmonary alveolar proteinosis</article-title><source>Chest</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tazawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1348</fpage><lpage>1355</lpage><volume>136</volume><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19892674</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Pulmonary alveolar proteinosis-like change: a fairly common reaction associated with the severity of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>Respir Investig</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Nunomura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>272</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><volume>54</volume><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>