<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Appl Environ Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Appl Environ Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aem</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0099-2240</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-5336</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>1752 N St., N.W., Washington, DC</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40202322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC12093946</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">aem02253-24</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.02253-24</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">aem.02253-24</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbial Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="biological-terms"><compound-subject><compound-subject-part content-type="code">applied-and-industrial-microbiology</compound-subject-part><compound-subject-part content-type="label">Applied and Industrial Microbiology</compound-subject-part></compound-subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Polymer biodegradation by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> promotes reservoir souring during hydraulic fracturing</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8027-2086</contrib-id><name><surname>Scheffer</surname><given-names>Gabrielle</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>Anirban</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5271-5356</contrib-id><name><surname>Amundson</surname><given-names>Kaela K.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Rohan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8691-8116</contrib-id><name><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>Casey R. J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/><email>chubert@ucalgary.ca</email></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution>Geomicrobiology Group, Department of Biological Sciences, University of Calgary</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="Ringgold">98634</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/038rjvd86</institution-id></institution-wrap>, <city>Calgary</city>, <state>Alberta</state>, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution>Department of Biological Sciences, Idaho State University</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="Ringgold">166927</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/0162z8b04</institution-id></institution-wrap>, <city>Pocatello</city>, <state>Idaho</state>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution>Department of Soil and Crop Sciences, Colorado State University</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="Ringgold">124498</institution-id></institution-wrap>, <city>Fort Collins</city>, <state>Colorado</state>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution>Chevron Technical Center</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Houston</city>, <state>Texas</state>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><role>Editor</role><name><surname>Cann</surname><given-names>Isaac</given-names></name><aff><institution-wrap><institution>University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Urbana</city>, <state>Illinois</state>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to Casey R. J. Hubert, <email xlink:href="mailto:chubert@ucalgary.ca">chubert@ucalgary.ca</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>09</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>09</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><!--PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>.--><volume>91</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e02253-24</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date>
</history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2025 Scheffer et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Scheffer et al.</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" start_date="2025-04-09"/><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="aem.02253-24.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="primary"><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Hydraulically fractured shale reservoirs have facilitated studies of unexplored niches in the continental deep biosphere. In high-salinity North American shale systems, members of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> seem to be ubiquitous. Polymers like guar gum used as gelling agents in hydraulic fracturing fluids are known to be fermentable substrates, but metabolic pathways encoding these processes have not been characterized. To explore this, produced water samples from the Permian Basin were incubated both at 30&#x000b0;C to simulate above-ground storage conditions and at 60&#x000b0;C to simulate subsurface reservoir conditions. Guar metabolism coincided with <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> growing only at 30&#x000b0;C, revealing genes for polymer biodegradation through the mixed-acid fermentation pathway in different metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs). Whereas thiosulfate reduction to sulfide is often invoked to explain the dominance of <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> in these settings, genes for thiosulfate metabolism were lacking in <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> genomes with high estimated completeness. Sulfide production was observed in 60&#x000b0;C incubations, with corresponding enrichment of <italic toggle="yes">Desulfohalobium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionaceae</italic> that possess complete pathways for coupling mannose and acetate oxidation to sulfate reduction. These findings outline how production of fermentation intermediates (mannose and acetate) by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> in topside settings can result in reservoir souring when these metabolites are introduced into the subsurface through produced water reuse.</p><sec><title>IMPORTANCE</title><p>Hydraulically fractured shale oil reservoirs are ideal for studying extremophiles such as thermohalophiles. During hydraulic fracturing, reservoir production water is stored in surface ponds prior to reuse. Microorganisms in these systems therefore need to withstand various environmental changes such as the swing between warm downhole oil reservoir temperatures and cooler surface conditions. While most studies on hydraulically fractured oil reservoirs mimic the environmental conditions found in oil wells, this study follows this water cycle during fracking and the associated microbial metabolic potential during topside-produced water storage and subsurface oil reservoir conditions. Of particular interest are members of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> that have been reported to reduce thiosulfate contributing to souring of oil reservoirs. Here, we show that some <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> strains were unable to grow at hotter temperatures reflective of oil reservoir conditions and lack genes for thiosulfate reduction, despite the proposed importance of this metabolism in other studies. Rather, it is likely that these organisms metabolize complex organics in fracking fluids at lower temperatures, thereby generating substrates that support reservoir souring by thermophilic sulfate-reducing bacteria at higher temperatures. In this way, <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> promotes souring indirectly by feeding sulfate-reducing microorganisms fermentation products (e.g., acetate and hydrogen) rather than via direct sulfidogenesis via thiosulfate reduction. Therefore, the novelty of this research is not within the detection of known oil reservoir colonizing bacteria but rather in the relationship between bacteria and the indirect involvement of <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic>, promoting souring throughout the produced water reuse cycle.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic></kwd><kwd>sulfidogenesis</kwd><kwd>produced water storage</kwd><kwd>hydraulic fracturing</kwd><kwd>guar gum</kwd><kwd>fermentation</kwd><kwd>souring</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group specific-use="FundRef"><award-group award-type="grant" id="award-1"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000038</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><principal-award-recipient>
<name><surname>Scheffer</surname><given-names>Gabrielle</given-names></name>
</principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><counts><count count="1" count-type="supplementary-material"/><count count-type="authors" count="7"/><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="53"/><page-count count="16"/><word-count count="8438"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>May 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Studies of the terrestrial deep biosphere have advanced in recent years due to hydraulic fracturing for oil and gas production (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), showcasing polyextremophiles able to contend with high temperatures and salinities (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Shale formations ranging from 45&#x000b0;C to 190&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) with salinities of 40,000&#x02013;280,000 mg/L (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) are further impacted by organic polymers that are used in the hydraulic fracturing process. Common organic polymers used as gelling agents such as guar gum, carboxymethyl cellulose, or polyacrylamide-based compounds have all been shown to be biodegradable as fermentable substrates (for guar gum and carboxymethyl cellulose) or sources of nitrogen (for polyacrylamide-based polymers; <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>Among the most commonly detected microorganisms in hydraulically fractured shale reservoirs are members of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic>. These bacteria appear to be ubiquitous throughout most North American shale reservoir operations, including the Marcellus, Barnett, Antrim, and Haynesville systems (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> spp. are known to ferment a wide range of carbohydrates, including guar gum (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), but can also reduce elemental sulfur or thiosulfate to generate sulfide (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Formation of precursors to sulfide biogenesis (e.g., zero-valent polysulfide or thiosulfate intermediates) depends on temperature, oxygen, pH, metals, and the presence of other sulfur species (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). While some studies have measured very low to non-detectable levels of thiosulfate in shale reservoir systems (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), others have amended sulfur species as electron acceptors at artificially high levels to provoke sulfide generation in incubations (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). While the most well-understood paradigm for oil reservoir souring involves sulfate reduction, knowledge gaps persist regarding the mechanisms of souring in shale systems, where it is popular to invoke reduction of thiosulfate or elemental sulfur by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> spp. <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). These proposals are supported by the physiology of pure cultures, including the type strain <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium congolense</italic> (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>Limited water sources in the vicinity of hydraulic fracturing operations lead many companies to reuse produced water from subsurface reservoirs to generate subsequent batches of fracturing fluids (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). As part of this process, microbial populations are exposed to different temperatures for prolonged periods between produced water stored in what are termed storage ponds at the surface and reintroduction into the reservoir. In the Permian Basin, shale formations tend to be around 60&#x000b0;C, while surface storage ponds are commonly around 30&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Little is known about the persistence and activity of microorganisms in topside storage ponds, the populations that can survive for prolonged periods, the type of metabolic ability they have, and whether that metabolism influences operations. Given that <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> strains have only been isolated below 42&#x000b0;C, it is not well understood how they may withstand the temperature fluctuations between hotter subsurface reservoirs and cooler topside storage ponds (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The objectives of this study were to better understand how the genomic and biogeochemical dynamics between produced water storage ponds and hydraulically fractured oil reservoir conditions can contribute to carbon and sulfur cycling.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Metabolic processes at 30&#x000b0;C and 60&#x000b0;C</title><p>To stimulate growth in a way that mimics the presence of polymer biodegradation products, glucose and six volatile fatty acids (VFAs) were amended to the medium that was inoculated with produced water (20% vol/vol). The added 10 mM glucose was minimally consumed, decreasing by only 0.5 mM within the initial 14 days (results not shown), whereas VFAs exhibited more dynamic responses. In 60&#x000b0;C incubations, formate decreased between 14 and 21 days from 4.9 &#x000b1; 0.1 mM to 3.6 &#x000b1; 0.3 mM. Conversely, formate production was not observed in 30&#x000b0;C incubations with guar gum (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>), where acetate levels increased to 2.8 &#x000b1; 0.4 mM. A similar increase in acetate (up to 2.8 mM) was observed at 60&#x000b0;C with glucose and VFAs (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>). Acetate was also present in the incubations that did not receive VFA amendment (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A and C</xref>) owing to being present at 2.1 mM in the original produced water (<xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>). Carbon dioxide production was the most pronounced in 30&#x000b0;C guar gum incubations, reaching a final concentration of 1.2 &#x000b1; 0.1 mM (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). Only the incubations at 60&#x000b0;C with glucose and VFA showed a clear decrease in sulfate concentration, which dropped from 8.7 &#x000b1; 0.9 mM to 5.4 &#x000b1; 0.4 mM over the 42-day incubation period, coinciding with an increase in sulfide from 1.4 &#x000b1; 0.1 mM to 3.4 &#x000b1; 0.5 mM (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>). Sulfate concentrations did not change significantly in the 60&#x000b0;C incubation amended with guar, or in either of the 30&#x000b0;C incubations (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A through C</xref>). No thiosulfate was detected throughout the microbial incubations or in the initial produced water (<xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>). No metabolic activity was observed in any of the sterile or substrate-free controls. Incubations with undiluted produced water amended with the same organic substrates to the same final concentrations showed the same trends and are presented in the supplemental materials (<xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F1"><label>Fig 1</label><caption><p>Concentrations of acetate, formate, carbon dioxide, sulfate, and sulfide throughout 42 day incubations of produced water at 30&#x000b0;C (A and B) and 60&#x000b0;C (C and D) and amended with different substrates. Error bars represent standard deviations based on triplicate incubations for each condition. Carbon compounds are represented by dots connected with solid lines, and sulfur compounds are represented by squares connected with dashed lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aem.02253-24.f001" position="float"><alt-text>Dual lines and scatterplots present concentration in mM vs. days, depicting trends for acetate, formate, carbon dioxide, sulfate, sulfide, and thiosulfate under different conditions. Acetate depicts the highest concentration with variations.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Microbial community composition</title><p>Microbial populations enriched during incubations at 30&#x000b0;C featured a higher relative abundance of some <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> amplicon sequence variants (ASVs), whereas at 60&#x000b0;C members of this lineage did not increase relative to initial levels detected in the produced water samples (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Guar gum amendment at 30&#x000b0;C resulted in the highest relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic>, with ASV3 reaching 47% after 42 days of incubation (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>). Similarly, <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> ASV7 reached 10% after 21 days in the same 30&#x000b0;C incubation (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref>), whereas other incubation conditions resulted in its relative abundance dropping to 1%&#x02013;7% compared to being at 8% at the start of the incubation period (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B through D</xref>). On the other hand, <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> ASV5 did not increase in relative abundance. Incubations with undiluted produced water showed similar shifts in microbial community composition (<xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F2"><label>Fig 2</label><caption><p>Relative sequence abundance of abundant ASVs during produced water incubations at temperatures mimicking topside storage ponds (30&#x000b0;C) (A and B) and subsurface oil reservoirs (60&#x000b0;C) (C and D). Only ASVs detected at least once at over 5% relative abundance are included. The taxonomy of each ASV is denoted in parentheses based on genus (G) or family (F) level affiliations. Values and shading indicate the average percentage of relative abundance of each ASV at a given time point, based on amplicon sequencing of triplicate incubations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aem.02253-24.f002" position="float"><alt-text>Heatmaps present relative sequence abundance in percent for different ASVs across days under varying conditions. G_Halanaerobium and G_Halomonas depict the highest abundance with variations over time, while other genera maintain lower or fluctuating values.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>Putative sulfate-reducing bacteria were observed to increase from low levels at day 0 only in the 60&#x000b0;C incubations amended with glucose and VFA (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>), corresponding with sulfate reduction to sulfide (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>). In this incubation, increases in <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionales</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfobulbales</italic> were observed after 14 days of incubation, reaching 0.9% and 1.9%, respectively (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). Within <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionales</italic>, the most prevalent genus was <italic toggle="yes">Desulfohalobium</italic> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>), and within <italic toggle="yes">Desulfobulbales</italic>, the genera most enriched were <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrio</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfocapsa</italic> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref>). The other three incubation conditions showed very low levels (&#x0003c;0.5%) of putative sulfate-reducing microorganisms (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F3"><label>Fig 3</label><caption><p>Relative sequence abundance of putative sulfate-reducing bacteria in produced water incubated at 60&#x000b0;C with glucose and volatile fatty acids over a 42 day period (<bold>A</bold>). The heatmap (<bold>A</bold>) shows microbial orders within the samples as the cumulative sequence abundance of ASVs affiliated with these orders throughout this incubation. Highlighted boxes are plotted in greater detail (at the individual ASV level) in histograms for <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionales</italic> (<bold>B</bold>) and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfobulbales</italic> (<bold>C</bold>) corresponding to 14 days of incubation when an increase in sulfide was observed (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>). Relative abundances of sulfate-reducing microorganisms in the three other incubation types presented in this study are also presented for comparison (<bold>D</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aem.02253-24.f003" position="float"><alt-text>Heatmaps and bar graphs present relative sequence abundance in percent for different taxa under varying conditions. G_Desulfohalobium and G_Desulfocapsa depict the highest abundance with variations, while other taxa maintain lower or fluctuating values.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Metagenomic analysis and quality assessment of reconstructed metagenome-assembled genomes</title><p>Metagenomic sequencing was performed on DNA extracted from the sample collected after 28 days from the 30&#x000b0;C guar-amended incubations and the 60&#x000b0;C incubations amended with glucose and VFA, based on chemical changes observed by this point (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). A total of 25 unique medium- and high-quality metagenome-assembled genomes (MAGs) were reconstructed: 9 from 30&#x000b0;C incubations and 16 from 60&#x000b0;C incubations (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S4</xref>). MAGs belonging to the family <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobiaceae</italic> were only retrieved from the 30&#x000b0;C guar gum incubations (MAG 4, MAG 6, and MAG 8; <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Among these, MAG 6 was classified to the genus level (<italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic>), and MAG 4 and MAG 8 were classified to the species level as <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium saccharolyticum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">H. congolense</italic>, respectively. MAGs belonging to lineages known to include organisms capable of sulfate reduction were only found within the incubations at 60&#x000b0;C; MAG 10 and MAG 11 both belong to the order <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionales</italic> and could be further classified to the order <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionaceae</italic> (MAG 11) and to the species level as <italic toggle="yes">Desulfohalobium retbaense</italic> (MAG 10). Sulfate-reducing <italic toggle="yes">D. retbaense</italic> (MAG 10) had the highest replication rate among MAGs for which this feature was able to be estimated (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F4"><label>Fig 4</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Phylogenomic relationships among <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobiaceae</italic> from Permian Basin produced water and other environments reconstructed from GTDK-Tk. Three <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAGs from this study (i.e., 30&#x000b0;C incubation with guar gum) are highlighted in bold blue font. GenBank accession numbers for genomes from other environments are indicated in parentheses. These include the type strain <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium congolense</italic> (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and different <italic toggle="yes">H. saccharolyticum</italic> strains that are closely related to new MAGs uncovered in this study. The tree scale is shown at the bottom left of the figure. (<bold>B</bold>) Genes associated with thiosulfate metabolism/sulfur-compound disproportionation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aem.02253-24.f004" position="float"><alt-text>The phylogenetic tree and heatmap present Halanaerobium species relationships and gene counts for sulfur metabolism across shale formations. Halanaerobium congolense and Halanaerobium saccharolyticum have the highest gene counts, while others remain lower.</alt-text></graphic></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Taxonomy and predicted replication rate for 25 metagenome-assembled genomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">MAG<break/>ID</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Temp (&#x000b0;C)</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Taxonomy</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Predicted replication rate</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Completion (%)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Redundancy (%)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Domain</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Phylum</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Class</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Order</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Family</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Genus</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Species</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>1</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="9" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patescibacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gracilibacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BD1-5</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UBA6164</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UBA6164</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;<xref rid="T1_FN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup><italic toggle="yes">a</italic></sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA<xref rid="T1_FN2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup><italic toggle="yes">b</italic></sup></xref></td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">64</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Proteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gammaproteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pseudomonadales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonadaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas stutzeri</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">82</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>3</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Proteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alphaproteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rhodobacterales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rhodobacteraceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Roseovarius</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Firmicutes</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Halanaerobiia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Halanaerobiales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobiaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">H. saccharolyticum</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Marinilaniliaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>6</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Firmicutes</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Halanaerobiia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Halanaerobiales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobiaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>7</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Proteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gammaproteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pseudomonadales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halomonadaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halomonas</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halomonas ventosae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Firmicutes</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Halanaerobiia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Halanaerobiales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobiaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium congolense</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Proteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alphaproteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rhodobacterales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rhodobacteraceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Roseovarius</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">97</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">60</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Desulfobacterota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Desulfovibrionia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Desulfovibrionales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Desulfohalobiaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Desulfohalobium</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">D. retbaense</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.56</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">98</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>11</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Desulfobacterota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Desulfovibrionia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Desulfovibrionales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">88</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>12</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Flavobacterales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Flavobacteraceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Psychroflexus</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Psychroflexus salarius</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>13</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Proteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alphaproteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rhizobiales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Xanthobacteraceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bradyrhizobium</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">sp003020075</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.32</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>14</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Proteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gammaproteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pseudomonadales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halomonadaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Halomonas</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">H. ventosae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>15</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Proxilibacteraceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">SKHV01</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>16</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UBA12170</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>17</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Campylobacterota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Campylobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Campylobacterales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Arcobacteraceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">99</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>18</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Archaea</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Halobacteriota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Methanosarcina</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Methanosarcinales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Methanosarcinaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Methanohalophilus</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">73</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>19</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thermotogota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Thermotogae</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Petrotogales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">95</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>20</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patescibacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gracilibacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Absconditabacterales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">X112</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>21</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Defferibacterota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Defferibacteres</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Defferibacterales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Flexistipitaceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Flexistipes</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>22</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Proteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Alphaproteobacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Rhodobacterales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rhodobacteraceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Roseovarius</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.62</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>23</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Firmicutes</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacilli</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Izemoplasmatales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Izemoplasmataceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">93</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>24</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidota</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteroidia</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Flavobacterales</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Flavobacteraceae</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Psychroflexus</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">96</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
<bold>25</bold>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Bacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patescibacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Gracilibacteria</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">BD1-5</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UBA6164</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">UBA6164</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">76</td><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1"><label>
<sup>
<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>
</sup>
</label><p>&#x02013; no further taxonomy is available</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN2"><label>
<sup>
<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>
</sup>
</label><p>NA, not available.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Metabolic features encoded in MAGs</title><sec id="s2-4-1"><title>Guar gum fermentation potential in MAGs from 30&#x000b0;C incubations</title><p>Guar gum biodegradation by extracellular enzymes involves &#x003b2;-1,4-mannanase, which catalyzes hydrolysis of the mannose backbone of the polymer, and &#x003b1;-1,6-galactosidase, which breaks down galactose units branching out of the mannose backbone (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Both enzymes are encoded by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 6, with <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 4 and MAG 8 also encoding the &#x003b1;-galactosidase. The &#x003b2;-mannanase was also found in <italic toggle="yes">Marinilabillaceae</italic> MAG 5. ABC transporters for internalization of mannose are encoded by all three <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAGs as well as by <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic> MAG 2. The mannose phosphotransferase system (PTS) responsible for internalizing and phosphorolyzing mannose to mannose-6-phosphate was found in <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 8. Galactose ABC transporter genes were found in <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 4, MAG 6, and MAG 8, as well as in <italic toggle="yes">Halomonas</italic> MAG 7. No galactose permease genes were observed in any of the three MAGs.</p><p>The mannose PTS (enzyme IIA [EIIA] component) is known to internalize and phosphorolyze mannose to mannose-6-phosphate (found in MAG 6), which can then be further converted to fructose-6-phosphate by the mannose-6-phosphate isomerase and introduced in the glycolysis pathway. All three <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> genomes encode mannose-6-phosphate isomerases and enzymes needed for glycolysis (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Mannose conversion to mannose-6-phosphate requires a hexokinase that was not observed in any of the MAGs retrieved from the 30&#x000b0;C guar gum incubations. <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 6 and MAG 8 have complete sets of genes for the Leloir pathway to ferment galactose to UDP-glucose. Further conversion of UDP-glucose to glucose-1-phosphate by the UTP-glucose-1-phosphate-ur(idyltransferase) and glucose-6-phosphate by phosphoglucomutase (to integrate into glycolysis) is also encoded in both genomes (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Mannose and galactose were below detection throughout the incubation, suggesting active internalization of sugars by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic>.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F5"><label>Fig 5</label><caption><p>Genes present within three <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> genomes (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>) encoding enzymes for catalyzing biodegradation of guar gum polymers to acetate and CO<sub>2</sub> through the mixed-acid fermentation pathway (see <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). Green arrows and boxes indicate genes and pathways detected in <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAGs 4, 6, and 8 that were enriched at 30&#x000b0;C in the presence of guar gum. Red arrows and boxes signify non-detection. Dashed green lines indicate partial detection of genes but not the complete pathway.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aem.02253-24.f005" position="float"><alt-text>The diagram presents guar gum degradation, glycolysis, and fermentation with enzymes and intermediates. MAG 4, MAG 6, and MAG 8 map to key steps, with acetyl-CoA leading to acetate, ethanol, or lactate production through enzymatic conversions.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="s2-4-2"><title>Mixed-acid fermentation potential in MAGs from 30&#x000b0;C incubations</title><p>Mixed-acid fermentation includes production of lactate, acetate, ethanol, CO<sub>2</sub>, and H<sub>2</sub> via intermediate pyruvate. Genes for lactate dehydrogenase were not detected in three <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAGs or in any contigs annotated from the assemblies prior to binning, whereas genes for acetate production were found in all three <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAGs (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Furthermore, although complete pathways were not observed, genes for the production of CO<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>2</sub> are present in <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 4 and MAG 8. Genes encoding enzymes for ethanol production were observed in all three <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAGs. Acetate production was observed and could have been due to the conversion of pyruvate by the pyruvate oxidase gene. However, given that pyruvate oxidase was not observed in any of the three genomes, a more likely explanation is mixed-acid fermentation associated with guar gum biodegradation (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2-4-3"><title>Potential for sulfur metabolism in MAGs from 30&#x000b0;C and 60&#x000b0;C incubations</title><p>Members of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> have been studied for their potential to catalyze sulfidogenesis via thiosulfate reduction, yet very few genes related to thiosulfate metabolism were found in <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> genomes recovered from 30&#x000b0;C incubations with guar gum. Genes previously reported for sulfur compound disproportionation, i.e., molybdopterin oxidoreductases, SOX system genes (<italic toggle="yes">SoxABCDXYZ</italic>), sulfate adenylyltransferase, adenylylsulfate transferase subunits a and b, sulfite oxidoreductase, sulfide:quinone oxidoreductase, and sulfur oxigenase/reductase (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), were all absent from MAG 4, MAG 6, and MAG 8 despite being present in other <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> genomes (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>). They were not detected in MAG 4, MAG 6, and MAG 8, which exhibited 89%&#x02013;98% estimated completeness (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S4</xref>). However, thiosulfate sulfurtransferase genes were found within MAG 4 and MAG 8. A single rhodanese gene for thiosulfate conversion to elemental sulfur and sulfite was detected in all three MAGs, and genes for the further reduction of sulfite to sulfide were also detected in MAG 6 (<italic toggle="yes">sir</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">asrABC</italic>) and MAG 8 (<italic toggle="yes">sir</italic>), as shown in <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5B</xref>. Genes encoding the complete pathway for dissimilatory sulfate reduction were identified in genomes assembled from the 60&#x000b0;C incubations classified as <italic toggle="yes">Desulfohalobium</italic> (MAG 10) and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionaceae</italic> (MAG 11). Genes for dissimilatory sulfate reduction were not detected in the metagenomes associated with incubation at 30&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4-4"><title>Organotrophic potential of sulfate reducers and other thermophiles at 60<bold>&#x000b0;C</bold></title><p>Genes encoding complete pathways for the oxidation of acetate to CO<sub>2</sub> and acetyl-coA (acetyl-coA pathway) in MAG 10 and MAG 11 with higher replication rates (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) suggest that these organisms can couple acetate oxidation to sulfate reduction at higher temperatures (60&#x000b0;C) in the subsurface. Highly incomplete genomic pathways for the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle were retrieved from both MAG 10 and 11 with key steps missing (genes for the conversion of oxaloacetate to citrate, succinate to fumarate, fumarate to malate, and malate to oxaloacetate). Interestingly, while no genes related to hydrolysis of guar gum were found within these genomes, genes for the internalization of mannose and conversion to mannose-6-phosphate (PTS system EIIA components) were retrieved from sulfate-reducing <italic toggle="yes">Desulfohalobium</italic> MAG 10 and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionaceae</italic> MAG 11, with the latter also having hexokinase genes for converting mannose to mannose-6-phosphate. Both sulfate-reducing microorganisms have genes for the conversion of mannose-6-phosphate to fructose-6-phosphate and genes for the glycolysis pathway that are complete (MAG 10) or nearly complete (MAG 11). This indicates the potential to use mannose to complete glycolysis, coupled to sulfate reduction.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Fermentative metabolism under lower-temperature storage pond conditions</title><p>Members of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> have been extensively documented within hydraulically fractured shale oil reservoirs where they potentially catalyze fermentation (notably guar gum utilization) and/or thiosulfate metabolism (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Despite <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> being routinely recovered from shale formations with downhole temperatures up to 60&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> spp. have not been cultivated above 42&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Consistent with these observations, <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> ASVs and metagenomic raw reads increased in relative abundance during incubations at 30&#x000b0;C with guar gum but not in 60&#x000b0;C incubations (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>; <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>; <xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Fig. S4</xref>). This is corroborated by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 4, MAG 6, and MAG 8 that were enriched at 30&#x000b0;C all having optimal growth temperatures of 39&#x000b0;C&#x02013;40&#x000b0;C estimated by the Tome algorithm (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p><p>Previous studies have not reported on biochemical pathways for guar gum metabolism by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> spp., although isolated members of this genus have been shown to biodegrade the polymer, commonly used as a gelling agent during hydraulic fracturing operations (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Liang et al. (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) isolated a strain of <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> able to couple guar gum conversion to acetate with the reduction of thiosulfate to sulfide (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). In the present study, <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAGs encode mannanase and galactosidase genes for internalizing mannose and galactose derived from extracellular hydrolysis of guar gum, i.e., ABC transporters for both sugars or the mannose PTS system (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Once inside the cell, these sugars can be metabolized through a mixed-acid fermentation pathway (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>) to produce acetate and CO<sub>2</sub>, which were both observed to accumulate in the corresponding incubations (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>).</p><p>Accordingly, fermentation of larger substrates by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>) may be a more plausible metabolism than thiosulfate reduction in lower-temperature topside conditions like produced water storage ponds. Fermentation appeared to be the predominant metabolism when produced water was incubated under temperatures representative of storage ponds (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), resulting in communities dominated by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). The presence of very few genes for thiosulfate metabolism in three near-complete <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> genomes from this Permian Basin-produced water is notable (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAGs contain fewer genes for thiosulfate metabolism than in closely related genomes (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A</xref>) as well as genomes analyzed in previous studies of other basins (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>). In particular, <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 8 shares 97.8 average nucleotide identity with type strain <italic toggle="yes">H. congolense</italic>, an oil reservoir isolated that has been characterized as a thiosulfate reducer (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Genes for rhodanese, which catalyzes thiosulfate disproportionation into elemental sulfur and sulfite (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), were found in a single copy within <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 4, MAG 6, and MAG 8 compared to the multiple copies in other <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> strains (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4B</xref>). Genes for a thiosulfate sulfurtransferase, leading to the same intermediates as rhodanese, were found within MAG 4 and MAG 8. These enzymes alone would not result in the production of sulfide (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), whereas <italic toggle="yes">asr</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sir</italic> genes in MAG 6 and MAG 8 enable conversion of sulfite to sulfide. Thus, while thiosulfate-based souring by those two organisms is possible in principle, levels of thiosulfate remained below detection limits within the produced water samples and during the incubation experiments (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>; <xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>). Furthermore, these <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> strains did not grow at temperatures representative of the oil reservoir, where thiosulfate could potentially be present (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S2</xref>).</p><p>These observations raise questions about the likelihood of thiosulfatedriven biogenic souring in oil reservoirs more generally and plausible sources of thiosulfate as a terminal electron acceptor. Oxidation of pyrite in Permian Basin formations represents one possible mechanism. However, it has been suggested that this reaction is more likely to result in sulfate generation due to the unstable nature of the thiosulfate molecule (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Thiosulfate was not detected in the produced water samples used in this study and accordingly was not amended into incubations designed to mimic conditions in the reservoir. Had thiosulfate been included, it appears unlikely that the <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> strains uncovered in the 30&#x000b0;C incubations would have catalyzed thiosulfate reduction based on the evidence from their genomes, although it cannot be ruled out that this would have enriched different thiosulfate-reducing bacteria as other studies have demonstrated (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p><p>Indeed, very few studies have measured the presence of thiosulfate in produced water. Liang et al. (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) similarly found <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> with genes for thiosulfate metabolism but in a system with a very low thiosulfate concentration of 0.02 mM. That study conducted incubations at 40&#x000b0;C, whereas the formation that the samples originated from (Utica shale) reached from 55&#x000b0;C to 125&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Another strain of <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> able to couple thiosulfate reduction with guar metabolism was shown to do so in the presence of 10 mM thiosulfate amended to Barnett shale-produced water in which thiosulfate levels were otherwise below detection limits (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Again, the incubation temperature was at 37&#x000b0;C, despite the Barnett shale formation temperatures reaching 65&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Other studies of shale reservoir <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> found genes for the reduction of thiosulfate but did not report thiosulfate concentrations in the produced water (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Based on these observations combined with results reported here, <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> thiosulfate reduction by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> is difficult to confirm. While more work is needed to detect and measure levels of thiosulfate in these systems to understand a potential role for <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> in sulfide biogenesis, it is also worthwhile to consider alternate explanations for the predominance of these organisms in shale reservoir systems.</p></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title><italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> acting in concert with sulfate-reducing bacteria during produced water reuse</title><p>Sulfate reduction to sulfide at 60&#x000b0;C in incubations amended with glucose and volatile fatty acids (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) appears to be catalyzed by thermophilic sulfate-reducing bacteria including <italic toggle="yes">Desulfohalobium</italic> MAG 10 and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionaceae</italic> MAG 11, despite amplicon sequencing suggesting these groups were present in relatively low abundance (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) during the incubation period. At 30&#x000b0;C, a small drop in acetate (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>) and a slight increase in relative abundance of putative sulfate-reducing bacteria (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3D</xref>) suggest sulfatereducing activity under these conditions should not be ruled out. Sulfate reduction corresponding to low abundances of putative sulfate-reducing microorganisms has been reported in other environmental systems (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In the 60&#x000b0;C incubations presented here, sulfate reduction took place during the first half of the 42-day incubation period (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>), coinciding with the largest increase in relative sequence abundance of ASVs affiliated with known sulfate-reducing bacteria (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Reconstruction of <italic toggle="yes">D. retbaense</italic> (MAG 10) and a member of the <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionaceae</italic> family (MAG 11) showed that in addition to complete pathways for dissimilatory sulfate reduction, these genomes contained incomplete sets of genes for the TCA cycle and all genes required for acetate oxidation via the acetyl-CoA pathway.</p><p>This understanding is consistent with <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> spp. being detected in saline oil fields experiencing high levels of souring caused by sulfate-reducing microorganisms (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Metagenomic sequencing points to the main role of <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> in this system being able to secrete extracellular enzymes to hydrolyze guar gum, thereby releasing mannose and galactose and leading to the release of other by-products (hydrogen, carbon dioxide, and acetate) for other microorganisms to utilize whether in topside storage (e.g., storage ponds) mimicked by 30&#x000b0;C incubations or in the subsurface mimicked by 60&#x000b0;C incubations. This evidence of fermentative metabolism is particularly important in the context of reinjecting produced water after a period of topside storage at lower temperature that affords <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> the opportunity to generate electron donors for sulfate reduction, including hexose sugars (mannose and galactose), acetate, ethanol, and hydrogen. If these compounds are introduced into the subsurface in the presence of sulfate, thermophilic sulfate-reducing microorganisms in the reservoir are presented with the opportunity to catalyze reservoir souring via dissimilatory sulfate reduction. Supporting this statement is the presence of acetate and sulfate within the sample obtained from the Permian Basin oil reservoir-produced water obtained for this study (<xref rid="SuF1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>). Also, extracellular &#x003b2;-1,4-mannanase secretion at storage pond temperatures for hydrolysis of guar gum would lead to increased levels of mannose (<italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> MAG 4, MAG 6, and MAG 8), which could be directly coupled to dissimilatory sulfate reduction by <italic toggle="yes">Desulfohalobium</italic> (MAG 10) and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrionaceae</italic> (MAG 11). Further studies should examine this in more detail by incubating produced water directly with by-products of guar gum biodegradation extracts as a way to provoke sulfate-reducing activity at higher temperatures.</p><p>In conclusion, produced water incubations at 30&#x000b0;C and 60&#x000b0;C demonstrated the potential for cooperative metabolic activity by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> and sulfate-reducing microorganisms via produced water storage and reuse in hydraulically fractured shale formations. This highlights the importance of organotrophic metabolism by <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> and its potential for indirectly promoting reservoir souring by providing substrates for sulfate-reducing microorganisms. Fermentative metabolism is therefore a likely explanation for the broad prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Halanaerobium</italic> in shale oil fields.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s4-1"><title>Microbial incubations</title><p>Produced water samples from Permian Basin hydraulically fractured wells (New Mexico, USA) were used to set up microbial incubations. The medium (per 1 L) was composed of 1 g NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, 10 g MgCl<sub>2</sub>&#x02022;6H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.1 g CaCl<sub>2</sub>&#x02022;2H<sub>2</sub>O, 1 g KCl, 100 g NaCl, 0.72 g cysteine HCl, 500 &#x000b5;M K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>/KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.2% (vol/vol) NAHCO<sub>3</sub>, 10 mL trace element solution, and 10 mL vitamin solution (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Microcosms were prepared by combining 20 mL saline-produced water (14.6% salinity) with 80 mL of medium in 125 mL serum bottles under anoxic conditions. Serum bottles were immediately sealed with sterile rubber stoppers, and the headspace was exchanged with N<sub>2</sub>:CO<sub>2</sub> (90%:10%). Two different substrate types were used, either glucose (10 mM) together with a VFA mixture (acetate, butyrate, formate, lactate, propionate, and succinate, each at 5 mM) or guar gum at a concentration of 0.05% (wt/vol). Sulfate was added to all microcosms to a final concentration of 10 mM. Bottles were incubated at 30&#x000b0;C or 60&#x000b0;C. Sterile controls (medium only with substrates) and substrate-free controls (medium and produced water without substrates) were prepared and incubated in parallel. Parallel incubations with the same substrates and electron acceptors added directly to undiluted produced water were run for comparison. Subsamples from microcosms were removed using N<sub>2</sub>:CO<sub>2</sub>-flushed sterile syringes and immediately stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C until further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Concentrations of metabolic reactants and products</title><p>Sulfate depletion was assessed by ion chromatography (Dionex ICS-5000) using an analytical column (AS23) with 8 mM Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>/1 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub> eluent at a flow rate of 1 mL/min. Chromeleon software was used for visualization. Peak area calibration used Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> standard solutions. Sulfide production was measured using a spectrophotometric assay (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Samples for sulfide analysis were collected at different time points of the experiment and mixed with zinc acetate (20% [vol/vol]) to limit sulfide volatility (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Samples were kept frozen until analyzed.</p><p>Volatile fatty acid levels were measured using high-performance liquid chromatography in an Ultimate 3000 RSLC system with a 5 mM H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> mobile phase at a flow rate of 0.6 mL/min and a temperature of 60&#x000b0;C using a Bio-Rad Aminex HPX-87H column. Carbon dioxide production was measured using gas chromatography with a flame ionization detector by injecting headspace gas into an Agilent 7890B gas chromatograph equipped with a Hayesep N packing column (stainless steel tubing, 0.5 m length &#x000d7; 1/8 inch outer diameter &#x000d7; 2 mm internal diameter, mesh size 80/100). Helium was used as a carrier gas (flow rate 21 mL/min). The oven temperature was set to 105&#x000b0;C, and carbon dioxide was detected by a thermal conductivity detector set to 200&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Genomic DNA extraction</title><p>Five-milliliter aliquots were removed from microcosms at days 0, 7, 14, 21, and 28 and then frozen until genomic DNA was extracted using the DNeasy PowerSoil extraction kit (Qiagen) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Resulting DNA concentrations were measured by fluorimetry (Qubit, Qiagen). DNA was used for both 16S rRNA gene amplicon sequencing and shotgun metagenomic sequencing, as described below.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>16S rRNA gene amplicon sequencing and sequence analysis</title><p>The V4 hypervariable region of the 16S rRNA gene was amplified using primers 515F (GTGYCAGCMGCCGCGGTAA) and 806R (GGACTACNVGGGTWTCTAAT). PCR reactions with a total volume of 25 &#x000b5;L included 2&#x000d7; KAPA HiFi Hot Start Ready Mix (KAPA Biosystems), a final concentration of 0.1 mM for each primer, and 7.5 &#x000b5;L of DNA sample. PCR included an initial denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 30 seconds, annealing at 55&#x000b0;C for 45 seconds, and extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 1 min. This was followed by a final extension for 5 min at 72&#x000b0;C. PCR products followed post-PCR. Triplicate PCR products were pooled prior to cleanup and indexing. Indexed amplicon samples were sequenced using Illumina&#x02019;s v3 600-cycle (paired-end) reagent kit on an in-house Illumina MiSeq benchtop sequencer (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) after all DNA extraction blanks and PCR reagent blanks were confirmed negative for amplification. Quality-controlled reads were merged and subsequently dereplicated to construct an ASV table. Relative abundance calculations were based on the number of unrarefied reads per sample. Analysis and visualization were done using R and GraphPad Prism (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Metagenomic sequencing</title><p>Genomic DNA extracted from produced water incubations after 28 days of incubation was sent to the Centre for Health Genomics and Informatics (University of Calgary, Calgary, Canada) for library preparation using sonication (Covaris) and sequencing using a NovaSeq platform (Illumina). Adapters were removed; the last 151 bp of the last read was trimmed; contaminants (PhiX control V3 library, Illumina) were filtered; and lowquality ends were clipped off with BBDuk (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Assembly was done with Megahit using a co-assembly for replicates of a given sample, and reads were assembled using Bowtie2 (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). DasTool allowed for binning of the contigs while combining outputs from Concoct, Maxbin, and Metabat (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref><xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Quality assessment of the bins was performed with CheckM &#x0201c;lineage_wf&#x0201d; (v.1.1.2) with taxonomy assigned using GTDB-Tk &#x0201c;classify_wf&#x0201d; (v.1.5.0) (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Only bins with &#x0003c;10% contamination and &#x0003e;70% completeness were retained for annotation and further study. DRAM (v.1.2) was used to annotate dereplicated MAGs for functional potential (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). PhyloFlash allowed for taxonomic identification from the metagenomic reads (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Estimations of temperature optima for MAGs used Tome (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). iRep allowed for estimation of replication rates on MAGs (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Genomes outside the minimal requirements (under 2% contamination, over 75% complete) to analyze with iRep were excluded from the analyses.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Comparative analyses of other halanaerobium genomes</title><p>Genomes from other studies (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">&#x02013;</xref><xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) were downloaded from the National Center for Biotechnology Information (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) or JGI (<ext-link xlink:href="https://genome.jgi.doe.gov/portal/" ext-link-type="uri">https://genome.jgi.doe.gov/portal/</ext-link>) as an assembly FASTA file and annotated with DRAM for comparison of thiosulfate-related metabolism.</p></sec><sec id="s4-7"><title>Phylogeny</title><p>Phylogenomic trees were constructed using CheckM (v.1.1.3) and included 2,052 finished genomes and 3,604 draft genomes from the Integrated Microbial Genomes database (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Genes were aligned using GAMMA and WAG models. Nodes were interpreted as bootstrap values, and the tree was constructed using Dendroscope for visualization (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>The authors acknowledge that this work was done on the traditional territories of the Blackfoot Confederacy (Siksika, Kainai, and Piikani), the Tsuut'ina, the &#x000ce;y&#x000e2;xe Nakoda Nations, the M&#x000e9;tis Nation (Region 3), and all people who make their homes in the Treaty 7 region of Mohk&#x000ed;nsstsisi (now named Calgary). The authors thank Dana Jwad for laboratory support as well as Srijak Bhatnagar for bioinformatics support.</p><p>This work was funded by Chevron and grants from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada to C.R.J.H. and by the Eyes High Doctoral Scholarship (University of Calgary) and the Alexander Graham Bell scholarship (Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada [NSERC]) to G.S.</p><p>P.E. and C.R.J.H. secured produced water samples; G.S. and A.C. designed the study with input from C.R.J.H., K.A. and M.W.; G.S. and R.K. performed lab work; and G.S. wrote the manuscript with input from C.R.J.H. All authors reviewed and agreed on the published version of the manuscript.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5-1"><title>DATA AVAILABILITY</title><p>The data discussed in this paper are available online under GenBank BioProject number <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA972118/" ext-link-type="uri">PRJNA972118</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5-2"><title>SUPPLEMENTAL MATERIAL</title><p specific-use="print-only">The following material is available online at <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.02253-24" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1128/aem.02253-24</ext-link>.</p><supplementary-material id="SuF1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.02253-24.SuF1</object-id><label>Supplemental material</label><caption><title>aem.02253-24-s0001.docx</title><p>Figures S1 to S4; Tables S1 and S2.</p></caption><media xlink:href="aem.02253-24-s0001.docx"/></supplementary-material><p specific-use="online-only">ASM does not own the copyrights to Supplemental Material that may be linked to, or accessed through, an article. The authors have granted ASM a non-exclusive, world-wide license to publish the Supplemental Material files. Please contact the corresponding author directly for reuse. </p></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Whitman</surname>
<given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coleman</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wiebe</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1998</year>. <article-title>Prokaryotes: the unseen majority</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>95</volume>:<fpage>6578</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6583</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.12.6578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9618454</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mouser</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borton</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Darrah</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hartsock</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wrighton</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Hydraulic fracturing offers view of microbial life in the deep terrestrial subsurface</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>18</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsec/fiw166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dutta</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dutta Gupta</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarkar</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roy</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mukherjee</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sar</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <article-title>Exploration of deep terrestrial subsurface microbiome in Late Cretaceous Deccan traps and underlying Archean basement, India</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>17459</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-35940-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30498254</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Daly</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borton</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkins</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoyt</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kountz</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolfe</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Welch</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marcus</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Trexler</surname>
<given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>MacRae</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krzycki</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mouser</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wrighton</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Microbial metabolisms in a 2.5-km-deep ecosystem created by hydraulic fracturing in shales</article-title>. <source>Nat Microbiol</source>
<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>16146</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmicrobiol.2016.146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27595198</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davidova</surname>
<given-names>IA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marks</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stamps</surname>
<given-names>BW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harriman</surname>
<given-names>BH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stevenson</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duncan</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suflita</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Metabolic capability of a predominant Halanaerobium sp. in hydraulically fractured gas wells and its implication in pipeline corrosion</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<elocation-id>988</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27446028</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Booker</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borton</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daly</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Welch</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicora</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoyt</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Purvine</surname>
<given-names>SO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wolfe</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mouser</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lipton</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wrighton</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkins</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Sulfide generation by dominant Halanaerobium microorganisms in hydraulically fractured shales</article-title>. <source>mSphere</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<elocation-id>e00257-17</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphereDirect.00257-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28685163</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lipus</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vikram</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ross</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bain</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gulliver</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hammack</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bibby</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Predominance and metabolic potential of Halanaerobium spp. in produced water from hydraulically fractured Marcellus shale wells</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>83</volume>:<elocation-id>e02659-16</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02659-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28159795</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Vigneron</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alsop</surname>
<given-names>EB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lomans</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kyrpides</surname>
<given-names>NC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Head</surname>
<given-names>IM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsesmetzis</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Succession in the petroleum reservoir microbiome through an oil field production lifecycle</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>2141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2154</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2017.78</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28524866</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>MV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Panescu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanson</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Welch</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sheets</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nastasi</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daly</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cole</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Darrah</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkins</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wrighton</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mouser</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <article-title>Members of Marinobacter and Arcobacter influence system biogeochemistry during early production of hydraulically fractured natural gas wells in the Appalachian basin</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>2646</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.02646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30498478</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>The effect of temperature on flowback data analysis in shale gas reservoirs: a simulation-based study</article-title>. <source>Energies</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>3751</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/en12193751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>You</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tian</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Salinity of flowback fracturing fluid in shale reservoir and its reservoir damage: experimental and field study</article-title>. <source>J Pet Sci Eng</source>
<volume>211</volume>:<fpage>110217</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.petrol.2022.110217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hasan</surname>
<given-names>AMA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abdel-Raouf</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <article-title>Applications of guar gum and its derivatives in petroleum industry: a review</article-title>. <source>Egypt J Pet</source><volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1050</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejpe.2018.03.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Basafa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hawboldt</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Reservoir souring: sulfur chemistry in offshore oil and gas reservoir fluids</article-title>. <source>J Petrol Explor Prod Technol</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1118</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13202-018-0528-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Strong</surname>
<given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gould</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kasinkas</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadowsky</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aksan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wackett</surname>
<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Biodegradation in waters from hydraulic fracturing: chemistry, microbiology, and engineering</article-title>. <source>J Environ Eng</source>
<volume>140</volume>:<fpage>B4013001</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>B4013008</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1061/(ASCE)EE.1943-7870.0000792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Magot</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ravot</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campaignolle</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ollivier</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>BKC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fardeau</surname>
<given-names>M-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crolet</surname>
<given-names>J-L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia</surname>
<given-names>J-L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1997</year>. <article-title>Dethiosulfovibrio peptidovorans gen. nov., sp. nov., a new anaerobic, slightly halophilic, thiosulfate-reducing bacterium from corroding offshore oil wells</article-title>. <source>Int J Syst Bacteriol</source>
<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>818</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>824</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-47-3-818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9226912</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grizzle</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duncan</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McInerney</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suflita</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Roles of thermophilic thiosulfate-reducing bacteria and methanogenic archaea in the biocorrosion of oil pipelines</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<elocation-id>89</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2014.00089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24639674</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cliffe</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nixon</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daly</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eden</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boothman</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkins</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wrighton</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lloyd</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Identification of persistent sulfidogenic bacteria in shale gas produced waters</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>286</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.00286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32153553</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ravot</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Magot</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ollivier</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>BKC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ageron</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grimont</surname>
<given-names>PAD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia</surname>
<given-names>J-L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1997</year>. <article-title>Haloanaerobium congolense sp. nov., an anaerobic, moderately halophilic, thiosulfate- and sulfur-reducing bacterium from an African oil field</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>
<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1997.tb10224.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9037768</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cooper</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCall</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stokes</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKay</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bentley</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenblum</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blewett</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miara</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Talmadge</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sitterley</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kurup</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stokes-Draut</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macknick</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borch</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cath</surname>
<given-names>TY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Katz</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Oil and gas produced water reuse: opportunities, treatment needs, and challenges</article-title>. <source>ACS EST Eng</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>366</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsestengg.1c00248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Keay</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Reilly</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mayer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valenciano</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richards</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>New life for old wells &#x02014; repurposing oil and gas well data for geothermal prospecting</article-title>. <conf-name>First international meeting for applied geoscience &#x00026; energy</conf-name>; <conf-loc>Denver, CO and virtual</conf-loc>: <comment>Vol</comment>. <volume>10</volume>, <comment>p</comment>
<fpage>3345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3348</lpage><publisher-name>OnePetro</publisher-name>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1190/segam2021-3595029.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Weather Spark</collab></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://weatherspark.com/y/4333/Average-Weather-in-Midland-Texas-United-States-Year-Round" ext-link-type="uri">https://weatherspark.com/y/4333/Average-Weather-in-Midland-Texas-United-States-Year-Round</ext-link>. <comment>Retrieved</comment>
<date-in-citation>13 Jun 2022</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Berdugo-Clavijo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scheffer</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gieg</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Biodegradation of polymers used in oil and gas operations: towards enzyme biotechnology development and field application</article-title>. <source>Polymers (Basel)</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/polym14091871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hashimoto</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shimamura</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tame</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sawayama</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyazaki</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Takai</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakagawa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Physiological and comparative proteomic characterization of Desulfolithobacter dissulfuricans gen. nov., sp. nov., a novel mesophilic, sulfur-disproportionating chemolithoautotroph from a deep-sea hydrothermal vent</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<elocation-id>1042116</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.1042116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36532468</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Booker</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoyt</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meulia</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eder</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicora</surname>
<given-names>CD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Purvine</surname>
<given-names>SO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daly</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wunch</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pfiffner</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lipton</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mouser</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wrighton</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilkins</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Deep-subsurface pressure stimulates metabolic plasticity in shale-colonizing Halanaerobium spp</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>85</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00018-19</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rabe</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nielsen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Engqvist</surname>
<given-names>MKM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Machine learning applied to predicting microorganism growth temperatures and enzyme catalytic optima</article-title>. <source>ACS Synth Biol</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1420</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acssynbio.9b00099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31117361</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nixon</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walker</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Streets</surname>
<given-names>MDT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eden</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boothman</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lloyd</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Guar gum stimulates biogenic sulfide production at elevated pressures: implications for shale gas extraction</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>679</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.00679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28469616</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Berdugo-Clavijo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seyyedi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quintero</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Neil</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gieg</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>High temperature utilization of PAM and HPAM by microbial communities enriched from oilfield produced water and activated sludge</article-title>. <source>AMB Express</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<elocation-id>46</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13568-019-0766-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30968201</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Scheffer</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Berdugo-Clavijo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gieg</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Enzyme biotechnology development for treating polymers in hydraulic fracturing operations</article-title>. <source>Microb Biotechnol</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>953</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>966</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.13727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33428324</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heaney</surname>
<given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reis</surname>
<given-names>FDAA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brantley</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Deep abiotic weathering of pyrite</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>370</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb8092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>TH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <part-title>Petrophysical characteristics of shale reservoirs</part-title>, <comment>p</comment>
<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. In <source>Transport in shale reservoirs</source>. <publisher-name>Gulf Professional publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tinker</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lipus</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gardiner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stuckman</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gulliver</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>The microbial community and functional potential in the Midland basin reveal a community dominated by both thiosulfate and sulfate-reducing microorganisms</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>e0004922</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/spectrum.00049-22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35695567</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hausmann</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knorr</surname>
<given-names>K-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schreck</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tringe</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Glavina Del Rio</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loy</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pester</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Consortia of low-abundance bacteria drive sulfate reduction-dependent degradation of fermentation products in peat soil microcosms</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2375</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2016.42</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27015005</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Valdez-Nu&#x000f1;ez</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayala-Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Espa&#x000f1;a</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Andrea</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2022</year>. <article-title>Microbial communities in peruvian acid mine drainages: low-abundance sulfate-reducing bacteria with high metabolic activity</article-title>. <source>Geomicrobiol J</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>867</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>883</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01490451.2022.2087808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pimenov</surname>
<given-names>NV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuranov</surname>
<given-names>GV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bryukhanov</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veslopolova</surname>
<given-names>EF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koryukina</surname>
<given-names>IP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maslov</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>The sulfate-reducing bacterial community of sulfide-rich water of the Ust&#x02019;-Kachka resort spring, Perm Krai, Russia</article-title>. <source>Microbiology (Reading, Engl)</source>
<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>726</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1134/S0026261712060112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>An</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voordouw</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Control of sulfide production in high salinity Bakken shale oil reservoirs by halophilic bacteria reducing nitrate to nitrite</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>1164</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28680423</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cline</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1969</year>. <article-title>Spectrophotometric determination of hydrogen sulfide in natural waters1</article-title>. <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>454</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>458</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4319/lo.1969.14.3.0454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cassella1</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Oliveira1</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santelli</surname>
<given-names>RE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1999</year>. <article-title>On line dissolution of ZnS for sulfide determination in stabilized water samples with zinc acetate, using spectrophotometry by methylene blue method</article-title>. <source>Spectrosc Lett</source>
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>484</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00387019909349999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Illumina</collab></person-group>. <year>2023</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.illumina.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.illumina.com</ext-link>. <comment>Retrieved</comment>
<date-in-citation>12 Jan 2022</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Project</collab></person-group>. <year>2023</year>. <article-title>The R project for statistical computing</article-title>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.r-project.org</ext-link>. <comment>Retrieved</comment>
<date-in-citation>12 Jan 2022</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>GraphPad Software</collab></person-group>. <year>2023</year>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.graphpad.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.graphpad.com</ext-link>. <comment>Retrieved</comment>
<date-in-citation>12 Jan 2022</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bushnell</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rood</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singer</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>BBMerge &#x02013; Accurate paired shotgun red merged via overlap</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<elocation-id>e0185056</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0185056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29073143</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>C-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sadakane</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>T-W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>MEGAHIT: an ultra-fast single-node solution for large and complex metagenomics assembly via succinct de Bruijn graph</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1674</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1676</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25609793</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Langmead</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salzberg</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>359</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Alneberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjarnason</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Bruijn</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schirmer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quick</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ijaz</surname>
<given-names>UZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lahti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loman</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Andersson</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Quince</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Binning metagenomic contigs by coverage and composition</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1146</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25218180</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y-W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>Y-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tringe</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simmons</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singer</surname>
<given-names>SW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>MaxBin: an automated binning method to recover individual genomes from metagenomes using an expectation-maximization algorithm</article-title>. <source>Microbiome</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2049-2618-2-26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25136443</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>DD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Froula</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Egan</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>MetaBAT, an efficient tool for accurately reconstructing single genomes from complex microbial communities</article-title>. <source>PeerJ</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<elocation-id>e1165</elocation-id>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26336640</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Parks</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Imelfort</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skennerton</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hugenholtz</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tyson</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>CheckM: assessing the quality of microbial genomes recovered from isolates, single cells, and metagenomes</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>
<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1055</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.186072.114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25977477</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chaumeil</surname>
<given-names>P-A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mussig</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hugenholtz</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parks</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>GTDB-Tk: a toolkit to classify genomes with the Genome Taxonomy Database</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>1925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1927</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31730192</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sieber</surname>
<given-names>CMK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Probst</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharrar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hess</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tringe</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banfield</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year>. <article-title>Recovery of genomes from metagenomes via a dereplication, aggregation and scoring strategy</article-title>. <source>Nat Microbiol</source>
<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>836</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>843</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41564-018-0171-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29807988</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shaffer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Borton</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McGivern</surname>
<given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zayed</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>La Rosa</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Solden</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Narrowe</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Ramos</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bolduc</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gazit&#x000fa;a</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daly</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vik</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pope</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sullivan</surname>
<given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roux</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wrighton</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>DRAM for distilling microbial metabolism to automate the curation of microbiome function</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>8883</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8900</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkaa621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32766782</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gruber-Vodicka</surname>
<given-names>HR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Seah</surname>
<given-names>BKB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pruesse</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>phyloFlash: rapid small-subunit rRNA profiling and targeted assembly from metagenomes</article-title>. <source>mSystems</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00920-20</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olm</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Banfield</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Measurement of bacterial replication rates in microbial communities</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1256</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1263</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.3704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27819664</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Huson</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richter</surname>
<given-names>DC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rausch</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dezulian</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Franz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rupp</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>Dendroscope: an interactive viewer for large phylogenetic trees</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>460</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>466</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-8-460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18034891</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>